<sect1 id="sect-bugs">
  <title>Overview</title>

  <para>
    &gnum; is a complex computer program
    and therefore necessarily contains some mistakes. The
    &gnum; team is keenly interested in
    finding these errors and correcting them. Suggestions for
    improvement are also welcome and can be submitted in the same
    fashion as an error report.
  </para>

  <para>
    <emphasis>
      Please, help us to fix any errors by telling us about them.
    </emphasis>
  </para>

  <para>
    Reports of problems with &gnum;
    provide the project with a way of making sure that the mistake is
    eventually fixed. Often the mistake is obvious and a fix can be
    made immediately to be included in the very next release of
    &gnum;. Occasionally, the mistake is
    more complex and the problem may take a while to be resolved. In
    these cases, the report provides a way to remind the developers that
    the problem still exists.
  </para>

  <note>
    <para>
      Mistakes in programs are often called "bugs" after one of the
      earliest errors in an old machine which was actually caused
      by an insect entering the machine and preventing a switch from
      closing.
    </para>
  </note>

  <para>
    The &gnum; project uses a world wide
    web system called <application>GitLab</application> to collect
    reports of program errors and then to track these errors until
    they are finally fixed. The system was developed as part of the
    <application>Mozilla</application> web browser project, which
    explains the origin of the strange name.
  </para>

  <para>
    The process of submitting the report of a problem or of a
    suggested enhancement is quite simple and can be completed in just
    a few steps. The process begins with obtaining a good
    understanding of the problem to be able to provide a detailed
    statement explaining the problem exactly. Next, the user must open
    an account with the GNOME project's
    <application>GitLab</application> system. Finally, the user must
    submit the statement of the problem, ideally, along with some
    information about the computer setup being used by the person
    experiencing the problem.
  </para>

  <para>
    The explanation given below should be sufficient to file a
    report. For more detailed
    instructions, the main page of GNOME's GitLab can be found at
    <ulink type="http" url="https://gitlab.gnome.org/GNOME">
      <uri>https://gitlab.gnome.org/GNOME</uri>
    </ulink> and instructions can be found at 
    <ulink type="http" url="https://handbook.gnome.org/issues/reporting.html">
      <uri>https://handbook.gnome.org/issues/reporting.html</uri>
    </ulink>.
  </para>

</sect1>


  <sect1 id="sect-bugs-understand">
    <title>Defining the error</title>

    <para>
      The most critical step is understanding the error as well as
      possible. This requires knowing clearly what was happening
      before the error occurred, what specifically caused the error to
      occur, what the error condition is and what happened as a
      consequence of the error.
    </para>

    <para>
      The most helpful situation to enable the developers to find and
      correct the error is to come up with a sequence of steps that
      generate the error. If the error can be repeated, it can almost
      always be corrected. The most helpful error reports include a
      small recipe that can cause the error to occur.
    </para>

  </sect1>




<sect1 id="sect-bugs-gitlab_account">
  <title>Opening an account</title>

    <para>
      The first time a user uses <application>Gitlab</application>,
      they must create an account. This account is needed to allow
      users to be informed of the status of the bug as it is tracked
      by the system from submission to resolution. The only
      requirement for opening a <application>Gitlab</application>
      account is the possession of a valid email address through which
      the user can receive a password.
    </para>

  <sect2 id="sect-bugs-gitlab_account-create">
    <title>Creating a new account</title>

    <para>
      Users of <application>Gitlab</application> are automatically
      redirected to a login page, unless they have previously logged
      into the system and accepted a 'cookie' with which they identify
      themselves. The login page has a link called "Create a new
      account" which will direct users to the account creation page.
    </para>

    <para>
      Alternatively, by clicking on this <ulink type="http"
      url="https://gitlab.com/users/sign_in#register-pane">link</ulink>,
      users can follow a shortcut directly to the account creation
      page.
    </para>

    <para>
      Creating a new account is very simple. The account creation page
      has two fields. In the first, a valid email account must be
      given. The second asks for a name by which the user wishes to be
      known. After a user fills out these two fields, clicking on the
      button labeled "Create Account" will cause a new account to be
      created and an email sent to the address given in the email
      field. The email will contain the password used to identify this
      user.
    </para>

  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sect-bugs-gitlab_account-login">
    <title>Logging into the account</title>

    <para>
      After creating an account, users can visit the bug entry
      <ulink type="http" 
      url="https://gitlab.gnome.org/GNOME/gnumeric/-/issues/new">page
      </ulink>
      for &gnum;. Here
      users are asked to login with their email address and
      password. After logging in, <application>GitLab</application>
      will present a page to add a bug report.
   </para>

   <note>
     <para>
       A user who accepts cookies from <literal>gitlab.gnome.org</literal>
       will only have to give a password the first time they visit
       GNOME's <application>GitLab</application>. During all future
       visits, GNOME will recognize the cookie and thereby identify
       the user.
     </para>
   </note>

 </sect2>

</sect1>




<sect1 id="sect-bugs-report">
  <title>Filing a report</title>

    <warning>
      <para>
        In order to file a report of a problem with
        &gnum;, a
        <application>GitLab</application> account is
        necessary. Please see the previous section, <xref
        linkend="sect-bugs-gitlab_account" />, for an explanation of
        how to open an account.
      </para>
    </warning>

    <para>
      The &gnum; bug entry page consists
      of several fields many of which must be filled out to provide a
      useful bug report. The most important of these will be the "Bug
      Description" which contains both the brief "Summary" field which
      acts like an email subject line and the detailed description
      field "Step to reproduce the bug" which should be used to give a
      more complete explanation of the problem and, ideally, to
      describe step by step how to reproduce the bug. The only other
      field which is required is the "Component" field which can be
      set to "General" and left to the developers to define more
      specifically. The remaining fields can be helpful, since they
      provide extra information which may help resolve the problem, but
      are not necessary. After filling out these three fields, a user
      can, if they desire, simply skip to the bottom and press the
      <guibutton>Commit</guibutton> button.
    </para>

  <sect2 id="sect-bugs-gitlab_access">
    <title>Accessing the GNOME project's GitLab</title>

    <para>
      There are several ways to file a bug report through
      <application>GitLab</application>.
    </para>

    <para>
       One of the entries in the <guimenu>Help</guimenu> menu is
      called <guimenuitem>Report a Problem</guimenuitem>. This menu
      entry should cause a browser window to launch and open
      <application>GitLab</application> to the
      &gnum; page.
    </para>

    <para>
      Alternatively, users can click on this <ulink type="http"
      url="https://gitlab.gnome.org/GNOME/gnumeric/-/issues/new">
      link</ulink> to access the &gnum;
      page in <application>Gitlab</application>.
    </para>

    <para>
      If neither of those shortcuts work, the user must use a web
      browser to access the following location:
<screen>https://gitlab.gnome.org/GNOME/gnumeric/-/issues/new
</screen>
      The simplest way would be to use the mouse to copy the text and
      paste that text into the location bar of a web browser.
    </para>

    <para>
      The user may be asked to login, by giving their account name and
      their password, when they begin their browser session with
      <application>GitLab</application>. See <xref
      linkend="sect-bugs-gitlab_account-login" /> for an explanation
      of how to login to <application>GitLab</application>.
    </para>

  </sect2>


    <sect2 id="sect-bugs-report-description">
      <title>The Bug Description</title>

      <para>
        A useful error report will include a subject that describes
        the error concisely, has a brief introduction which explains
        in greater detail what happened and, ideally, has a small
        recipe that leads to the error being repeated.
      </para>

      <para>
        The summary field, like the subject of an email message,
        briefly describes the problem. For example, a useful error
        report might have a summary "Gnumeric crashes when saving a
        file".
      </para>

      <para>
        The field titled "Steps to reproduce the bug" should contain a
        slightly expanded version of the summary giving an overview of
        the problem and then give a step-by-step example of how to
        reproduce the problem. For example, this field could look like
        the following: 
<screen> 
This report describes an error which causes Gnumeric to crash
during the use of the file save dialog.

1) Start a new Gnumeric
2) In Cell A1 type "hello"
3) From the "File" menu, select "Save As"
=> The "Save As dialog" opens up
4) In the file name box, type "my_spreadsheet.gnumeric"
5) Click on the "Save" button
=> I expected the file to be saved, and to be able to keep
working but instead Gnumeric disappeared and the file was 
never saved.

thanks, 
a user
</screen>
       </para>

    </sect2>




  <sect2 id="sect-bugs-report-product">
    <title>Product and Component</title>

    <para>
      The <emphasis>Product</emphasis> should be set to
      &gnum; since the GNOME version of
      <application>GitLab</application> is used for all the different
      programs in the project.
    </para>

    <para>
      The <emphasis>Component</emphasis> describes the part of
      &gnum; that causes the
      problem. This may not be obvious so, unless one of the other
      entries clearly matches, the component should be set to
      "General". The possible components for
      &gnum; are as follows.
    </para>

<table frame='all'><title>Components of Gnumeric</title>
<tgroup cols='2' align='left' colsep='1' rowsep='1'>

<thead>
<row>
  <entry align="center">Component</entry>
  <entry align="center">Explanation</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
  <entry>Analytics</entry>
  <entry>Problems with calculations and other mathematics.</entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry>Charting</entry>
  <entry>Problems with graphical plots of worksheet data.</entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry>Compilation</entry>
  <entry>Problems encountered during source code compilation.</entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry>Database plugin</entry>
  <entry>Problems when using a database from
  &gnum;.</entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry>Documentation</entry>
  <entry>Problems with this manual, with the explanations of
  functions, or with any other explanations.</entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry>General</entry>
  <entry><emphasis>The Default.</emphasis> Use this when none of the other
  categories apply.</entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry>GUI</entry>
  <entry>Problems with the graphical user interface.</entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry>GUI Expression Entry Widget</entry>
  <entry>Problems while entering or editing cell contents.</entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry>import/export Applix</entry>
  <entry>Problems opening or saving a file to the file format used by
  the Applix spreadsheet.</entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry>import/export HTML</entry>
  <entry>Problems opening or saving a file to the HTML or LaTeX file
  formats.</entry> 
</row>
<row>
  <entry>import/export MS Excel (tm)</entry>
  <entry>Problems opening or saving a file to any of the various file
  formats used by the Microsoft Excel spreadsheet.</entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry>import/export OOo / OASIS</entry>
  <entry>Problems opening or saving a file to the OASIS file format
  used by OpenOffice.Org Calc or Star Office Calc.</entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry>import/export Text</entry>
  <entry>Problems opening or saving a file to a text file format
  including tab, comma and space delimited files.</entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry>Installation</entry>
  <entry>Problems encountered during
  &gnum; installation.</entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry>Main System</entry>
  <entry>This component is no longer used.</entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry>Printing</entry>
  <entry>Problems encountered when printing a worksheet.</entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry>Sheet Objects</entry>
  <entry>Problems with any images, widgets, or drawing elements added
  to a worksheet.</entry> 
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>


  </sect2>



    <sect2 id="sect-bugs-report-severity">
      <title>The Severity and Priority of the Problem</title>

      <para>
        The severity level indicates the seriousness of the problem
        and the priority level indicates the desire of the developers
        to address the bug. These fields are used mostly by the
        developers and should both be left as "normal" unless the user
        has a good reason to change them.
      </para>

      <para>
        There are two cases when the user should change the severity
	of the report. In the first case, if the user has a problem
	which causes &gnum; to crash (to
	suddenly disappear or stop working) or a problem in which data
	is lost, the severity should be set to "critical". In the
	second case, if the user has a report about a desired feature,
	the severity should be set to "enhancement" so the developers
	will know right away that the desired functionality has not
	yet been added to the program.
      </para>

      <para>
        The problem severity levels are explained below.
      </para>

<table frame='all'><title>Problem Severity</title>
<tgroup cols='2' align='left' colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
<thead>
<row>
  <entry align="center">Severity Level</entry>
  <entry align="center">Explanation</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
  <entry>blocker</entry>
  <entry>The level used to indicate a problem which must be fixed
  before any next release.</entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry>critical</entry>
  <entry>The level used to indicate a very important problem such as a
  program crash or loss of data.</entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry>major</entry>
  <entry>The level used to indicate a severe problem but one that does
  not cause a crash or loss of data.</entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry>normal</entry>
  <entry>The level to use by default and used for the majority of
  reports.</entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry>minor</entry>
  <entry>The level used for problems which do not affect the
  functioning of the program.</entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry>trivial</entry>
  <entry>The level used to report typos, aesthetic, and other very
  small problems.</entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry>enhancement</entry>
  <entry>These are reports which are requests for future improvements
  of the program.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>

      <para>
        The priority level should be left at the "normal" level since this
        is a field used by the developers themselves.
      </para>

    </sect2>




    <sect2 id="sect-bugs-report-version">
      <title>The Version of Gnumeric and GNOME</title>

      <para>
        The version field is used to indicate the version of
	&gnum; which was used when the
	problem occurred. If the problem occurs with several versions,
	the most recent version number should be used. The version
	number can be obtained by opening the <interface>"About
	Gnumeric"</interface> dialog using the <guimenu>Help</guimenu>
	menu and the <guimenuitem>About</guimenuitem> menu item.
      </para>

      <para>
        The "GIT" version refers to a version which the user has
        recently obtained from the Git revision control
        repository provided by the GNOME project.
      </para>

      <para>
        The "Other version details" text box can be used to describe
        any unusual characteristics of the program such as plugins
        which were added or other uncommon modifications.
      </para>

      <para>
        If &gnum; is being used with a
        GNOME desktop, the version of GNOME being used can be entered
        in the "Gnome Version" field.
      </para>

    </sect2>



    <sect2 id="sect-bugs-report-os">
      <title>The Type of Operating System and Distribution</title>

      <para>
        The "Operating System" field can be used to describe the
	underlying operating system being used to run the
	&gnum; program. Please note, that
	if the program is run in an artificial environment such as a
	virtual machine or a Cygwin setup, this should be indicated in
	the next field.
      </para>

      <para>
        The "Distribution/Version" field should be used to add detail
        to the operating system described earlier.
      </para>

    </sect2>






    <sect2 id="sect-bugs-report-other">
      <title>Other fields and keywords</title>

     <para>
        These fields are used by advanced users to better sort through
        all the reports. The "Keywords" field is used to relate the
        reports to each other and the "CC" field is used by those who
        are interested to add themselves to those who are notified
        when changes are made to the report.
      </para>

    </sect2>


    <sect2 id="sect-bugs-report-commit">
      <title>Submitting the report</title>

      <para>
        In order to submit the bug report into
        <application>GitLab</application>, once all of the important
        fields have been submitted, simply click on the
        <guibutton>Commit</guibutton> button.
      </para>

      <para>
        Once the bug is committed, a bug report number for this bug
        will be assigned, and email will be sent either the
        project maintainer or to one of the other developers which
        deal specifically with that component of the program. When
        others take an interest in the bug and add comments or
        solutions, email will be sent out to the user to inform them
        of the status of the bug until it is either dismissed or
        resolved. Bugs can be dismissed if they describe a behaviour
        that is expected or if they are not deemed important enough to
        fix. 
      </para>

      <note>
        <para>
	  A user can choose not to be notified when changes to reports
	  are submitted. The user preference page can be accessed <ulink
	  type="http"
	  url="https://gitlab.gnome.org/profile/notifications">here</ulink> at the
	  following URL.
<screen>https://gitlab.gnome.org/profile/notifications
</screen>
       </para>
     </note>

    </sect2>




    <sect2 id="sect-bugs-report-template">
      <title>Bookmarking a template</title>

      <para>
        A version of the bug entry page with most of the fields
        already filled out can be saved as a link and bookmarked for
        future use. This ability is only of use for developers or for
        users who have found a large number of bugs in one particular
        component of &gnum;.
      </para>

      <para>
        To use this shortcut, first open a new bug report, then fill
        out only the fields that will apply to all the future bugs
        being reported and then click on the button labelled "Bookmark
        these values". <application>GitLab</application> will then
        construct a template and will provide a link which can be
        saved for future use just as any other page on the web can be
        saved as a bookmark. To use these values, simply clicking on
        the bookmark will open the &gnum;
        page of <application>GitLab</application> with the common
        fields already filled out.
      </para>

    </sect2>


</sect1>

