<sect1 id="strings-and-numbers">
  <title>Strings and numbers</title>
  
  <para>
    There are four basic types of data that can be entered into cells.
    They are:
    <variablelist>
       <varlistentry>
         <term>Strings</term>
         <listitem>
           <para>
              A string is any set of letters, or of letters and
              numbers. The only limitations are that strings cannot
              contain newlines.  Put a single quote before strings
              beginning with a single quote and and an @ sign, +, -,
              or =. See <xref
              linkend="stringnumber" /> for an example of entering a
              string.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
           <varlistentry>
         <term>Numbers</term>
         <listitem>
           <para>
              Numbers can be formatted as money, ($10.00), dates (11
              Nov. 2002), or scientific notation (2.3e12). If you want
              a number to be displayed as a plain string without any
              number formatting, you can put a single quote (') before
              it.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

           <varlistentry>
         <term>Formulas</term>
         <listitem>
           <para>Formulas are ways of describing a calculation you
           want Gnumeric to make automatically.  Formulas always begin
           with a special character, which is usually the equals sign
           (=). You may also use the at symbol (@) or the plus or
           minus symbols (+ or -).
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

           <varlistentry>
         <term>Cell References</term>
         <listitem>
           <para>
           A cell reference is the part of a formula which refers to
           another cell.  For example, in the formula to add two cells
           =(A4+A1), both A4 and A1 are cell references. 
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </para>
  
  <figure id="stringnumber">
    <title>Entering strings and numbers.</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
	<imagedata fileref="figures/editing-1.png" format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

<sect2 id="entering-dates-and-numbers">
  <title>Dates and Numbers</title>

  <para>
    When you begin entering a number,
    <application>Gnumeric</application> will attempt to match the data
    you enter with existing formats for numbered data. If it matches a
    data format, <application>Gnumeric</application> will
    automatically convert the entered data into the appropriate serial
    number, displaying it in an appropriate format.
  </para>

  <para>
    Because of the format matching ability, user-entered data can be
    autofilled (see <xref linkend="autofill" /> for more information)
    properly. </para>

  <para>See <xref linkend="number-format-date-examples" /> for some examples of 
	the many date and time formats that are accepted by
	<application>Gnumeric</application>. </para>

  </sect2>

 <sect2 id="editing-of-cells">
    <title>Editing of cells.</title>
    
    <procedure>
      <title>Entering data in a cell</title>
      <step>
        <para>Select the cell where you want to enter data by clicking
         on it with the white cross cursor.
  </para></step>
      <step>
        <para>Type in the data or formula.</para></step>

      <step>
        <para>Press Enter.</para></step>
    </procedure>
 
    <para>
      See <xref linkend="formulas" /> for more detail on entering formulas into cells.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="editing-commands">
    <title>Editing commands</title>
    
    <para>After selecting the cell and initially entering the data, the user is in
      a limited editing mode, designed to aid in entering data which may contain
      cell references. The main keys for editing mistakes in this mode is the backspace
      key.</para>
    
    <sect3 id="advanced-editing-mode">
      <title>Advanced Editing mode</title>
      
      <para>For a more complete set of editing options, especially for
	longer entries, there is an advanced editing mode.  To enter
	the advanced editing mode, press <keycap>F2</keycap>. The
	keyboard focus will then shift from the current cell to the
	editing region at the top of the worksheet. There, you can use
	cursor keys to position the cursor within the data in the
	cell, and have all of the capabilities of the data entry area
	available. 
 </para>
 <para>
    For example, you can use:      
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><keycap>Backspace</keycap></term>
	  <listitem><para>Delete the character to the left of the cursor.</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><keycap>Cursor keys</keycap></term>
	  <listitem><para>Move the cursor appropriately.</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><keycap>Ctrl+K</keycap></term>
	  <listitem><para>Delete to the end of the line</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
       See <xref linkend="data-entry" /> For more info on
	the data entry area.</para>

      <tip>
        <title>TIP</title> <para>All the normal key bindings for Gnome
	application entry boxes also apply in the data entry
	box.</para>
      </tip>
    </sect3>
    
    <sect3 id="error-message">
      <title>Error Messages</title>

      <para>If a formula or set of data is not acceptable, Gnumeric
	will display an error message in the cell.</para>
    </sect3>
  </sect2>
</sect1>

<!--  include the files for formulas and for cell referencing -->

&formulas;

&cellrefer;

<sect1 id="selecting-cells-entering-formulas">
  <title>Selecting Cells While Entering Formulas.</title>

  <para>When entering a formula into a cell, you can use the mouse and
    the keyboard cursor keys enter data more quickly.</para>

  <para>There are several ways to enter a cell range into a formula. Cell
    ranges and references can be entered into a formula simply by typing in
    the proper syntax (see <xref linkend="cell-referencing" /> for more details).
    But manually entering in cell ranges is slow and cumbersome. </para>

  <para>When entering data into a cell, and the cursor is at a point
    where a cell reference is appropriate, it is possible to define a cell
    reference by selecting a cell via the mouse or keyboard. This selection
    is a little different from the ordinary selection. It is highlighted
    by a "marching ants" border. </para>

  <figure id="editing-cell-selection">
    <title>The highlighted selection</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
	<imagedata fileref="figures/editing-cell-selection-1.png"
      format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  
  <sect2 id="entering-data-formula-mouse">
    <title>Entering data into a formula with the mouse</title>
<para>
To make a cell reference using the mouse:
</para>
    <procedure>
      <title>Using the mouse to enter a cell reference into a formula</title>
      <step>
	<para>
          Begin entering a formula as you would normally. Stop at the
	  point where a cell reference is appropriate. For example,
	  example, type <userinput>=exp(</userinput>
	</para>
	</step>
      <step>
	<para>
	  Click on the cell you want to reference. Its reference will
	  be entered into the formula.
	</para>
      </step>
      <step>
	<para>
	  To finish the formula, just type in the closing parenthesis. This will
	  also "unselect" the region.
	</para>
      </step>
    </procedure>
    
    <para>This can be used to select a range of cells just like regular selections. </para>
    
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="entering-data-formula-keyboard">
    <title>Entering data into a formula with the keyboard.</title>

    <para>If entering lots of formulas or even just entering a few formulas, it is
      often quickest to use the keyboard to select cells and ranges of cells for use
      in formulas. Just as reaching a input point allows the user to select cells 
      with the mouse, it is possible to use the keyboard to select cells. Just use 
      the cursor keys and selection modifiers to create a selection.</para>

    <procedure>
      <title>Using the keyboard to enter data into a formula.</title>

      <step>
	<para>
	  Select a cell to enter a formula into. For example A1.
	</para>
      </step>
      <step>
	<para>Enter a formula, but stop the cursor at a point
	  where a cell reference is appropriate. For this example,
	  =SUM( 
	</para>
      </step>
      <step>
	<para>
	  Move the selection around with the cursor keys. Move the selection
	  cursor to cell B1 to start the selection.
	</para>
      </step>
      <step>
	<para>
	  Hold down <keycap>Shift</keycap> and move the selection one cell
	over and one cell down. Cells B1,B2,C1,C2 should now be selected and
	the formula should show =sum(B1:C2 
	</para>
      </step>
      <step>
	<para>
	  To finish the function, close the parenthesis. The cell should
	  now show =sum(B1:C2). Press enter and the formula is entered.
	</para>
      </step>
    </procedure>

    <para>To select a range of cell, hold <keycap>Shift</keycap> and  move over the desired area.</para>

    <para>To stop entering a selection or to start over, press <keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap>
	<keycap>Backspace</keycap></keycombo></para>

    </sect2>
</sect1>	  

  <!-- include the files for handling selections -->
  
   &selections; 
