<sect1 id="fill-series">
  <title>Fill Series</title>

 <para>Fill series tool can substatially speed up the filling of
  related values into a sheet. The tool is able to fill cells
  according to a linear or exponential serie. In addition, dates
  having certain intervals can be filled automatically using the
  tool. For example, series like 2, 5, 8, 11, ..., or, 2, 4, 8, 16,
  ..., or, Jan 1st 2003, Jan 3rd 2003, Jan 5th 2003, ..., can be
  automatically filled into a sheet by using the tool.</para>

  <sect2 id="fill-series-basic">
    <title>Filling Linear and Growth (Exponential) Series</title>

    <para>Each serie has to have an initial first value and a step
     value. In linear series, the next value is generated using the
     formula `V(n+1) := V(n) + step', where V(n) is the previous value in
     the serie.  In growth series, the next value is generated using the
     formula `V(n+1) := V(n) * step'.</para>

    <para>In order to use the tool, set an initial value into the first
     cell of a serie.  Then paint a column or a row area so that the
     first cell in the selection contains the initial value.  Now select
     the ``Fill'' menu item in ``Edit'' menu, and then select
     ``Series...'' in the popup submenu.</para>

    <para>If you painted a column, select ``Columns'' in ``Series in''
     frame. Otherwise, let the default setting be ``Rows''.  Then type
     the ``Step Value'' into the corresponding entry box.  As described
     already, there are two types of series that the tool supports:
     linear and growth (exponential) series. Select the one you want to
     use by checking the corresponding radio button on. If you want to
     stop filling after certain limit is reached, you can also specify the
     ``Stop Value'' in the corresponding entry box.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="fill-series-dates">
    <title>Filling Date Series</title>

    <para>In order to fill dates, set an initial date into the first
    cell and then select a row or a column to be filled, and start the
    tool just like in the case of a linear serie filling. But in this
    case, now select ``Date'' button in the ``Type'' frame in order to
    make the ``Date unit'' frame sensitive for user input. In the
    ``Date unit'' frame you can select the date unit to be stepped in
    each step. Date unit can be a day, a weekday (weekends are
    skipped), a month, or a year.  For example, if you select
    ``Weekday'' the tool steps in each iteration the number of working
    days specified in the ``Step Value'' entry.</para>

  </sect2>
</sect1>

  <!-- Keep this comment at the end of the file
  Local variables:
  mode: sgml
  sgml-omittag:t
  sgml-shorttag:t
  sgml-minimize-attributes:nil
  sgml-always-quote-attributes:t
  sgml-indent-step:2
  sgml-indent-data:t
  sgml-parent-document:nil
  sgml-exposed-tags:nil
  sgml-local-catalogs:nil
  sgml-local-ecat-files:nil
  End:
  -->             
