<sect1 id="sect-gui-menus">
  <title>Menus</title>

<!-- TODO: add explanation of how to use a menu. -->
<!-- TODO: go over sub-menus and treat consistently. -->
<!-- TODO: add xref to each menu entry for other section of the manual. -->

  <para>
    This section of the manual describes the use of the menubar and
    the menus themselves. The rest of <xref linkend="sect-gui-menus"
    /> then explains each entry in every
    &gnum; menu, submenu or context menu.
  </para>

  <para>
    A menu is a graphical element within a program which appears with
    a list of options. For instance, almost all applications have a
    <guimenu>File</guimenu> menu through which the user can access the
    computer's filesystem to open or save their work. The main menus
    are on the menubar. The use of these menus is discussed in <xref
    linkend="menu-bars" />.
  </para>

  <para>
    &gnum; also uses context menus to
    give users a quick way to access certain commands. The context
    menu will open up right under the mouse pointer when one of the
    secondary mouse buttons, usually the rightmost, is clicked. This
    menu is called a context menu because the entries in the menu are
    different depending on the location of the mouse pointer. The
    <guilabel>context</guilabel> menus are discussed in <xref
    linkend="context-menu" />.
  </para>

  <para>
    Both the main menus, on the menubar, and context menus may have
    sub-menus. Sub-menus are indicated by a small right pointing
    arrow. To access the sub-menus, the user must move the pointer
    down to the sub-menu entry and carefully across to the position of
    the little arrow. After an instant the sub-menu will open up and
    the user must carefully move the pointer directly across into the
    sub-menu. Occasionally, when there is not enough room to the right
    of the currently open menu, sub-menus may open to the
    left. Navigating sub-menus can be difficult since the menu will
    close if the mouse pointer moves into any other menu entry.
  </para>

  <para>
    Menu entries which are followed by an ellipsis (three dots)
    indicate that this entry will open a dialog window which will ask
    the user for more choices.
  </para>
	

  <sect2 id="menu-bars">
    <title>The Menubar</title>    

    <para>
      The default location of the menubar is at the top of the
      application window.  The menus provide quick and organized access
      to all major commands such as opening files, saving files,
      printing and quitting the application.
    </para>

    <figure id="menubar.png">
    <title>The Gnumeric menubar.</title>
    <screenshot>
      <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/menubar.png" />
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>An image of the Gnumeric menubar.</phrase>
            </textobject>
           </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
    </figure>


    <para>
      &gnum; menus are opened with a
      simple click on the name of the menu in the menu bar. Once
      clicked, the menu will stay open. If the mouse pointer is
      dragged over the name of another menu on the menubar, the first
      menu will close and the new menu open up. This is a useful way
      to look in each menu to hunt for a commands. Menus can also be
      opened through the keyboard. One of the letters in each menu is
      underlined. Typing the <keycap>Alt</keycap> key at the same time
      as the underlined letter key will open the menu. This is also
      true of sub-menus. Once the menus are open, the arrow keys can
      be used to move between menus or select an entry in a particular
      menu. An open menu can be closed with a click over any other
      area of the application or of the desktop. The menus can also be
      closed by typing the escape key, <keysym>Esc</keysym>.
    </para>

    <para>
      Many menu entries are followed by a series of keynames. These
      keys can be used to perform the menu action without having to
      open the menu.  These are often combinations of keys involving
      the control key which is labeled as <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>, the
      shift key which is labeled <keycap>Shift</keycap> and the
      function keys which are labeled with an <keycap>F</keycap> and
      then a number. For example, to quickly cut a selection
      (accessible through the <guimenu>Edit</guimenu> menu), the user
      can make a selection and then type the control key and the "x"
      key at the same time.
    </para>

  </sect2>




  <!-- ************************  FILE MENU   *************************** -->
  <sect2 id="File-Menu">
    <title>The File Menu</title>

    <para>
      The <guimenu>File</guimenu> menu is the most important menu in
      &gnum; because it gives the user
      the ability to interact with the computer operating system. This
      menu allows the user to create files containing all the work
      they have done. It also enables users to print the results of
      their work. Finally, the <guimenu>File</guimenu> menu is the
      best way to close &gnum;.
    </para>

    <figure id="menu-file-labelled.png">
      <title>The <guimenu>File</guimenu> menu.</title>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/menu-file-labelled.png" />
          </imageobject>
          <textobject>
            <phrase>An image of the File menu.</phrase>
          </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>

    <para>
      The menu choices are grouped into the following groups:
    </para>


    <para>
      <variablelist>

      <varlistentry>
	<term>
	  <emphasis role="bold">1</emphasis>
	    Workbook creation operations.
	</term>

	<listitem>
	  <para>These menu items perform operations on files. Each item is
	  presented below. File operations are critical and are therefore
	  discussed in their own section latter in this manual in <xref
	  linkend="chapter-files" />. </para>
	 <itemizedlist>

      	    <listitem>
     	      <para>
     	        <guimenuitem>New</guimenuitem> &mdash; Create a new
                workbook. This opens a new workbook in a new
                window. By default the workbook will be named "Book1"
                or another number if there is already a worksheet with
                that name open. Note that the opened file has not yet
                been saved.
     	      </para>
     	    </listitem>

      	    <listitem>
     	      <para>
     	        <guimenuitem>New From Template</guimenuitem> &mdash; This 
                menu item brings up a submenu from which a template can be selected.
                Rather than creating a new empty workbook, the template 
                specifies some standard content. The new workbook is opened in a new
                window. The name named of the workbook is determined by the name
                of the template. Note that the opened file has not yet
                been saved.
     	      </para>
     	    </listitem>

     	    <listitem>
     	      <para>
     	        <guimenuitem>Open</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
	        <guimenuitem>Open</guimenuitem> menu item opens the
	        file chooser dialog to allow the user to pick an
	        existing workbook for Gnumeric to open. Files in many
	        different formats can be opened, see <xref
	        linkend="sect-file-formats" /> for details.  The
	        <guimenuitem>Open</guimenuitem> menu item creates a
	        new window containing the selected file.  A more
	        extensive discussion is presented in <xref
	        linkend="sect-file-open" />.
      	      </para>
     	    </listitem>

          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
	<term>
	  <emphasis role="bold">2</emphasis>
	    File creation operations.
	</term>
	<listitem>
	  <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <guimenuitem>Save</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
		<guimenuitem>Save</guimenuitem> menu item saves the
		current worksheet. If the file has been named and
		saved before, this will silently save the file to the
		current filename. If it has not been saved before,
		this will act as if the <guimenuitem>Save
		As...</guimenuitem> menu item had been called and
		prompt the user for a filename.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <guimenuitem>Save As...</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
		<guimenuitem>Save As...</guimenuitem> menu item allows
		users to save a file which has not yet been named to a
		named file. This is always used when a user saves a
		file which Gnumeric has named by default.  This menu
		item can also be used to save a newly created file or
		to save an existing file to a new and different
		name. For an explanation of the file formats which
		gnumeric supports see <xref linkend="sect-file-save"
		/>.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
	<term>
	  <emphasis role="bold">3</emphasis>
	    Printing operations.
	</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    These menu items enable
	    &gnum; to print. Each item is
	    presented below and printing issues are discussed fully in
	    <xref linkend="chapter-printing" />.
          </para>
	  
	 <itemizedlist>
 	    <listitem>
	      <para>
 	        <guimenuitem>Page Setup...</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
                <guimenuitem>Page Setup...</guimenuitem> menu item
                call the <guilabel>Page Setup</guilabel> dialog. This
                dialog allows the user to set various printing options
                such as paper type, margin sizes and running header
                and footer formats. This dialog is explained in detail
                in <xref linkend="sect-printing-setup" />.
  	       </para>
  	      </listitem>

 	    <listitem>
	      <para>
 	        <guimenuitem>Print Area</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
                <guimenuitem>Print Area</guimenuitem> menu item
                opens the submenu shown in <xref linkend="menu-file-printarea.png" />.
                The items in this submenu allow the print area to be set, 
                shown or cleared. The print area of a sheet is that range 
                of the sheet that should be printed. Items outside of the
                print area are usually omitted when printing.
  	       </para>
    <figure id="menu-file-printarea.png">
      <title>The <guimenu>Print Area</guimenu> submenu.</title>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/menu-file-printarea.png" />
          </imageobject>
          <textobject>
            <phrase>An image of the Print Area submenu.</phrase>
          </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>
  	      </listitem>
  	      <listitem>
   	      <para>
   	        <guimenuitem>Print...</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
		<guimenuitem>Print...</guimenuitem> menu item allows a
		user to print one or all of the worksheets in a
		workbook. Gnumeric can send files directly to a
		printer or can print to postscript or portable
		document format files. The <guilabel>Print</guilabel>
		dialog is explained further in <xref
		linkend="sect-printing" />.
         </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para>
                <guimenuitem>Print Preview...</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
		<guimenuitem>Print Preview...</guimenuitem> menu item
		calls a dialog which presents the current workbook as
		it would be printed with the current <guilabel>Page
		Setup</guilabel> settings. The dialog also permits the
		user to print. This dialog is explained in <xref
		linkend="sect-printing-preview" />.
         </para>
        </listitem>

		   
		</itemizedlist>
		
      </listitem>


	
      </varlistentry>



	<!-- summary -->
      <varlistentry>
		<term>
		  <emphasis role="bold">4</emphasis>
	  Miscellaneous Operations.
	</term>
	<listitem>
	 <itemizedlist>
 	   <listitem>
	      <para>

 	         <guimenuitem>Send To...</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
	         <guimenuitem>Send To...</guimenuitem> menu item call
	         the <guilabel>Send To</guilabel> dialog. This dialog
	         allows the user to send a &gnum; workbook as an
	         attachment to an email message. This dialog is
	         explained in detail in <xref
	         linkend="sect-files-email" />.
	  </para> 
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	  <para>
	    <guimenuitem>Document Properties...</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
	    <guimenuitem>Document Properties...</guimenuitem> menu item calls
	    the <guilabel>Document Properties</guilabel> dialog, a 
        dialog with several tabs that allow many document specific
        settings to be adjusted. The dialog is described in detail in
        <xref linkend="chapter-workbooks" />.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	 </itemizedlist>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>

	<!-- recent files -->
      <varlistentry>
	<term>
          <emphasis role="bold">5</emphasis>
	  Recently used files.
	</term>
	<listitem>
        <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    The first three menu entries in this section are shortcuts to 
        re-open recently used
	    files.  The list will change dynamically as new workbooks
	    are opened and created.  Clicking on a file name listed
	    here is the same as using the
	    <guimenuitem>Open</guimenuitem> menu entry and finding the
	    file in the <guilabel>Find File</guilabel> dialog. Note
	    that if the file has been moved since
	    &gnum; last saved it,
	    &gnum; will not find the
	    file. To access any recent file not listed, one can use the the
	    <guimenuitem>Full History...</guimenuitem> menu item below.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	  <listitem>
	  <para>
	    <guimenuitem>Full History...</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
	    <guimenuitem>Full History...</guimenuitem> menu item opens a dialog
        that shows all recently used files.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	 </itemizedlist>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      
      
      <varlistentry>
	<term>
          <emphasis role="bold">6</emphasis>
          The Close and Quit operations.
	</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    These menu items either close the current worksheet,
	    <guimenuitem>Close</guimenuitem>, or close all open
	    worksheets, <guimenuitem>Quit</guimenuitem>. Gnumeric will
	    prompt the user with a <guilabel>Save
	    Workbook..</guilabel> dialog for any workbooks that have
	    been changed since the last time they were opened or
	    saved.
	  </para>
	  
	  <itemizedlist>
      	    <listitem>
     	      <para>
     	       <guimenuitem>Close</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
	       <guimenuitem>Close</guimenuitem> menu item allows the
	       user to close the current workbook. If this is the only
	       workbook which this instance of
	       &gnum; has open, the close
	       operation will also quit
	       &gnum;. If other workbooks
	       are open, this workbook will close without affecting
	       the others.  If the workbook has unsaved changes,
	       &gnum; will ask the user
	       if he wants to save the file.
     	      </para>
     	   </listitem>

      	    <listitem>
     	      <para>

     	       <guimenuitem>Quit</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
	       <guimenuitem>Quit</guimenuitem> menu item will close
	       all the workbooks currently being used by
	       &gnum; and quit the
	       program. &gnum; will
	       prompt the user asking if he wants to save any
	       workbooks which has changes which have not been saved.

     	      </para>
     	   </listitem>
		   
		</itemizedlist> 
	  </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
	  
      </variablelist>
    </para>		

  </sect2>


  <!--  ******************************** EDIT MENU    ******************** -->
  <sect2 id="Edit-Menu">
    <title>The Edit Menu</title>

    <para>
      The <guimenu>Edit</guimenu> menu is mostly used for operations
      on a worksheet or between worksheets. This menu gives users
      powerful editing operations such as the ability to undo recent
      changes, the ability to cut and paste selections of cells and
      the ability to search for specific cell contents.
    </para>
		
    <figure id="menu-edit-labelled.png">
		    <title>The <guimenu>Edit</guimenu> menu.</title>
		    <screenshot>
		      <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/menu-edit-labelled.png" />
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>An image of the Edit menu.</phrase>
            </textobject>
           </mediaobject>
		    </screenshot>
    </figure>

    <para>
      The menu choices are grouped into the following groups:
    </para>



  <variablelist>
    
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
        <emphasis role="bold">1</emphasis>
	  Change History.
      </term>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  These menu items allow the user to remove recent changes to
	  a worksheet or re-introduce changes which have been
	  undone. These options give the user control over recent
	  edits. This functionality is often called the "change
	  history" of an application. </para>
	
	<para>
	  The type of edit has no importance. An edit which deletes
	  the contents of a cell is treated in the same way as an edit
	  which adds contents to a cell. The change history is session
	  specific. The user will not be able to undo changes through
	  the change history if the file is saved and then
	  re-opened. Note also that the list only covers the last few
	  dozen operations. The number of operations which Gnumeric
	  tracks in its history depends on the size and complexity of
	  those operations. You can customize this number using the preference
	  facility described in <xref linkend="chapter-configuring" />. 
	  There are a few unusual operations which
	  are not yet tracked in this way.
	</para>
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <guimenuitem>Undo</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
	      <guimenuitem>Undo</guimenuitem> menu item is used to
	      remove the last few edits from a workbook. The edits
	      must be undone in order. This menu item removes only the
	      last edit from the workbook. The user can also access
	      the undo list through one of the toolbar buttons and its
	      associated menu.  With this menu, the user can undo
	      several operations at once. This is explained in section
	      <xref linkend="std-toolbar" />.  </para> </listitem>
	  
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <guimenuitem>Redo</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
	      <guimenuitem>Redo</guimenuitem> menu item is used after
	      an undo operation to restore the change that was undone.
	      The menu item only restores the last undone
	      operation. Users can also restore edit using a button on
	      the standard toolbar and through the associated
	      menu. The menu allows several operations to be redone at
	      once. It is explained in <xref linkend="std-toolbar" />.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    
    
    
    
    <!-- Cut, Copy, Paste, Paste Special... -->
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
	<emphasis role="bold">2</emphasis>
	  Operations on selected areas.
      </term>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	These menu items enable selected cell contents to be moved
	around a spreadsheet, moved between worksheets or between
	workbooks. Selections are areas of the spreadsheet that have
	been chosen, usually with the mouse, and are usually colored
	pale blue. Selections are explained in greater detail in <xref
	linkend="sect-data-selections" />.
	&gnum; currently only allows
	single range selections for these operations.
	</para>

	<para>
	  To use these menuitems, the user must first select the range
	  of the cut or copy area. When the user then picks these
	  menuitems, the contents of the selected areas will be
	  entered into the &gnum;
	  clipboard and into the X clipboard. The
	  contents of the &gnum;
	  clipboard can then be inserted into a new region of the
	  spreadsheet, into another worksheet or into a new
	  workbook. The X clipboard holds the space delimited results
	  of each cell: either the text or the result of any
	  calculation. The X clipboard can be pasted into any text
	  area.
	</para>

        <itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>

	    <para>
	      <guimenuitem>Cut</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
	      <guimenuitem>Cut</guimenuitem> menu item is used to
	      remove a selection from the selected area of a currently
	      open workbook. When the menu item is chosen, the
	      selected area will be outlined with a moving dotted
	      line. This is the area which will be moved. The
	      selection will only be removed after it is moved to the
	      new location. Until then cut has not had an effect on
	      the worksheet.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <guimenuitem>Copy</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
	      <guimenuitem>Copy</guimenuitem> menu item allows a user
	      to duplicate a selection. The original data remains
	      where it was and the &gnum;
	      clipboard (and the X clipboard) has a copy which can be
	      inserted elsewhere.

	    </para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <guimenuitem>Paste</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
	      <guimenuitem>Paste</guimenuitem> menu item is used to
	      paste the contents of a selection which has been cut or
	      copied. If the selection was cut, it is pasted into the
	      new location unchanged. Cell references will not change
	      in that they will still point to the same cells.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <guimenuitem>Paste Special...</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
	      <guimenuitem>Paste Special...</guimenuitem> is used to
	      paste a selection while altering certain
	      characteristics. The <guimenuitem>Paste
	      Special...</guimenuitem> menu item opens a dialog with
	      three categories. The defaults make <guimenuitem>Paste
	      Special...</guimenuitem> act as if it were the
	      <guimenuitem>Paste</guimenuitem> menu item.
	    </para>

    <figure id="menu-edit-paste-special.png">
		    <title>The Paste Special Dialog</title>
		    <screenshot>
		      <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/menu-edit-paste-special.png" />
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>An image of the Paste Special Dialog.</phrase>
            </textobject>
           </mediaobject>
		    </screenshot>
    </figure>



	    <para>
	      The first set of choices allow the user to control the
	      data pasted.The user can chose to limit the pasting to
	      only the cell contents (no cell formatting is copied) or ---
	      the opposite --- only cell formats copied (no
	      contents). Furthermore, the user can insert the
	      selection while transforming all the contents into
	      values only. In this case, formulas will not be copied, only the
	      results will be.
	    </para>
	    <para>
	      A second set of choices allows the user to perform
	      simple mathematical transformations during the
	      paste. The data in the cells being pasted into are
	      modified by the cell contents. For instance, using the
	      divide operation will result in each cell in the zone
	      pasted into being divided by the equivalent cell which
	      was copied originally.
	    </para>
	    <para>
	      The third set of choices allow the transposition or flip of the
	      original selection. The
	      <guilabel>transpose</guilabel> choice will change the
	      selection by flipping it about the diagonal from top left to 
	      bottom right. Similarly, <guilabel>flip horizontally</guilabel> and 
	      <guilabel>flip vertically</guilabel> paste the selection accordingly.
	    </para>
	    <para>The <guilabel>skip
	      blanks</guilabel> check box prevents
	      &gnum; from taking any
	      action for the cells in the selection that are
	      blank. Normally &gnum; will modify formulae that use relative 
	      addressing to cells outside the selection. The <guilabel>do not
	      change formulae</guilabel> checkbox suppresses this change. (Note that 
	      references to cells within the selection are always preserved.)
	    </para>
	  </listitem>

	</itemizedlist>
	  
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>


	<varlistentry>
		<term>
			<emphasis role="bold">3</emphasis>
			Data entry and removal operations.
		</term>
		<listitem>
			<para>These operations either add or remove data from the worksheet. They
			differ in the type of data removed and the re-arrangement of
			remaining data. The differences are explained below.
			</para>


			<itemizedlist>
      	    	<listitem>
     	      	<para>
     	       	<guimenuitem>Clear</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
			       <guimenuitem>clear</guimenuitem> menu item merely opens a
				   sub-menu with four choices. The user can choose to clear all
				   the elements of the cells in a selection: the formats, the
				   comments, the contents. Alternatively, the user can choose
				   to clear a single one of those elements. Clearing the formats
				   will leave the data or formula in the cell intact. It will
				   remove any borders, re-set the cell alignments, change the
				   background colour to white and the text colour to black and
				   reset the number format to <guilabel>General</guilabel>. Clearing the comments
				   will simply delete the comments for the cells in that
				   location. Finally clearing the contents will leave the
				   cell's formatting in place but remove the formula or data
				   contents of the cell.
				   </para>
     	   		</listitem>

      	    	<listitem>
     	      	<para>
     	       	<guimenuitem>Delete</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
			       <guimenuitem>delete</guimenuitem> menu item may open a dialog
				 giving the user a choice of options. Any of the options
				 will completely delete the selected cells. Depending on the
				 selection, &gnum; will fill in the space the cells
				 were occupying differently. With column or row selections,
				 the effect is easy to understand and no choice is possible
				 so &gnum; does not open the dialog. The space left by
				 selected rows, is filled by moving lower rows up
				 whereas the space filled by deleting columns is filled by
				 moving to the left columns which were right of the selection. 
				 For example, if columns D and E are selected for deletion,
				 &gnum; will move the contents of all columns from F
				 onwards two columns to the left.
				 </para>
				 <para>
				 With blocks of cells, the <guimenuitem>delete</guimenuitem> 
				 menu item will open a dialog asking the user how to fill in the
				 deleted cells. Blocks of cells will either be filled in by the
				 columns of cells below the block selection or by the rows on 
				 the right of the block. 
				 </para>

    <figure id="menu-edit-delete-cells.png">
		    <title>The Delete Cells Dialog</title>
		    <screenshot>
		      <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/menu-edit-delete-cells.png" />
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>An image of the Delete Cells Dialog.</phrase>
            </textobject>
           </mediaobject>
		    </screenshot>
    </figure>


				 <para>
				 For example, if the user chose the
				 block of cells from E6:G8 for deletion, those cells could be
				 filled in by the cells below E8, F8 and G8 if the <guilabel>Shift cells
				 up</guilabel> option were chosen. Alternatively, the cells to the right
				 of G6, G7 and G8 could fill in the space from the right if the
				 <guilabel>Shift cells left</guilabel> option were chosen.
				 </para>
     	   		</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
		<term>
	            <emphasis role="bold">4</emphasis>
			Search and replace operations.
		</term>
		<listitem>
			<para>These menu entries relate to search and replace operations. Each
			  entry is explained in detail below. </para>

	 		<itemizedlist>

      	    	<listitem>
     	      	<para>
     	       	<guimenuitem>Search...</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
			       <guimenuitem>Search...</guimenuitem> menu item opens a dialog
				 to search for cells with particular content. The dialog has
				 three tabs. In the first the user can enter the information
				 the user wants to find and some constraints on the search. The
				 second tab gives some extra choices for the search. When the
				 user has picked the options they prefer, pushing the search
				 button on the first tab will run the search. The third tab
				 will show which cells match the search.
				 </para>
     	   		</listitem>

      	    	<listitem>
     	      	<para>
     	       	<guimenuitem>Search &amp; Replace...</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
			       <guimenuitem>.Search &amp; Replace..</guimenuitem> menu item
				 will launch a dialog to find cells with particular
				 characteristics and replace them all with a common content.
				 This dialog is similar to the <guilabel>Search</guilabel>
				 dialog.
				 </para>
     	   		</listitem>

		    </itemizedlist>
		    </listitem>

	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
		<term>
	            <emphasis role="bold">5</emphasis>
			Other operations on worksheets.
		</term>
		<listitem>
			<para>These menu entries do not group together logically. Each
			  entry is explained in detail below. </para>

	 		<itemizedlist>
      	    	<listitem>
     	      	<para>
     	       	<guimenuitem>Sheet</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
			       <guimenuitem>Sheet</guimenuitem> menu item opens up a
				   submenu which allows users to perform operations on the
				   worksheet. Note that this is the same set of choices as are
				   available from the context menu which appears by clicking
				   (usually with the right mouse button) on one of the
				   worksheet tabs. The worksheet can be duplicated to create a
				   second sheet with the same contents. A new worksheet can be
				   inserted immediately following the current sheet. The
				   current sheet can be renamed. The
				   sheets can be re-ordered or the current sheet can be
				   deleted.
				 </para>
     	   		</listitem>

      	    	<listitem>
     	      	<para>
     	       	<guimenuitem>Select</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
			       <guimenuitem>Select</guimenuitem> menu item allows the user
				    to select various portions of the worksheet. When selected
                    it opens a submenu.
 				 </para>

    <figure id="menu-edit-select.png">
		    <title>The Select Submenu</title>
		    <screenshot>
		      <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/menu-edit-select.png" />
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>An image of the Select Submenu.</phrase>
            </textobject>
           </mediaobject>
		    </screenshot>
    </figure>


	            <itemizedlist>
     	   		  <listitem>
				    <para>The
				      <guimenuitem>All</guimenuitem> item provides a quick way to
				      select the entire worksheet. 
				    </para>
     	   		</listitem>

      	    	<listitem>
				    <para>
				      The <guimenuitem>Row</guimenuitem> and <guimenuitem>Column
                      </guimenuitem>
				      items allow the user to select all the rows or columns 
				      spanned by the current selection.
				    </para>
     	   		</listitem>

      	    	<listitem>
				    <para>
				      The <guimenuitem>Array</guimenuitem> menu item allows a
				      user to select all the cells which are part of the same array
				      as the current cell. 
				    </para>
     	   		</listitem>

      	    	<listitem>
				    <para>
				      The <guimenuitem>Depends
                      </guimenuitem> 
				      menu item selects all the cells which contain formulas that
				      reference data in the current cell. 
				    </para>
     	   		</listitem>

      	    	<listitem>
				    <para>
				      Similarly, the <guimenuitem>Inputs
                      </guimenuitem> 
				      menu item selects all the cells whose data is referenced
                      by the formula in the current cell. 
				    </para>
     	   		</listitem>

      	    	<listitem>
				    <para>
				      The <guimenuitem>Next Object
                      </guimenuitem> 
				      menu item selects the next sheet object on the current sheet.
                      If no object is selected it will select the object locate at
                      the front.
				    </para>
     	   		</listitem>


      	    	<listitem>
     	      	<para>
     	       	<guimenuitem>Goto cell...</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
			       <guimenuitem>Goto cell...</guimenuitem> menuitem opens up a
				   dialog which allows the user to type the name or address of 
                    a cell in
				   the worksheet. The current view will then change to ensure
				   that the selected cell is in the current view and the
				   selection will cover that cell.
				 </para>
     	   		</listitem>
	            </itemizedlist>
     	   		</listitem>

      	    	<listitem>
     	      		<para>
     	       		<guimenuitem>Recalculate</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
			       	  <guimenuitem>Recalculate</guimenuitem> menu item forces
					the workbook to recalculate its results. This is useful
					if a formula in the current worksheet depends on a cell in
					a different workbook. &gnum; will not necessarily know
					when that data has been updated so a user can force
					&gnum; to recalculate all the cells in the current
					workbook.
     	      		</para>
     	   		</listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>
	</listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
		<term>
	            <emphasis role="bold">6</emphasis>
			General Configuration of
            &gnum;.
		</term>
		<listitem>
                <para>
                    <guimenuitem>Preferences...</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
                    <guimenuitem>Preference...</guimenuitem> menu item calls
                    the <guilabel>Gnumeric Preferences</guilabel> dialog 
                    explained in detail in <xref linkend="chapter-configuring" />
                </para>
	    </listitem>
	</varlistentry>

  </variablelist>
</sect2>


  <!-- *************************** View Menu *********** -->
  <sect2 id="View-Menu">
    <title>The View Menu</title>

 


    <para>
      The <guimenu>View</guimenu> menu is 
    </para>
		
    <figure id="menu-view-labelled.png">
      <title>The <guimenu>View</guimenu> menu.</title>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/menu-view-labelled.png" />
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>An image of the View menu.</phrase>
            </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>
	
    <para>
      The menu choices are grouped into the following groups:
    </para>



    <variablelist>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <emphasis role="bold">1</emphasis>
          Alternative views of the current document.
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            These menu items allow the user to open multiple views of
            the same document. 
          </para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <guimenuitem>New View...</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
                <guimenuitem>New View...</guimenuitem> menu item opens
                up a new window with the current workbook visible.
                and where both windows are open to the same section of
                the workbook. If the user starts editing a different
                part of the sheet in one view, the other view moves
                automatically to that portion of the
                worksheet. Similarly, if the user changes to a
                different worksheet in one view, the other view
                changes also.
<!-- TODO: are views 'shared' or 'unshared'? To what extent? -->
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <guimenuitem>Freeze Panes</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
                <guimenuitem>Freeze Panes</guimenuitem> menu item is
                used to freeze the top-most and leftmost visible
                portion of the worksheet. This is useful to be able to
                line up portions of the worksheet which are not
                usually together. For instance, if a user had a very
                large table with the titles of each column of data on
                row 12, the user could select row 13 and select this
                menu item.  If the user scrolled through each data
                row, the data would line up underneath each header.
              </para>
              <para> There are 3 ways to determine which rows and/or 
                columns should be frozen.
              </para>
              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    If the selection is at least partially visible does 
                    not include the cell
                    A1, &gnum; freezes the
		            portion of the worksheet above or to the left of the 
                    current selection. 
                 </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    If the selection is at least partially visible, 
                    includes cell A1, and does not consist
                    of whole rows or columns,
                    &gnum; freezes all rows or columns intersecting the
                    selection.
                 </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    If the selection is at least partially visible, 
                    includes cell A1, and consists
                    of whole rows or columns,
                    &gnum; freezes those rows or columns.
                 </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>If the
		            selection is not visible at all, then &gnum; freezes those 
                    rows and columns to the left or above the sixth visible column
                    and tenth visible row.
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
              <para>In all cases, the region of the worksheet above or to the right 
                of the currently visible region will become inaccessible until the
                view is unfrozen.
              </para>
<!-- TODO: menu elements, freeze only row/col. -->
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <guimenuitem>Windows</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
                <guimenuitem>Windows</guimenuitem> menu item provides
		access to a sub-menu which lists all of the windows
		which are currently open. This provides an easy way to
		jump between all the different instances and views of
		&gnum; documents.
              </para>
            </listitem>


          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>



      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <emphasis role="bold">2</emphasis>
          Changes to the current view.
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            These menu items alter the display of the current view.
	  </para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <guimenuitem>Toolbars</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
                <guimenuitem>Toolbars</guimenuitem> menu item provides
                a submenu which lists each &gnum; toolbar. The
                toolbars in this submenu which have a check mark in
                front of their name will be shown. The display status
                of each toolbar can be changed by selecting the menu
                item with that toolbar's name. 
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <guimenuitem>View Statusbar</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
                <guimenuitem>View Statusbar</guimenuitem> menu item
                determines whether to display the status bar and
                information area at the bottom of each
                worksheets. Selecting the menu item toggles the check
                mark in front. When this menu item has the checkmark,
                &gnum; will display the statusbar.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <guimenuitem>Full Screen</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
                <guimenuitem>Full Screen</guimenuitem> menu item
                changes the display of gnumeric from a window based
                display to a display which occupies the whole
                screen. In full screen mode, the window borders will
                not be displayed nor will the toolbars. The key
                <keysym>F11</keysym> toggles between full screen and
                regular display mode. When this menu item has the checkmark,
                &gnum; is in <guimenuitem>Full Screen</guimenuitem> mode.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <guimenuitem>View Properties...</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
                <guimenuitem>View Properties...</guimenuitem> menu item opens the 
                <guimenuitem>View Properties</guimenuitem> dialog.
                </para> 

                <figure id="menu-view-properties-dialog.png">
                <title>The <guimenu>View Properties</guimenu> dialog.</title>
                    <screenshot>
                        <mediaobject>
                            <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="figures/menu-view-properties-dialog.png" />
                            </imageobject>
                            <textobject>
                            <phrase>An image of the View Properties dialog.</phrase>
                            </textobject>
                        </mediaobject>
                    </screenshot>
                </figure>

                <para>The <guimenu>View Properties</guimenu> dialog has three tabs.
                    <guimenu>Auto Completion </guimenu>is described in 
                    <xref linkend="sect-worksheets-settings" />, 
                    <guimenu>Protection</guimenu> in
                    <xref linkend="sect-worksheets-settings-protection" />.
                </para>
                <para>The check boxes on the <guimenu>Widget</guimenu> tab shown in 
                    <xref linkend="menu-view-properties-dialog.png" /> determine
                    whether the notebook tabs, the horizontal scrollbar and/or 
                    the vertical scrollbars are shown in this view.
                </para>
            </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <emphasis role="bold">3</emphasis>
          Zoom Menu Item
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
                <guimenuitem>Zoom...</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
                <guimenuitem>Zoom</guimenuitem> menu item opens a
                dialog which allows the user to set the magnification
                of all worksheets in the current workbook. This item 
                is separated from the previous ones since it always acts
                on all views of a worksheet.
          </para>
        </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>


	</variablelist>
  </sect2>


  <!--  *********************************** INSERT MENU ********************* -->
  <sect2 id="Insert-Menu">
    <title>The Insert Menu</title>

    <para>
      The <guimenu>Insert</guimenu> menu is 
    </para>

    <figure id="menu-insert-labelled.png">
      <title>The <guimenu>Insert</guimenu> menu.</title>
        <screenshot>
	  <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/menu-insert-labelled.png" />
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>An image of the Insert menu.</phrase>
            </textobject>
           </mediaobject>
	 </screenshot>
    </figure>

    <para>
      The menu choices are grouped into the following groups:
    </para>

    <variablelist>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>
	  <emphasis role="bold">1</emphasis>
	  Insert into workbook.
	</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    These menu items alter the cells available in a workbook. 
	  </para>
	  <itemizedlist>

	   <listitem>
	     <para>
	       <guimenuitem>Cells...</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
	       <guimenuitem>Cells...</guimenuitem> menu item opens a
	       dialog asking the user how the sheet should be altered
	       when new cells are inserted. The dialog lists four
	       choices. The user can choose one of these by clicking
	       the mouse pointer on one of the four dots.  Only one
	       choice is possible and the currently selected choice
	       has a black dot in front.
	     </para>
	     <para>
	       The <guilabel>Shift cells right</guilabel> will insert
	       a region of new cells of the size of the current
	       selection. Cells which are on the same row as the
	       selection and within or to the right of the selection
	       will shift over to the right to accommodate the new
	       cells. The <guilabel>Shift cells down</guilabel> choice
	       will also insert a region of new cells the same size as
	       the current selection. With this choice, cells which
	       are in the selection or below the selection will move
	       down to accommodate the new cells. The two other
	       choices will act as if the user had chosen to insert
	       rows or columns. These actions are explained above.
	     </para>
	   </listitem>

	   <listitem>
	     <para>
	       <guimenuitem>Columns</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
	       <guimenuitem>Columns</guimenuitem> menu item will
	       insert columns to the left of the current
	       selection. The number of columns inserted will equal
	       the number of columns spanned by the current selection.
	     </para>
	   </listitem>

	   <listitem>
	     <para>
	       <guimenuitem>Rows</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
	       <guimenuitem>Rows</guimenuitem> menu item will insert
	       rows above the current selection. The number of rows
	       inserted will be equal to the number of rows spanned by
	       the current selection.
	     </para>
	   </listitem>

	    <listitem>
	      <para>
	        <guimenuitem>Sheet</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
		<guimenuitem>Sheet</guimenuitem> menu item allows the
		user to inset a worksheet immediately following the
		current sheet.
	     </para>
	   </listitem>

	 </itemizedlist>
       </listitem>
     </varlistentry>

<!-- TODO: add a separtor to insert menu. Sep. sheet obj. from cell content. -->

     <varlistentry>
       <term>
         <emphasis role="bold">2</emphasis>
	 Insert an object into the worksheet or content into the current cell.
       </term>

       <listitem>
         <para>
	   The menu items insert sheet objects into the worksheet or
	 insert content into the current cell.
	 </para>
	 <itemizedlist>

	   <listitem>
	     <para>
	       <guimenuitem>Graph...</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
	       <guimenuitem>Graph...</guimenuitem> menu item will
	       allow a user to insert a graphic plot of data. This
	       menu item will launch the graph druid. Graphing in
	       &gnum; is explained in
	       <xref linkend="chapter-graphs" />.
	     </para>
	   </listitem>

	   <listitem>
	     <para>
	       <guimenuitem>Image...</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
	       <guimenuitem>Image...</guimenuitem> menu item will
	       allow a user to insert a graphic object containing the
	       image from an external file. The use of images in
	       &gnum;  is explained in
	       <xref linkend="sect-graphics-images" />.
	     </para>
	   </listitem>

<!-- TODO: bonobo build where are insert obj/ins. shaped obj. ? -->
<!--
	   <listitem>
	     <para>
	       <guimenuitem>Object...</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
	       <guimenuitem>Object...</guimenuitem> menu item launches
	       a dialog with the objects which
	       &gnum; is currently able
	       to embed in a worksheet. The user simply picks one of
	       the objects in the list, and then inserts the object
	       into the worksheet. These objects are not part of
	       &gnum; but are provided by
	       other programs in the GNOME project.
	     </para>
	   </listitem>

	   <listitem>
	     <para>
	       <guimenuitem>Shaped Object...</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
	       <guimenuitem>Shaped Object...</guimenuitem> menu item
	       allows user to insert more complicated objects into a
	       worksheet. This is currently not used but will provide
	       more extended functionality for the future.
	     </para>
	   </listitem>
-->

	   <listitem>
	     <para>
	       <guimenuitem>Function</guimenuitem> &mdash; This menu item
		opens a dialog to allow the user to enter a
		mathematical formula into the cell. The function
		dialog includes the names and a brief explanation of
		all the available functions.
	     </para>
	   </listitem>

	   <listitem>
	     <para>
	       <guimenuitem>Names</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
	       <guimenuitem>Names</guimenuitem> menu item opens a
	       sub-menu with the single entry
	       <guilabel>Define</guilabel>. This will open a dialog to
	       allow the user to define a named expression. The
	       expression can be as simple as defining an expression
	       called "Total" which refers to a particular
	       cell. However, the user can also build up a whole sheet
	       with named expressions.  <xref linkend="sect-data-formulas-names"
	       /> explains names in greater detail.
	     </para>
	   </listitem>

	   <listitem>
	     <para>
	       <guimenuitem>Comment...</guimenuitem> &mdash;
		This menu item opens a dialog to allow the user to
		enter a comment to the currently selected cell. A red
		triangle will appear in the top right corner of the
		cell to show that the cell has a comment.
	     </para>
	   </listitem>

<!-- TODO: cell selection (not here) how to select a cell with a hyperlink. -->

	   <listitem>
	     <para>
	       <guimenuitem>Hyperlink...</guimenuitem> &mdash; This menu
		item opens a dialog to allow the user to enter the
		location of a link. The cell contents will become the
		text for the link and clicking on the cell will move
		the user to the new location. The link can point to
		another area of the worksheet, to another worksheet,
		or to any location which can be defined with a
		Universal Resource Locator (URL). If the URL points to
		a resource accessible over the Internet, &gnum; will
		launch the desktop web browser to open that URL.
	   </para>
	   </listitem>

	   <listitem>
	     <para>
	       <guimenuitem>Special</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
	       <guimenuitem>Special</guimenuitem> menu item opens a
	       sub-menu which allows the user to insert predefined
	       content into a cell. The current choices are to insert
	       the current date, time or both.
	     </para>
	   </listitem>

	 </itemizedlist>
       </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>


</sect2>













  <!--  ************************************FORMAT MENU ********************* -->
  <sect2 id="Format-Menu">
    <title>The Format Menu</title>

    <para>
      The <guimenu>Format</guimenu> menu allows users to control the
      formats of cells, columns, rows, worksheets and the
      workbook. This menu also gives users access to templates of
      standard formats.
    </para>

    <figure id="menu-format-labelled.png">
      <title>The <guimenu>Format</guimenu> Menu.</title>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/menu-format-labelled.png" />
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>An image of the Format menu.</phrase>
            </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>

    <!-- the list of format menu items -->
    <variablelist> 
      <varlistentry>
       <term><guimenu>The Format Menu</guimenu> offers these menuitems:</term>
       <listitem>
       <para>
         <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
           <para>
            <guimenuitem>Cells...</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
	    <guimenuitem>Cells...</guimenuitem> menu item opens the
	    cell format dialog. This dialog is used to set cell data
	    types and formats. It is explained in <xref
	    linkend="sect-data-format" />.
	  </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
         <para>

          <guimenuitem>Column</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
	  <guimenuitem>Column</guimenuitem> menu item opens a sub-menu
	  with choices to allows the user to modify the view of the
	  selected columns.
        </para>
    <figure id="menu-format-column.png">
      <title>The <guimenu>Column</guimenu> Submenu.</title>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/menu-format-column.png" />
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>An image of the Column submenu.</phrase>
            </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>

        <para>
	 <itemizedlist>
	   <listitem>
	     <para>
	     <guimenuitem>Width...</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
	     <guimenuitem>Width...</guimenuitem> menu item opens a
	     dialog to enable the user to adjust the size of the
	     columns which hold the current selection. The dialog has
	     a single entry box in which the user can change the
	     current size of the column in points.
	   </para>
	 </listitem>
	 <listitem>
	   <para>
	     <guimenuitem>Auto Fit Selection</guimenuitem> &mdash;
	     This menu item makes &gnum;
	     automatically choose the optimal column size to display
	     all of the text in the current selection.
	   </para>
	 </listitem>
	 <listitem>
	   <para>
	     <guimenuitem>Hide</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
	     <guimenuitem>Hide</guimenuitem> menu item will hide the
	     columns containing the current
	     selection. &gnum; still
	     holds these columns in memory and will save them to a
	     file but will not display those columns. The only
	     indication that a user has that columns have been hidden
	     is that the column header names are not sequential.
	   </para>
	 </listitem>
	 <listitem>
	   <para>
	     <guimenuitem>Unhide</guimenuitem> &mdash; This menu item
	     will show columns which are hidden if the selection spans
	     the two columns on either side of the selection. If
	     columns D, E, and F have been hidden, the selection must
	     span at least across columns C and G for this menu item
	     to unhide columns D, E, and F.
	   </para>
	 </listitem>
	 <listitem>
	   <para>
	     <guimenuitem>Standard Width</guimenuitem> &mdash; This
	     menu item allows the user to resize the columns which
	     hold the selection to the standard size. At 100 percent
	     zoom this is 48 points or 64 pixels.
	   </para>
	 </listitem>
       </itemizedlist>
     </para>
   </listitem>


        <listitem>
         <para>
           <guimenuitem>Row</guimenuitem> &mdash; The <guimenuitem>Row</guimenuitem>
					 menu item provides the same functions as the <guimenuitem>Column</guimenuitem>
					 menu item but operates on rows.
					 <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                <guimenuitem>Height...</guimenuitem> &mdash; This menu item opens a
								dialog which allows the user to type in a row height in pixels.
								</para>
	      </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                <guimenuitem>Auto Fit Selection</guimenuitem> &mdash; This menu item
								changes the rows which hold the selection to the optimal height
								to hold the text in the selection. 
								</para>
	      </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                <guimenuitem>Hide</guimenuitem> &mdash; The 
								  <guimenuitem>Hide</guimenuitem> menu item will hide the rows
									in the selection. The workbook still contains the data in the
									hidden rows but those rows are not shown. 
									</para>
	      </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                <guimenuitem>Unhide</guimenuitem> &mdash; This menu item will make
								hidden rows visible. The selection must span the rows which are
								hidden for this menu item to unhide the hidden rows.
	        </para>
	      </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                <guimenuitem>Standard Height</guimenuitem> &mdash; This menu item 
                resizes the rows back to the default height of 12.75 points or
								17 pixels (at 100 percent zoom).
	        </para>
	      </listitem>
           </itemizedlist>
         </para>
        </listitem>


        <listitem>
         <para>
          <guimenuitem>Sheet</guimenuitem> &mdash; The <guimenuitem>Sheet</guimenuitem>
			menu item opens a sub-menu with operations to change properties of the
			worksheet. This submenu has three sections.
        </para>
    <figure id="menu-format-sheet.png">
      <title>The <guimenu>Sheet</guimenu> Submenu.</title>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/menu-format-sheet.png" />
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>An image of the Sheet submenu.</phrase>
            </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>

    <variablelist>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>
	  <emphasis role="bold">1</emphasis>
	    Sheet Management Items
	</term>
	<listitem>
        <para>
            The first section contains menu items used to modify sheets indirectly.
            Note that these items are also
	    	available from the context menu which appears by clicking
	       (usually with the right mouse button) on one of the
	       worksheet tabs.
        </para>
        <para>
		<itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                 <para>
                <guimenuitem>Manage Sheets...</guimenuitem> &mdash;- This opens a
				dialog with the names and properties of all the sheets. 
                A user can click on
				one of the names in the dialog and then click on the up and
				down arrows, as appropriate, to move the selected sheet in
				front or behind others. The tabs for the sheets will move at
				the same time. This dialog also allows the user to delete
				sheets, to rename sheets, and to change many other sheet 
                properties.
				</para>
	      </listitem>
           <listitem>
              <para>
                <guimenuitem>Rename</guimenuitem> &mdash; After selecting this
                item the sheet name in the sheet tab is selected and can now be
                changed there.
	        </para>
	      </listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	    </para>
	      </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>
	  <emphasis role="bold">2</emphasis>
	    Toggle Items
	</term>
	<listitem>
        <para>The second section contains various toggle menu items 
            used to switch sheet
            properties directly.
        </para>
        <para>
		<itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                <guimenuitem>Display Formulas</guimenuitem> &mdash; This menu item
						acts as a toggle. By default it is unset and formulas results
						are displayed. If this menu item is clicked, it will display a
						little check mark on the left. The worksheet will show the
						actual formulas for all cells with formulas instead of showing
						the calculated result. This is useful for quickly assessing
						which cells contain formulas and which contain data.
	        			</para>
	      </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                <guimenuitem>Use R1C1 Notation</guimenuitem> &mdash; This
						menu item acts as a toggle. If this menu item is clicked,
						&gnum; display a check mark on the left of the menu item.
						&gnum; will also use R1C1 style notation to address cells
                        rather than A1 notation.
	        			</para>
	      </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                <guimenuitem>Hide Zeros</guimenuitem> &mdash; This menu item acts as
						a toggle. Click on this menu item will cause a check mark to
						appear on the left. The sheet will then display all the cells
						which display zeros as empty cells. This is useful in sheets
						with many zero results, to quickly find cells with data.
	        			</para>
	      </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                <guimenuitem>Hide Gridlines</guimenuitem> &mdash; This menu item
						acts as a toggle. If this menu item is clicked, &gnum; will
						display a check mark to the left of the menu item. The lines
						which separate all the cells will then be hidden and &gnum;
						will appear to be a blank background. This is useful to make
						certain data look pretty on screen.
	        			</para>
	      </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                <guimenuitem>Hide Column Headers</guimenuitem> &mdash; This
						menu item acts as a toggle. If this menu item is clicked,
						&gnum; display a check mark on the left of the menu item.
						&gnum; will also hide the boxes with the alphabetical names
						of the columns.
	        			</para>
	      </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                <guimenuitem>Hide Row Header</guimenuitem> &mdash; This
						menu item acts as a toggle. If this menu item is clicked,
						&gnum; display a check mark on the left of the menu item.
						&gnum; will also hide the boxes with the numeric names
						of the rows.
	        			</para>
	      </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                <guimenuitem>Direction</guimenuitem> &mdash; This
						menu item acts as a toggle. When selected
						&gnum; will change from left-to-right sheets to 
                        right-to-left sheets.
	        			</para>
	      </listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	    </para>
	      </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <emphasis role="bold">3</emphasis>
          Zoom Menu Item
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
                <guimenuitem>Zoom...</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
                <guimenuitem>Zoom</guimenuitem> menu item opens a
                dialog which allows the user to set the magnification
                of all worksheets in the current workbook. This item is
                also included in the
                <guimenuitem>View</guimenuitem> menu discussed in 
                <xref linkend="View-Menu" />,
          </para>
        </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
         <para>
           <guimenuitem>Autoformat...</guimenuitem> &mdash; This menu item
	   opens the autoformat dialog to give user access to a list
	   of format templates.  Format templates are useful for users
	   who are often filling out tables in a particular
	   format. The user picks an area of the worksheet into which
	   they want to apply the template. Most templates define
	   headers and footers so the selection area must be big
	   enough to fit those template elements and the user's
	   data. The template will not affect data which has already
	   been input into a worksheet.
	 </para>
	 <para>
	   The dialog has two tabs: <guilabel>Preview</guilabel> and
	   <guilabel>Template Details</guilabel>. The details are
	   simply information about the template. The
	   <guilabel>Preview</guilabel> tab has three main options: a
	   <guilabel>Settings</guilabel> menu, an
	   <guilabel>Edit</guilabel> menu and a category chooser. The
	   settings menu allows a user to pick what parts of the
	   template they want to copy into the worksheet. The edit
	   menu will be used to create new templates. Currently
	   templates are written as text into an extensible markup
	   language (XML) format. The category chooser gives the user
	   access to different groups of templates.  Templates in each
	   category are displayed in the middle area of the
	   dialog. Users select the template they want to use by
	   clicking on it.  The currently selected template is
	   highlighted with a red boundary which may be hard to see.
	 </para>
       </listitem>

      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

  </sect2>



<!--   ********************* TOOLS MENU ************  -->
<sect2 id="Tools-Menu">
	<title>The Tools Menu</title>

	<para>The <guimenu>Tools</guimenu> menu is </para>
		<figure id="menu-tools-labelled.png">
		    <title>The <guimenu>Tools</guimenu> menu.</title>
		    <screenshot>
		      <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/menu-tools-labelled.png" />
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>An image of the Tools menu.</phrase>
            </textobject>
           </mediaobject>
		    </screenshot>
	    </figure>
	<para>The menu choices are grouped into the following groups:</para>



 <variablelist>

      <varlistentry>
	<term>
	  <emphasis role="bold">1</emphasis>
	    Automatic tools
	</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>These two tools allow the user to make
	  &gnum; automatically correct
	  typing or automatically save workbooks at periodic
	  intervals.</para>
       <itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
		<para><guimenuitem>Auto Correct...</guimenuitem> &mdash;
		The <guimenuitem>Auto Correct...</guimenuitem> menu
		item opens a dialog which allows the user to configure
		the way in which gnumeric automatically corrects text
		which is being entered. The dialog presents the user
		with three tabs. Each of these tabs allows the user to
		correct one type of common spelling mistake, while
		allowing the user to add exceptions to the
		rules. &gnum; can
		automatically capitalize the names of week
		days. &gnum; can
		automatically change an entry which starts with two
		capital letters to only start with one and
		&gnum; can change a
		sentence entry to start with a capital letter.
						</para>
					</listitem>

		<listitem>
		<para>
		  <guimenuitem>Auto Save</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
		  <guimenuitem>Auto Save</guimenuitem> menu item opens
		  a dialog which allows the user to have
		  &gnum; automatically
		  save the current workbook after a fixed interval of
		  time. The user can also have
		  &gnum; ask for
		  confirmation before saving so that the user always
		  remains aware of the state the workbook was in when
		  it was saved.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
				</listitem>
      </varlistentry>

<!-- TODO: Split lp and scenarios when the 2 chpt.  are written. -->
      <varlistentry>
	<term>
	  <emphasis role="bold">2</emphasis>
	   Linear programming, scenario generation, simulation and statistical
        analysis tools
	</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    &gnum; can be used to solve
	    systems of linear equations and other mathematical
	    problems. These two dialogs enable access to these
	    tools. A full discussion of these tools is presented in
	    <xref linkend="sect-advanced-analysis-solver" />.
	  </para>
	  <itemizedlist>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>

	      <guimenuitem>Goal Seek</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
	      <guimenuitem>Goal Seek</guimenuitem> menu item opens a
	      dialog through which the user can configure
	      &gnum; to iteratively
	      search for a numeric value which solves a formula. This
	      dialog is explained in <xref
	      linkend="sect-advanced-analysis-goalseek" />.

	    </para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <guimenuitem>Solver</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
	      <guimenuitem>Solver</guimenuitem> menu item opens a
	      dialog through which the user can configure
	      &gnum; to solve linear
	      systems of equations.  This is explained in <xref
	      linkend="sect-advanced-analysis-solver" />.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <guimenuitem>Scenarios</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
	      <guimenuitem>Scenarios</guimenuitem> menu item displays
	      a submenu with two entries. The
	      <guimenuitem>View...</guimenuitem> menu item opens a
	      dialog in which the user can select previously defined
	      scenarios. The <guimenuitem>Add...</guimenuitem> menu
	      item opens a dialog in which the user can define the
	      contents of a new scenario.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <guimenuitem>Simulation</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
	      <guimenuitem>Simulation</guimenuitem> menu item opens a
	      multipaned dialog allowing the user to configure the
	      parameters for a simulation using linear modeling
	      constraints. 
	    </para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	        <guimenuitem>Statistical Analysis</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
	        <guimenuitem>Statistical Analysis</guimenuitem> menu item opens a
	        submenu with all available statistical analysis tools. These tools
            are explained in <xref linkend="chapter-stat-analysis" />.
	      constraints. 
	    </para>
	  </listitem>

	</itemizedlist>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
	<term>
	  <emphasis role="bold">3</emphasis>
	    The Plug-ins dialog.
	</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>This entry launches the plug-in management
	  dialog. Plug-ins are programs which are separate from
	  &gnum; but provide useful
	  functionality.  Some of the core parts of gnumeric, such as
	  Excel file format support, are actually plugins. This means
	  that a user who never uses Excel files can remove this
	  module from &gnum; and make
	  &gnum; use less memory.<!--
	  <xref linkend="Plugins" /> explains plug-ins in greater
	  detail.--></para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>


</variablelist>

</sect2>


  <!-- ******************* THE DATA MENU   ************** -->
  <sect2 id="Data-Menu">
    <title>The Data Menu</title>

    <para>
      The <guimenu>Data</guimenu> menu is 
    </para>

    <figure id="menu-data-labelled.png">
      <title>The <guimenu>Data</guimenu> menu.</title>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/menu-data-labelled.png" />
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>An image of the Data menu.</phrase>
            </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>

    <para>
      The menu choices are grouped into the following groups:
    </para>

    <variablelist>

      <varlistentry>
	<term>
	  <emphasis role="bold">1</emphasis>
	    Data Field tools.
	</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    These menu items allow the user to re-organize data.
	  </para>

	  <itemizedlist>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
	        <guimenuitem>Sort...</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
		<guimenuitem>Sort...</guimenuitem> menu item opens a
		dialog which allows users to sort a selection
		according to defined criteria. By default
		&gnum; sorts the rows in
		a selected area 
		depending on the contents of the cells in a particular
		column of each row. The sort criteria can be extended
		to calculate on the basis of the cells in several
		columns.  &gnum; can sort
		a selection using any number of rules. Rules can be
		added using the <guibutton>Add</guibutton>
		button. Rules with no column entered will be ignored
		or the user can remove these rules with the
		<guibutton>Remove</guibutton> button.
	      </para>

	      <para> 
	        For each rule, the dialog has an entry box in
	        which the column to be sorted must be entered. The
	        dropdown box (the little down pointing arrow) will
	        show a list of appropriate columns.  The user can
	        determine a sort order for the selection. The
	        <guibutton>Advanced</guibutton> button allows the user
	        to further characterize the sort criteria..
	      </para>

	      <para> If the first row of the selection is a header,
	        &gnum; can be told not to
	        shuffle this row during the
	        sort. &gnum; can also
	        sort columns based on the contents of cells in
	        specified rows, instead of shuffling rows on the basis
	        of columns, if the user toggles the
	        <guilabel>Sort</guilabel> to act right-left instead of
	        top-down.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>

	    <listitem>
	      <para>
	        <guimenuitem>Fill</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
		<guimenuitem>Fill</guimenuitem> menu item opens a
		sub-menu that allows various forms of data to be created.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>

	    <listitem>
	      <para>
	        <guimenuitem>Filter</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
		<guimenuitem>Filter</guimenuitem> menu item opens a
		sub-menu with three entries: <guimenuitem>Add Auto
		Filter</guimenuitem>, <guimenuitem>Show
		All</guimenuitem>, and <guimenuitem>Advanced
		Filter</guimenuitem> entry. Filters are explained in
		<xref linkend="sect-data-filter" />.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>

	    <listitem>
	      <para>
	        <guimenuitem>Validate...</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
		<guimenuitem>Validate...</guimenuitem> menu item opens
		the cell format dialog to the validation
		tab. Validation is a means of constraining the
		contents of a cell either to have a certain value or
		to fall within a certain range.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>


	    <listitem>
	      <para>
	        <guimenuitem>Consolidate...</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
		<guimenuitem>Consolidate...</guimenuitem> menu item
		opens a dialog box through which a user can create
		derived information based on data in other worksheets.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>

	    <listitem>
	      <para>
	        <guimenuitem>Table...</guimenuitem> &mdash; 
	      </para>
	    </listitem>

	    <listitem>
	      <para>
	        <guimenuitem>Group and Outline</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
		<guimenuitem>Group and Outline</guimenuitem> menu item
		provides a sub-menu through which users can group rows
		or columns into units which can be collapsed to be
		hidden from view. These entries also allow users to
		alter the display of the grouping handles on the
		borders of the worksheet.

	      </para>
	    </listitem>

	  </itemizedlist>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
	<term>
	  <emphasis role="bold">2</emphasis>
	    Data Modifications or Import.
	</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    These entries allow user to convert data already in a worksheet or to 
        import external
	    data directly into a worksheet.
	    </para>
	    <itemizedlist>

	    <listitem>
	      <para>
	        <guimenuitem>Text to Columns...</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
		<guimenuitem>Text to Columns...</guimenuitem> menu item
		opens a dialog box through which a user can create
		derived information based on data in other worksheets.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>

	    <listitem>
	      <para>
	        <guimenuitem>Get External Data</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
		<guimenuitem>Get External Data</guimenuitem> menu item
		provides a sub-menu which currently only allow the
		import of text data from an external source.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>


	  </itemizedlist>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>

    </variablelist>


  </sect2>





  <!--  *********************** HELP MENU *****************-->
  <sect2 id="Help-Menu">
    <title>The Help Menu</title>

    <para>
      The <guimenu>Help</guimenu> menu is quite simple.
    </para>

    <figure id="menu-help-labelled.png">
      <title>The <guimenu>Help</guimenu> menu.</title>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/menu-help-labelled.png" />
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>An image of the Help menu.</phrase>
            </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>

    <para>
      The <guimenu>Help</guimenu> menu connects users to this manual,
      to the list of functions available for use in
      &gnum; and to the list of people
      who created this wonderful application.
    </para>

<!-- TODO: Split help from bug report. -->
    <!-- the help menu list -->
    <variablelist> 

      <varlistentry>
	<term>
	  <emphasis role="bold">1</emphasis>
	    Entries to find help and report a problem with &gnum;
	</term>

	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    These menu items allow the user to obtain help from
	    several sources or to report a problem with the program.
	  </para>

	  <itemizedlist>

	    <listitem>
              <para>
                <guimenuitem>Contents</guimenuitem> &mdash; This menu
                entry allows the user to launch the local help system
                and display this manual.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>

	    <listitem>
              <para>
                <guimenuitem>Gnumeric on the Web</guimenuitem> &mdash;
                This menu entry allows the user to launch a web
                browser and explore the web site dedicated to &gnum;
                on the server used by the GNOME project.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>

	    <listitem>
              <para>
                <guimenuitem>Live Assistance</guimenuitem> &mdash;
                This menu entry allows the user to launch an Internet
                Relay Chat (IRC) client to join the GIMPnet network
                and the #gnumeric channel. This channel is used by the
                &gnum; developers. There is generally someone around
                who will, after a few minutes, notice a nice question
                and attempt to answer it.
	      </para>
	      <warning>
	        <para>
		  Live assistance is provided on a purely voluntary
                  basis. There are no guarantees that your question
                  will be answered or that the answer will be
                  correct. We generally try our best to answer
                  questions when they are asked politely and when the
                  user shows that they have at least looked in the
                  User Manual for an answer.
		</para>
	      </warning>
	    </listitem>

	    <listitem>
              <para>
                <guimenuitem>Report a Problem</guimenuitem> &mdash;
                This menu entry allows the user to launch a web
                browser and open the page on GNOME's Bugzilla bug
                entry system for the &gnum; program. This page
                includes instructions on submitting reports of
                problems. The first time a user reports a problem,
                they will be asked to login to the system.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>

          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
	<term>
	  <emphasis role="bold">2</emphasis>
	    The <interface>About Gnumeric</interface> dialog.
	</term>

        <listitem>
         <para>
          <guimenuitem>About</guimenuitem> &mdash;Shows basic
          information about &gnum;, such
          as the authors' names and the application version number.
         </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

  </sect2>


</sect1>


<!--  *********************** CONTEXT MENUS *****************-->
<sect1 id="context-menu">
	<title>Context Menus</title>

<!-- TODO: add info area context menu. -->
<!-- TODO: add text entry context menu. -->

	<para>Context menus are menus which open up under the mouse pointer and are
	therefore detached from the format graphical structure
	of the application. These menus provide an extra and convenient way to access
	Gnumeric commands. All of the commands in context menus are available
	through the regular menu system. Context menus provide different commands
	depending on the position of the pointer.</para>

	<para>To activate a context menu, a user simply positions the pointer over
	the appropriate area and clicks one of the buttons on their mouse. Since this
	button is configurable and users have mice with different buttons, it may be a
	different button on any given machine or may even require the combination of a
	keyboard key and a mouse buttons. The user will have to find how to do this
	themselves.</para>

  <para>
    Currently Gnumeric provides five different context menus. The
    context menu that is called in the central grid area is discussed
    next in <xref linkend="menu-context-grid" />. The Context menu
    that appears when the pointer is over the row headers or column
    headers is presented in <xref
    linkend="menu-context-col-row-header" />. Another context menu
    relates to the worksheet tabs and is explained in <xref
    linkend="menu-context-tabs" />. Yet another context menu applies
    to embedded objects or shaped components such as a plot. These are
    shown in <xref linkend="menu-context-object" />.
  </para>


  <sect2 id="menu-context-grid">
    <title>The Context Menu for the Cell Grid Area</title>

    <para>
      The context menu in the cell grid area appears when the pointer
      is over the cell grid area. This menu applies to the cells that
      have been selected, not necessarily the cell underneath the
      mouse pointer.
    </para>
		<figure id="menu-context-grid.png">
		    <title>The Context Menu for the Cell Grid Area.</title>
		    <screenshot>
		      <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/menu-context-grid.png" />
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>An image of the context menu in the cell grid area.</phrase>
            </textobject>
           </mediaobject>
		    </screenshot>
	    </figure>
	<para>The grid context menu merely provides an extra way to access Gnumeric
	commands. The <guimenuitem>Cut</guimenuitem>, <guimenuitem>Copy</guimenuitem>, 
	<guimenuitem>Paste</guimenuitem>, <guimenuitem>Paste Special...</guimenuitem>,
	<guimenuitem>Delete...</guimenuitem>, and <guimenuitem>Clear Contents...</guimenuitem> 
	commands are taken from the Edit menu and are explained in
	<xref linkend="Edit-Menu" />.
	The <guimenuitem>Insert...</guimenuitem> menu item is explained in the section
	on the <guimenu>Insert</guimenu> menu in <xref
	linkend="Insert-Menu" />. The 
	<guimenuitem>Format Cells...</guimenuitem> is explained in the manual section
	on the <guimenu>Format</guimenu> menu in <xref
	linkend="Format-Menu" />.
	</para>
</sect2>


<sect2 id="menu-context-col-row-header">
	<title>The Context Menu for Column and Row Headers</title>
	<para>The Context Menu for Column and Row Headers</para>
		<figure id="menu-context-col-row-header.png">
		    <title>The Context Menu of a Row Header</title>
		    <screenshot>
		      <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/menu-context-col-row-header.png" />
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>An image of the context menu on a row header.</phrase>
            </textobject>
           </mediaobject>
		    </screenshot>
	    </figure>
	<para>The context menu which relates to column or row headers is similar to
	the context menu for the grid area. Both insert and delete operations are
	modified to operate explicitly on rows or on columns. An option is added
	which changes the height of rows or the width of columns. This context menu
	also provides a way to hide rows or columns and a way to reveal missing
	columns or rows.
	</para>


</sect2>

<sect2 id="menu-context-tabs">
	<title>The Context Menu menu for Worksheet Tabs</title>
		<para>The Context Menu menu for Worksheet Tabs.</para>
		<figure id="menu-context-tabs.png">
		    <title>The Context Menu.</title>
		    <screenshot>
		      <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/menu-context-tabs.png" />
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>An image of the context menu for worksheet tabs.</phrase>
            </textobject>
           </mediaobject>
		    </screenshot>
	    </figure>
	<para>The context menu for tabs provides the same functions as are provided 
	in the <guimenuitem>Sheet</guimenuitem> menu item in the
	<guimenu>Edit</guimenu> menu. These options are explained at the bottom of 
	<xref linkend="Edit-Menu" />. In addition, this context menu provides for two
        submenus to select any of the existing sheets, whether their tab is currently
        visible or not. The first submenu lists the sheets in their current order, 
        the second submenu lists them alphabetically.
	</para>


</sect2>


  <sect2 id="menu-context-object">
    <title>The Context Menu for Embedded Objects and Components</title>

    <para>
      The Context Menu for Embedded Objects and Components.
    </para>

    <figure id="menu-context-object.png">
      <title>The Context Menu for Graphical Objects</title>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/menu-context-object.png" />
          </imageobject>
          <textobject>
            <phrase>An image of the context menu on embedded objects.</phrase>
          </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>

    <para>
      All embedded objects, such as drawing elements, graphs and
      images, have a context menu which can be invoked by placing the
      mouse pointer over the element and clicking with one of the
      secondary mouse buttons.
    </para>

    <para>
      The first menu entry, labeled
      <guimenuitem>Properties</guimenuitem>, will open a dialog
      specific to the type of element selected in which the user can
      configure the properties of the element.
    </para>

    <para>
      The menu entry labeled
      <guimenuitem>Size &amp; Position</guimenuitem>, will open a dialog
      that permits the user to adjust the size and position of the embedded object.
    </para>

    <para>
      The menu entry labeled
      <guimenuitem>Snap to Grid</guimenuitem>, enlarges the object such that all of
        its corners are located at cell corners.
    </para>

    <para>
      The menu entry labeled <guimenuitem>Order</guimenuitem>,
      opens a submenu which allows the user to change the visual order
      in which the graphical elements are placed. This order will
      affect the way in which the graphical elements obscure each other.
    </para>

    <figure id="menu-context-object-order.png">
      <title>The Context Submenu for Graphical Object Order</title>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/menu-context-object-order.png" />
          </imageobject>
          <textobject>
            <phrase>An image of the context submenu allowing the
            re-ordering of graphical objects.</phrase>
          </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>


    <para>
      The remaining menu entries, labeled <guimenuitem>Cut</guimenuitem>,
      <guimenuitem>Copy</guimenuitem>, and
      <guimenuitem>Delete</guimenuitem>, allow the user to operate on
      the whole object at once. The <guimenuitem>Cut</guimenuitem>
      menu item allows the user to remove the element from its current
      position and then paste the object in a different location on
      the same sheet, in a different worksheet, in a different
      gnumeric file, or in a file from a different program entirely. The
      <guimenuitem>Copy</guimenuitem> menu item provides the same
      functionality while leaving the original item in place. The
      <guimenuitem>Delete</guimenuitem> allows the user to remove the
      graphical element entirely.
    </para>

    <para>
      For certain types of objects, menu entry labeled <guimenuitem>Save
      As...</guimenuitem> 
      allows the object to be saved as an image file. This menu item
      is not present in <xref linkend="menu-context-object.png"/> but is shown in 
        <xref linkend="menu-context-graph.png"/> .
    </para>

    <figure id="menu-context-graph.png">
      <title>The Context Menu for Graphs and Images</title>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/menu-context-graph.png" />
          </imageobject>
          <textobject>
            <phrase>An image of the context menu for graphs and images.</phrase>
          </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>

    <para>
        Graphs also have a context menu with a menu entry labeled <guimenuitem>Open in
        New Window</guimenuitem>. That menu item shows the graph by itself in a window.
    </para>



</sect2>

<!-- No longer relevant in version 1.4+

<sect2 id="menu-context-toolbars">
	<title>The Context Menu for Toolbars</title>
		<para>The Context Menu for Toolbars</para>
		<figure id="menu-context-toolbars.png">
		    <title>The Context Menu.</title>
		    <screenshot>
		      <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/menu-context-toolbars.png" />
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>An image of the context menu on the toolbars.</phrase>
            </textobject>
           </mediaobject>
		    </screenshot>
	    </figure>
	<para>The context menu for toolbars allows the user to configure toolbars.
	Each toolbar entry can have text associated with it or simply be an icon. The
	text only does not currently work in Gnumeric. The tooltips which are
	displayed by default can be turned off for this toolbar. The toolbar itself
	can be removed to save space. Finally the customize dialog can be launched
	which allows the user to configure these options for all the toolbars at
	once.
	</para>


</sect2>

-->

</sect1>







      <!-- IF someone knows a more approriate way to document menu
      options, let me know. This seems a bit excessive, and the output
      from db2html is kind of lame -->
      
     <!-- <title><guimenu><accel>F</accel>ile</guimenu></title>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><guimenuitem><accel>N</accel>ew</guimenuitem></term>
	  <listitem><para>Create a new worksheet. This opens a new
	  worksheet in a window.</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><guimenuitem><accel>O</accel>pen</guimenuitem></term>
	  <listitem><para>Open an existing worksheet. A new window is
	  created with the file selected in it.</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><guimenuitem><accel>S</accel>ave</guimenuitem></term>
	  <listitem><para>Save the current worksheet. If the file has been
	  named and saved before, this will silently save the file to the
	  current filename. If it has not been saved before, this will
	  prompt for a filename and path.</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><guimenuitem>S<accel>a</accel>ve
	  as..</guimenuitem></term>

	  <listitem><para>Save a file with a new name. Save a newly created
	  file or save a file with a different name. </para></listitem>

	</varlistentry>
	
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><guimenuitem><accel>P</accel>lugins</guimenuitem></term>
	  <listitem><para>Open the plugins dialog. For loading, saving of
	  plugins. This shows the listing of pre loaded plugins and allows
	  the user the user to add more.</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><guimenuitem><accel>C</accel>lose</guimenuitem></term>
	  <listitem><para>Close the current worksheet.</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><guimenuitem><accel>Q</accel>uit</guimenuitem></term>
	  <listitem><para>Close the open worksheets and quit
	  Gnumeric</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	
      </variablelist>  
      
      
    </sect3> 
    
    <sect3>
      <title><guimenu><accel>E</accel>dit</guimenu></title>
      <variablelist>
	
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><guimenuitem><accel>C</accel>ut</guimenuitem></term>
	  <listitem><para>Remove the content in the currently selected cells
	  and save it.</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><guimenuitem>C<accel>o</accel>py</guimenuitem></term>
	  <listitem><para>Make a copy of the current selection to be pasted
	  later.</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><guimenuitem><accel>P</accel>aste</guimenuitem></term>
	  <listitem><para>Paste whatever is in the cut buffer at the
	  cursor.</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><guimenuitem>P<accel>a</accel>ste
	  Special</guimenuitem></term> <listitem><para>Paste from the cut
	  buffer, but with more options as to what to paste.  Useful for
	  pasting just format, or just values, etc.</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><guimenuitem><accel>S</accel>elect All</guimenuitem></term>
	  <listitem><para>Select every cell in the worksheet.</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><guisubmenu>Clear -&gt;</guisubmenu></term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <variablelist>
		<varlistentry>
		  <term><guimenuitem><accel>A</accel>ll</guimenuitem></term>
		  <listitem><para>Clear every cell.</para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
		  <term><guimenuitem><accel>F</accel>ormats</guimenuitem></term>
		  <listitem><para>Clear the format from selected
		  cells.</para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>
	      </variablelist>
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><guimenuitem><accel>G</accel>oto Cell</guimenuitem></term>
	  <listitem><para>Let the user specify a cell to "jump" to.</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </sect3>
    
    <sect3>
      <title><guimenu><accel>V</accel>iew</guimenu></title>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry><term><guimenuitem><accel>Z</accel>oom</guimenuitem></term>
	<listitem><para>Zoom in. To show a area of the spreadsheet in more
	detail.</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </sect3>
    
    <sect3>
      <title><guimenu><accel>I</accel>nsert</guimenu></title>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry><term><guimenuitem><accel>C</accel>ells</guimenuitem></term>
	  <listitem><para>Insert a new cell.</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry><term><guimenuitem><accel>R</accel>ows</guimenuitem></term>
	  <listitem><para>Insert a Row of cells.</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry><term><guimenuitem>C<accel>o</accel>lumns</guimenuitem></term>
	  <listitem><para>Insert a Column of cells.</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </sect3>
    
    <sect3>
      <title><guimenu>F<accel>o</accel>rmat</guimenu></title>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry><term><guimenuitem><accel>C</accel>ells</guimenuitem></term>
	<listitem><para>Open the cell format dialog. Used to change
	formatting, color, etc</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </sect3>
    
    <sect3>
      <title><guimenu><accel>H</accel>elp</guimenu></title>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry><term><guimenuitem>Cells</guimenuitem></term>
	  <listitem><para>View the online help for Gnumeric</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </sect3>-->
  <!-- end of menubar description -->
  

