<sect1 id="data-entry">
  <title>Data Entry Area</title>

  <para>Immediately above the grid of cells is the data entry
    area as shown in <xref linkend="worksheet-data-1" />.</para>
  <figure id="worksheet-data-1">
    <title>The Data Entry area.</title>
    <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/worksheet-data-1.png" format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>An image of the data entry area.</phrase>
            </textobject>
           </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
  </figure>
  <para>This is a small area, which contains a current cell
    indicator, a <guibutton>cancel</guibutton> button, a 
    <guibutton>confirm</guibutton> button, an
    <guibutton>entry</guibutton> button, and an entry area for
    detailed editing of the cell contents. These elements are explained
    individually below.
  </para>
  
<!-- TODO: change through whole file current cell to selection. -->
    <sect2 id="data-entry-currentcell">
      <title>Current Cell Indicator</title>
	  
      <para>
        On the far left of the Data Entry area is the current cell
        indicator area.  This area is shown in <xref
        linkend="worksheet-data-2" />
      </para>

<!-- TODO: change the screenshot to drop the other two buttons. -->

      <figure id="worksheet-data-2">
	<title>The Current Cell Indicator.</title>
	<screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/worksheet-data-2.png" format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>An image of the current cell indicator.</phrase>
            </textobject>
           </mediaobject>
	</screenshot>
      </figure>

      <para>
        The cell indicator will show the address for the cell at the
        top left of the selected region. This address is listed in the
        standard column:row notation. The alphabetic part indicates
        the column of this top leftmost cell and the numeric part
        indicates the row of this top left cell. For instance, the
        cell which is over three columns and down two rows is
        designated:</para> <blockquote><para>C2</para></blockquote>
        <para>This designation matches the column and row headers for
        this cell.
      </para>

      <para>
        While a region is being selected, the current cell indicator
        will change to show the size of the region which is being
        selected. This information is presented in a row number by
        column number format. For instance, this designation:
      
        <blockquote><para>15R x 6C</para></blockquote>
      
        would indicate a selection area 15 rows high by 6 columns
        wide. Once the mouse is released at the end of the selection,
        the current cell indicator goes back to giving the address of
        the single top leftmost cell.
      </para>
      
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2 id="data-entry-cancel">
      <title>The <guibutton>Cancel</guibutton> Button</title>
      
    <para>
      The Cancel button 
      <guibutton>
	<inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/worksheet-data-4.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>An image of the cancel button.</phrase>
            </textobject>
           </inlinemediaobject>
      </guibutton>
      can be used to cancel the current edit and to restore the cell
      contents to the previous state. If a user decides in the middle
      of an edit that the data being entered into a cell is not what
      they want, the user can push this cancel button to cancel the
      current data and return the cell to the state it was at before.
    </para>
      
    <para>
      The most common use of this button is when overwriting the contents
      of a cell with new data. If the user decided to revert the change
      before confirming it, the cancel button is the answer. Note that this 
      button works just like typing the escape key on the keyboard.
    </para>
  </sect2>
  
	
    <sect2 id="data-entry-confirm">
      <title>The <guibutton>Confirm</guibutton> Button</title>
      
      <para>The confirm button
      <guibutton>
	<inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/worksheet-data-3.png" format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>An image of the enter button.</phrase>
            </textobject>
           </inlinemediaobject>
       </guibutton>.  can be used to finish the edit of a cell and
       enter the edit into the workbook. Note that this button works
       in the same way as the enter key.
	  </para>

    </sect2>
	
	
    <sect2 id="data-entry-equals">
      <title>The <guibutton>Equals</guibutton> Button</title>
      
      <para>The equals button 
		<guibutton>
		  <inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/button-equals.png" format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>An image of the equals button.</phrase>
            </textobject>
           </inlinemediaobject>
		</guibutton>
	  can be used to start a formula in the currently selected
	  cell. If a user wanted to make cell D10 equal to cell B4,
	  the user could simply click on cell D10, click this equals
	  button, click on cell B4 and type the enter key. Note that
	  this button works the same way as the equals key.
      </para>
      
    </sect2>

<!--TODO: Add <sect2> with discussion of the formula entry field. -->


</sect1>






  
<sect1 id="cell-grid">
    <title>The Cell Grid</title>
      
    <para>Most of the work done on a spreadsheet is done to the main
    Cell area, the large grid like part of the worksheet. This is
    where all the formulas and data are entered, and is the center of
    activity for the spreadsheet.</para>

<!-- TODO: change screenshot to fit in 510pixels. -->
    <figure id="cell-grid.png">
      <title>The Cell Grid area, with cells of different sizes.</title>
      <screenshot>
         <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/cell-grid.png" format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>An image of the cell grid area.</phrase>
            </textobject>
          </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>
 
 	<para><xref linkend="cell-grid.png" /> shows the cell grid
 	area, the column and row headers on the top and left, the
 	scrollbars on the right and bottom and the tab list at the
 	very bottom.
	</para>
	
	<para> The figure has a few and shows that cell B3 as being 
	selected. In this figure, the columns and rows have been 
	resized and therefore look uneven. </para>
	
	<para>Each cell in this area is delimited by a light grey line
	by default.  The current selection is indicated by a
	rectangular box with a little box on the lower right, this
	case cell J12. The view in this figure shows the middle
	portion of a worksheet which is evident in two ways. Firstly,
	the column and row headers do not start at column A and row
	1. Secondly, the scroll thumbs are not at the top and
	left. The thumbs are the boxes within the scroll bars that are
	used to scroll. Note also that cell D19 has a comment within
	it which is shown by the little red triangle at the top right
	corner.</para>
	
	<para>The size of a cell is determined by the width of the
	column and height of the row that the cell is in. The columns
	and rows can be resized by acting on the header relevant to
	the cell. The user must move the mouse pointer to the edge of
	the header which is either to the right or below the cell.
	With the mouse pointer in this position, the pointer will
	change to a set of opposite pointing arrows. The user must
	then drag this edge away from the top left corner. This takes
	a little practice.</para>
	
	
	<para>The cell area is the core of Gnumeric. Therefore the
	manual explains the use of cells in much greater detail in a
	separate section. Interested users should read <xref
	linkend="chapter-data" />.</para>

	

  <sect2 id="col-row-headers">
    <title>The Column and Row Headers</title>

    <para>
      The sheet is bordered by column headers on the top and row
      headers to the left.  Columns are labeled alphabetically running
      horizontally across the top of the sheet as shown in <xref
      linkend="worksheet-cols-1" />.

    <figure id="worksheet-cols-1">
      <title>The column labels at the top of the worksheet.</title>
      <screenshot>
         <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/worksheet-cols-1.png" format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>An image of the column labels.</phrase>
            </textobject>
           </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>

    Rows are labeled along the left side of the worksheet. Each label
    is a different integer increasing downward. This is shown in
    <xref linkend="worksheet-rows-1" />.
    
    <figure id="worksheet-rows-1">
      <title>The row labels at the left side of the worksheet.</title>
      <screenshot>
         <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/worksheet-rows-1.png" format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>An image of the row labels.</phrase>
            </textobject>
           </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>

    </para>

	</sect2>

  <sect2 id="cell-grid-scrollbars">
    <title>The Scrollbars</title>

<!-- TODO: add screenshot, explain the different parts: thumb, channel... -->
    <para>
      The cell grid area's scrollbars work like other scrollbars. In
      this case they let the user work on a worksheet which is much
      bigger than what could be shown at any given moment.
    </para>

  </sect2>




  <sect2 id="cell-grid-tabs">
    <title>The Tabbed Sheet Indicator</title>

<!-- TODO: add a screenshot. Explain selction, drag. -->
    <para>
      At the bottom of <xref linkend="cell-grid.png" />, Gnumeric has
      a tabbed sheet indicator. This is the boxes with the labels
      "Guppies", "Turtles", "Mermaids", "seahorses" and so on. In
      workbooks where there are more than one sheet, extra tabs are
      used to indicate how many sheets are there, and also allows the
      user to move to another sheet by clicking the proper tab. Each
      tab is a link to a separate worksheet within Gnumeric. In this
      figure, the "Turtles" tab has been selected. Gnumeric shows this
      by making the "Turtles" since the tab is a little bigger and
      making it overlap the two neighbouring tabs.
    </para>

    <para>
      On the far right, the two arrows indicate that there are more
      sheets in the workbook and more tabs for those
      sheets. Unfortunately, there is not enough space to show them
      all so Gnumeric displays these arrows. If all the sheets are
      visible, these arrows will not be displayed. These arrows can be
      used to scroll the tabs and bring tabs that were hidden into
      view. This may be a little difficult to understand and work with
      but becomes easier quickly.
    </para>

  </sect2>
    


</sect1>
 








<sect1 id="info-area">
    <title>The Information Area</title>
    
    <para>
      The section at the very bottom of the worksheet view is the
      information area as is shown in <xref linkend="info-area.png"
      />.

    <figure id="info-area.png">
      <title>The Information Display Area.</title>

      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/info-area.png" format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>
          <textobject>
            <phrase>An image of the information display area.</phrase>
          </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>

      The information area displays information depending on what is
      happening in Gnumeric.
    </para>
	
	<sect2 id="info-area-hint">
		<title>The Menu Hint Area</title>
	
	<para>
	The leftmost portion of the information display area, the part
	which reads: "Sort the selected cells" is a hint explaining
	what a menu does. In this case, the Data menu was opened and
	the pointer is hovering above the "sort" menu entry. Gnumeric
	is responding by giving a quick explanation of what that menu
	entry does.
	</para>

	</sect2>

	<sect2 id="info-area-file">
		<title>The File Status Indicator</title>

		<para>
		Whenever Gnumeric opens or saves a file, the file
		status indicator appears with a progress bar which
		grows as Gnumeric progresses. In <xref
		linkend="info-area.png" />, Gnumeric was just over
		halfway done opening a file.
		</para>
	</sect2>



       <sect2 id="info-area-calc">
      <title>The Running Calculation Area</title>
      
      <para>In the bottom right hand corner, is an info area that
      shows some constantly calculated values. The default set is to
      show the Sum of all the currently selected cells.</para>
      
      <para>There is a right click option that includes a few more
      options.  This can include Sum, Min, Max, Average, Count.</para>
      
      <figure id="worksheet-running-calc-1">
	<title>The running calculation area.</title>
	<screenshot>
	  <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/worksheet-running-calc-1.png" format="PNG" /></imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>An image of the running calculation area.</phrase>
            </textobject>
           </mediaobject>
	</screenshot>
      </figure>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

<!--end of chapter Other graphical elements.-->

