<sect1 id="sect-gui-menus">
  <title>Menus</title>

<!-- TODO: add explanation of how to use a menu. -->
<!-- TODO: go over sub-menus and treat consistently. -->
<!-- TODO: add xref to each menu entry for other section of the manual. -->

  <para>
    This section of the manual describes the use of the menubar and
    the menus themselves. It then explains each entry in every
    &gnum; menu, submenu or context menu.
  </para>

  <sect2 id="menu-nav">
    <title>Using Menus</title>    

  <para>
    A menu is a graphical element within a program which appears with
    a list of options. For instance, almost all applications have a
    <guimenu>File</guimenu> menu through which the user can access the
    computer's filesystem to open or save their work. The main menus
    are on the menubar. The use of these menus is discussed in <xref
    linkend="menu-bars" />.
  </para>

  <para>
    &gnum; also uses context menus to
    give users a quick way to access certain commands. The context
    menu will open up right under the mouse pointer when one of the
    secondary mouse buttons, usually the rightmost, is clicked. This
    menu is called a context menu because the entries in the menu are
    different depending on the location of the mouse pointer. The
    <guilabel>context</guilabel> menus are discussed in <xref
    linkend="context-menu" />.
  </para>

  <para>
    Both the main menus, on the menubar, and context menus may have
    submenus. A submenu is indicated by a small right-pointing
    arrow. To access a submenu, move the pointer
    down to the submenu entry. When the submenu opens, 
    move the pointer directly across into the submenu.
    When there is not enough room to the right
    of the currently open menu, submenus may open to the
    left. Note that the submenu will
    close if the mouse pointer moves into any other menu entry.
  </para>

  <para>
    You can also use the keyboard to navigate menus and submenus.
    See <xref linkend="menu-bars" /> to access the main menus using the keyboard.
    Once a menu is displayed, menu entries can be highlighted by pressing the
    down and up arrow keys. When a submenu opens, pressing the right
    arrow key moves the highlight to the first entry of the submenu. When
    a submenu entry is highlighted, pressing the left arrow key removes
    the highlight from the submenu. Pressing the space bar or the <keycap>Enter</keycap>
    key activates the highlighted menu entry.
  </para>

  <para>
    Menu entries ending with an ellipsis (three dots) open a dialog window which
    asks for more choices.
  </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="menu-bars">
    <title>Menubar</title>    

    <para>
      The default location of the menubar is at the top of the
      application window.  The menus provide quick and organized access
      to all major commands such as opening files, saving files,
      printing and quitting the application.
    </para>

    <figure id="menubar.png">
    <title>The Gnumeric menubar.</title>
    <screenshot>
      <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/menubar.png" />
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>An image of the &gnum; menubar.</phrase>
            </textobject>
           </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
    </figure>


    <para>
      To open a &gnum; menu, click on the name of the menu in the menu bar.
      Once clicked, the menu will stay open.
      If the mouse pointer is moved to the name of another menu on the
      menubar, the first menu will close and the new menu open up. This is a useful way
      to look in each menu to hunt for a commands. Menus can also be
      opened through the keyboard.
      Pressing and holding the <keycap>Alt</keycap> key causes 
      one of the letters in each menu name to be underlined.
      Press-and-hold <keycap>Alt</keycap> and press the underlined letter
      to open the associated menu.
      Using the keyboard for menu activation or navigation causes
      a letter of each menu or submenu item label to be underlined.
      Press that letter key to activate the menu item.
      Once a menu is open, the arrow keys can be used to move between
      menus or select an entry in a particular menu.
      To close an open menu, click over any other area of the application
      or of the desktop or press the Escape key, <keysym>Esc</keysym>.
    </para>

    <para>
      Many menu entries are followed by a series of key names. These
      keys can be used to perform the menu action without having to
      open the menu.  These are often combinations of keys involving
      the control key which is labeled as <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>, the
      shift key which is labeled <keycap>Shift</keycap> and the
      function keys which are labeled with an <keycap>F</keycap> and
      then a number. For example, to quickly cut a selection
      (accessible through the <guimenu>Edit</guimenu> menu), the user
      can make a selection and then type the control key and the "x"
      key at the same time.
    </para>

  </sect2>




  <!-- ************************  FILE MENU   *************************** -->
  <sect2 id="File-Menu">
    <title>File Menu</title>

    <para>
      The <guimenu>File</guimenu> menu is the most important menu in
      &gnum; because it gives the user
      the ability to interact with the computer operating system. This
      menu allows the user to create files containing all the work
      they have done. It also enables users to print the results of
      their work. Finally, the <guimenu>File</guimenu> menu is the
      best way to close &gnum;.
    </para>

    <figure id="menu-file-labelled.png">
      <title>The <guimenu>File</guimenu> menu.</title>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/menu-file-labelled.png" />
          </imageobject>
          <textobject>
            <phrase>An image of the File menu.</phrase>
          </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>

    <para>
      The menu choices are grouped into the following groups:
    </para>


    <para>
      <variablelist>

      <varlistentry>
	<term>
	  <emphasis role="bold">1</emphasis>
	    Workbook creation operations.
	</term>

	<listitem>
	  <para>These menu items perform operations on files. Each item is
	  presented below. File operations are critical and are therefore
	  discussed in their own section latter in this manual in <xref
	  linkend="chapter-files" />. </para>
	 <itemizedlist>

      	    <listitem>
     	      <para>
     	        <guimenuitem>New</guimenuitem> &mdash; Create a new
                workbook. This opens a new workbook in a new
                window. By default the workbook will be named "Book1"
                or another number if there is already a worksheet with
                that name open. Note that the opened file has not yet
                been saved.
     	      </para>
     	    </listitem>

      	    <listitem>
     	      <para>
     	        <guimenuitem>New From Template</guimenuitem> &mdash; This 
                menu item brings up a submenu from which a template can be selected.
                Rather than creating a new empty workbook, the template 
                specifies some standard content. The new workbook is opened in a new
                window. The name named of the workbook is determined by the name
                of the template. Note that the opened file has not yet
                been saved.
     	      </para>
     	    </listitem>

     	    <listitem>
     	      <para>
     	        <guimenuitem>Open</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
	        <guimenuitem>Open</guimenuitem> menu item opens the
	        file chooser dialog to allow the user to pick an
	        existing workbook for &gnum; to open. Files in many
	        different spreadsheet formats can be opened.
		To open files in  a non-spreadsheet format,
		use the <guimenuitem>Data</guimenuitem> menu described in
		<xref linkend="Data-Menu"/>. See <xref
	        linkend="sect-file-formats" /> for details.  The
	        <guimenuitem>Open</guimenuitem> menu item creates a
	        new window containing the selected file.  A more
	        extensive discussion is presented in <xref
	        linkend="sect-file-open" />.
      	      </para>
     	    </listitem>

          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
	<term>
	  <emphasis role="bold">2</emphasis>
	    File creation operations.
	</term>
	<listitem>
	  <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <guimenuitem>Save</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
		<guimenuitem>Save</guimenuitem> menu item saves the
		current worksheet. If the file has been named and
		saved before, this will silently save the file to the
		current filename. If it has not been saved before,
		this will act as if the <guimenuitem>Save
		As...</guimenuitem> menu item had been called and
		prompt the user for a filename.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <guimenuitem>Save As...</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
		<guimenuitem>Save As...</guimenuitem> menu item allows
		users to save a file which has not yet been named to a
		named file. This is always used when a user saves a
		file which &gnum; has named by default.  This menu
		item can also be used to save a newly created file or
		to save an existing file to a new and different
		name. To export data from &gnum; to a non-spreadsheet format,
		use the <guimenuitem>Data</guimenuitem> menu described in
		<xref linkend="Data-Menu"/>. 
		For an explanation of the file formats which
		&gnum; supports see <xref linkend="sect-file-save"/>.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
	<term>
	  <emphasis role="bold">3</emphasis>
	    Printing operations.
	</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    These menu items enable
	    &gnum; to print. Each item is
	    presented below and printing issues are discussed fully in
	    <xref linkend="chapter-printing" />.
          </para>
	  
	 <itemizedlist>
 	    <listitem>
	      <para>
 	        <guimenuitem>Page Setup...</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
                <guimenuitem>Page Setup...</guimenuitem> menu item
                call the <guilabel>Page Setup</guilabel> dialog. This
                dialog allows the user to set various printing options
                such as paper type, margin sizes and running header
                and footer formats. This dialog is explained in detail
                in <xref linkend="sect-printing-setup" />.
  	       </para>
  	      </listitem>

 	    <listitem>
	      <para>
 	        <guimenuitem>Print Area</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
                <guimenuitem>Print Area</guimenuitem> menu item
                opens the submenu shown in <xref linkend="menu-file-printarea.png" />.
                The items in this submenu allow the print area to be set, 
                shown or cleared; and manual page breaks to be set or cleared. 
		The print area of a sheet is that range 
                of the sheet that should be printed. Items outside of the
                print area are usually omitted when printing. When printing
		&gnum; will usually choose the appropriate page breaks. Manual
		page breaks can be used to force &gnum; to insert a page break 
		prematurely.
  	       </para>
    <figure id="menu-file-printarea.png">
      <title>The <guimenu>Print Area</guimenu> submenu.</title>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/menu-file-printarea.png" />
          </imageobject>
          <textobject>
            <phrase>An image of the Print Area submenu.</phrase>
          </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>
  	      </listitem>
  	      <listitem>
   	      <para>
   	        <guimenuitem>Print...</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
		<guimenuitem>Print...</guimenuitem> menu item allows a
		user to print one or all of the worksheets in a
		workbook. &gnum; can send files directly to a
		printer or can print to PostScript or portable
		document format files. The <guilabel>Print</guilabel>
		dialog is explained further in <xref
		linkend="sect-printing" />.
         </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para>
                <guimenuitem>Print Preview...</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
		<guimenuitem>Print Preview...</guimenuitem> menu item
		calls a dialog which presents the current workbook as
		it would be printed with the current <guilabel>Page
		Setup</guilabel> settings. The dialog also permits the
		user to print. This dialog is explained in <xref
		linkend="sect-printing-preview" />.
         </para>
        </listitem>

		   
		</itemizedlist>
		
      </listitem>


	
      </varlistentry>



	<!-- summary -->
      <varlistentry>
		<term>
		  <emphasis role="bold">4</emphasis>
	  Miscellaneous Operations.
	</term>
	<listitem>
	 <itemizedlist>
 	   <listitem>
	      <para>

 	         <guimenuitem>Send To...</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
	         <guimenuitem>Send To...</guimenuitem> menu item call
	         the <guilabel>Send To</guilabel> dialog. This dialog
	         allows the user to send a &gnum; workbook as an
	         attachment to an email message. This dialog is
	         explained in detail in <xref
	         linkend="sect-files-email" />.
	  </para> 
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	  <para>
	    <guimenuitem>Document Properties...</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
	    <guimenuitem>Document Properties...</guimenuitem> menu item calls
	    the <guilabel>Document Properties</guilabel> dialog, a 
        dialog with several tabs that allow many document specific
        settings to be adjusted. The dialog is described in detail in
        <xref linkend="chapter-workbooks" />.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	 </itemizedlist>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>

	<!-- recent files -->
      <varlistentry>
	<term>
          <emphasis role="bold">5</emphasis>
	  Recently used files.
	</term>
	<listitem>
        <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    The first three menu entries in this section are shortcuts to 
        re-open recently used
	    files.  The list will change dynamically as new workbooks
	    are opened and created.  Clicking on a file name listed
	    here is the same as using the
	    <guimenuitem>Open</guimenuitem> menu entry and finding the
	    file in the <guilabel>Find File</guilabel> dialog. Note
	    that if the file has been moved since
	    &gnum; last saved it,
	    &gnum; will not find the
	    file. To access any recent file not listed, one can use the
	    <guimenuitem>Full History...</guimenuitem> menu item below.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	  <listitem>
	  <para>
	    <guimenuitem>Full History...</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
	    <guimenuitem>Full History...</guimenuitem> menu item opens a dialog
        that shows all recently used files.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	 </itemizedlist>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      
      
      <varlistentry>
	<term>
          <emphasis role="bold">6</emphasis>
          The Close and Quit operations.
	</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    These menu items either close the current worksheet,
	    <guimenuitem>Close</guimenuitem>, or close all open
	    worksheets, <guimenuitem>Quit</guimenuitem>. &gnum; will
	    prompt the user with a <guilabel>Save
	    Workbook..</guilabel> dialog for any workbooks that have
	    been changed since the last time they were opened or
	    saved.
	  </para>
	  
	  <itemizedlist>
      	    <listitem>
     	      <para>
     	       <guimenuitem>Close</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
	       <guimenuitem>Close</guimenuitem> menu item allows the
	       user to close the current workbook. If this is the only
	       workbook which this instance of
	       &gnum; has open, the close
	       operation will also quit
	       &gnum;. If other workbooks
	       are open, this workbook will close without affecting
	       the others.  If the workbook has unsaved changes,
	       &gnum; will ask the user
	       if he wants to save the file.
     	      </para>
     	   </listitem>

      	    <listitem>
     	      <para>

     	       <guimenuitem>Quit</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
	       <guimenuitem>Quit</guimenuitem> menu item will close
	       all the workbooks currently being used by
	       &gnum; and quit the
	       program. &gnum; will
	       prompt the user asking if he wants to save any
	       workbooks which has changes which have not been saved.

     	      </para>
     	   </listitem>
		   
		</itemizedlist> 
	  </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
	  
      </variablelist>
    </para>		

  </sect2>


  <!--  ******************************** EDIT MENU    ******************** -->
  <sect2 id="Edit-Menu">
    <title>Edit Menu</title>

    <para>
      The <guimenu>Edit</guimenu> menu is mostly used for operations
      on a worksheet or between worksheets. This menu gives users
      powerful editing operations such as the ability to undo recent
      changes, the ability to cut and paste selections of cells and
      the ability to search for specific cell contents.
    </para>
		
    <figure id="menu-edit-labelled.png">
		    <title>The <guimenu>Edit</guimenu> menu.</title>
		    <screenshot>
		      <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/menu-edit-labelled.png" />
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>An image of the Edit menu.</phrase>
            </textobject>
           </mediaobject>
		    </screenshot>
    </figure>

    <para>
      The menu choices are grouped into the following groups:
    </para>



  <variablelist>
    
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
        <emphasis role="bold">1</emphasis>
	  Change History.
      </term>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  These menu items allow the user to remove recent changes to
	  a worksheet or re-introduce changes which have been
	  undone. These options give the user control over recent
	  edits. This functionality is often called the "change
	  history" of an application. </para>
	
	<para>
	  The type of edit has no importance. An edit which deletes
	  the contents of a cell is treated in the same way as an edit
	  which adds contents to a cell. The change history is session
	  specific. The user will not be able to undo changes through
	  the change history if the file is saved and then
	  re-opened. Note also that the list only covers the last few
	  dozen operations. The number of operations which &gnum;
	  tracks in its history depends on the size and complexity of
	  those operations. You can customize this number using the preference
	  facility described in <xref linkend="chapter-configuring" />. 
	  There are a few unusual operations which
	  are not yet tracked in this way.
	</para>
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <guimenuitem>Undo</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
	      <guimenuitem>Undo</guimenuitem> menu item is used to
	      remove the last few edits from a workbook. The edits
	      must be undone in order. This menu item removes only the
	      last edit from the workbook. The user can also access
	      the undo list through one of the toolbar buttons and its
	      associated menu.  With this menu, the user can undo
	      several operations at once. This is explained in section
	      <xref linkend="std-toolbar" />.  </para> </listitem>
	  
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <guimenuitem>Redo</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
	      <guimenuitem>Redo</guimenuitem> menu item is used after
	      an undo operation to restore the change that was undone.
	      The menu item only restores the last undone
	      operation. Users can also restore edit using a button on
	      the standard toolbar and through the associated
	      menu. The menu allows several operations to be redone at
	      once. It is explained in <xref linkend="std-toolbar" />.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    
    
    
    
    <!-- Cut, Copy, Paste, Paste Special... -->
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
	<emphasis role="bold">2</emphasis>
	  Operations on selected areas.
      </term>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	These menu items enable selected cell contents to be moved
	around a spreadsheet, moved between worksheets or between
	workbooks. Selections are areas of the spreadsheet that have
	been chosen, usually with the mouse, and are usually colored
	pale blue. Selections are explained in greater detail in <xref
	linkend="sect-data-selections" />.
	&gnum; currently only allows
	single range selections for these operations.
	</para>

	<para>
	  To use these menu items, the user must first select the range
	  of the cut or copy area. When the user then picks these
	  menu items, the contents of the selected areas will be
	  entered into the &gnum;
	  clipboard and into the X clipboard. The
	  contents of the &gnum;
	  clipboard can then be inserted into a new region of the
	  spreadsheet, into another worksheet or into a new
	  workbook. The X clipboard holds the space delimited results
	  of each cell: either the text or the result of any
	  calculation. The X clipboard can be pasted into any text
	  area.
	</para>

        <itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>

	    <para>
	      <guimenuitem>Cut</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
	      <guimenuitem>Cut</guimenuitem> menu item is used to
	      remove a selection from the selected area of a currently
	      open workbook. When the menu item is chosen, the
	      selected area will be outlined with a moving dotted
	      line. This is the area which will be moved. The
	      selection will only be removed after it is moved to the
	      new location. Until then cut has not had an effect on
	      the worksheet.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <guimenuitem>Copy</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
	      <guimenuitem>Copy</guimenuitem> menu item allows a user
	      to duplicate a selection. The original data remains
	      where it was and the &gnum;
	      clipboard (and the X clipboard) has a copy which can be
	      inserted elsewhere.

	    </para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <guimenuitem>Paste</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
	      <guimenuitem>Paste</guimenuitem> menu item is used to
	      paste the contents of a selection which has been cut or
	      copied. If the selection was cut, it is pasted into the
	      new location unchanged. Cell references will not change
	      in that they will still point to the same cells.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <guimenuitem>Paste Special...</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
	      <guimenuitem>Paste Special...</guimenuitem> is used to
	      paste a selection while altering certain
	      characteristics. The <guimenuitem>Paste
	      Special...</guimenuitem> menu item opens a dialog with
	      three categories. The defaults make <guimenuitem>Paste
	      Special...</guimenuitem> act as if it were the
	      <guimenuitem>Paste</guimenuitem> menu item.
	    </para>

    <figure id="menu-edit-paste-special.png">
		    <title>The Paste Special Dialog</title>
		    <screenshot>
		      <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/menu-edit-paste-special.png" />
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>An image of the Paste Special Dialog.</phrase>
            </textobject>
           </mediaobject>
		    </screenshot>
    </figure>



	    <para>
	      The first set of choices allow the user to control the
	      data pasted.The user can chose to limit the pasting to
	      only the cell contents (no cell formatting is copied) or ---
	      the opposite --- only cell formats copied (no
	      contents). Furthermore, the user can insert the
	      selection while transforming all the contents into
	      values only. In this case, formulae will not be copied, only the
	      results will be.
	    </para>
	    <para>
	      A second set of choices allows the user to perform
	      simple mathematical transformations during the
	      paste. The data in the cells being pasted into are
	      modified by the cell contents. For instance, using the
	      divide operation will result in each cell in the zone
	      pasted into being divided by the equivalent cell which
	      was copied originally.
	    </para>
	    <para>
	      The third set of choices allow the transposition or flip of the
	      original selection. The
	      <guilabel>transpose</guilabel> choice will change the
	      selection by flipping it about the diagonal from top left to 
	      bottom right. Similarly, <guilabel>flip horizontally</guilabel> and 
	      <guilabel>flip vertically</guilabel> paste the selection accordingly.
	    </para>
	    <para>The <guilabel>skip
	      blanks</guilabel> check box prevents
	      &gnum; from taking any
	      action for the cells in the selection that are
	      blank. Normally &gnum; will modify formulae that use relative 
	      addressing to cells outside the selection. The <guilabel>do not
	      change formulae</guilabel> checkbox suppresses this change. (Note that 
	      references to cells within the selection are always preserved.)
	    </para>
	  </listitem>

	</itemizedlist>
	  
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>


	<varlistentry>
		<term>
			<emphasis role="bold">3</emphasis>
			Data entry and removal operations.
		</term>
		<listitem>
			<para>These operations add or remove data from the worksheet. They
			differ in the type of data modified or removed and the possible
			re-arrangement of remaining data, as explained below. With one
			exception noted below, these operations are like the previous group
			in acting based on the selected cells.
			</para>


		<itemizedlist>
      	    	<listitem>
<!-- Do NOT introduce any whitespace AROUND the <anchor>. -->
     	      	<para><anchor id="edit-menu-clear-links"
     	      		  xreflabel="Clear&nbsp;&#9654; Formats &amp; Hyperlinks"
			  /><guimenuitem>Clear</guimenuitem> opens a submenu
			with eight choices, organized into two sets of four.
			The first group affects all cells in the selection.
			The second group applies the same actions to just the
			selected cells that are in rows selected by the filter.
			See <xref linkend="sect-data-filter" />
			for details of setting up a filter.
			</para>
		<para>
			Choose <guimenuitem>All</guimenuitem> to clear all
			the elements of the cells in the selection: the formats and hyperlinks,
			the comments, and the contents.
			Choose <guimenuitem>Formats &amp; Hyperlinks</guimenuitem>
			to clear the formats and hyperlinks while leaving the data or
			formula in the cell intact.
			This removes any borders, re-sets the cell alignments, changes the
			background colour to white and the text colour to black,
			resets the number format to <guilabel>General</guilabel>, and removes
			the hyperlink associated with each cell, if any.
			Choose <guimenuitem>Comments</guimenuitem> to delete the
			comments for the cells in the selection.
			Choose <guimenuitem>Contents</guimenuitem> to leave the
			cell's formatting in place but remove the formula or data
			contents of the cell.
			</para>
     	   		</listitem>

      	    	<listitem>
      	    	<para>
      	    		<guimenuitem>Delete</guimenuitem> opens a submenu
      	    		with five choices. They permit deleting a range of rows or
      	    		columns, deleting just the
      	    		selected cells, or deleting just the comments or hyperlinks
      	    		associated with the selected cells.
      	    	</para>
     	      	<para>
     	      		Choose <guimenuitem>Columns</guimenuitem> or
     	      		<guimenuitem>Rows</guimenuitem> to delete the columns or rows,
			respectively, that cover the cells in the selection.
			Selecting <guimenuitem>Rows</guimenuitem> when the selection
			is one or more columns or <guimenuitem>Columns</guimenuitem>
			when the selection is one or more rows deletes all cells in the
			worksheet.
			The space left by deleted rows is filled by moving lower rows up.
			The space left by deleted columns is filled by moving to the
			left columns which were right of the selection.
			For example, if columns D and E are deleted,
			&gnum; will move the contents of all columns from F onwards two
			columns to the left.
		</para>
		<para>
			<guimenuitem>Cells...</guimenuitem>: If the selection is one or more
			columns or one or more rows, <guimenuitem>Cells...</guimenuitem>
			deletes the selected columns or rows as described above.
			If the selection is a block of cells, <guimenuitem>Cells...</guimenuitem>
			opens a dialog asking how to fill in the deleted cells. Blocks of
			cells can be filled in by the columns of cells below the block
			selection or by the rows on the right of the block. 
		</para>

    <figure id="menu-edit-delete-cells.png">
		    <title>The Delete Cells Dialog</title>
		    <screenshot>
		      <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/menu-edit-delete-cells.png" />
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>An image of the Delete Cells Dialog.</phrase>
            </textobject>
           </mediaobject>
		    </screenshot>
    </figure>

				 <para>
				 For example, if the
				 block of cells from E6:G8 is deleted, those cells would be
				 filled in by the cells below E8, F8 and G8 if the <guilabel>Shift cells
				 up</guilabel> option were chosen. The cells to the right
				 of G6, G7 and G8 would fill in the space from the right if the
				 <guilabel>Shift cells left</guilabel> option were chosen. The
				 two <guilabel>Delete</guilabel> choices are the same as
				<guimenuitem>Edit &#9654; Delete &#9654; Rows</guimenuitem> and
				<guimenuitem>Edit &#9654; Delete &#9654; Columns</guimenuitem>.
				 </para>
		<para>
			<guimenuitem>Comments</guimenuitem>: This is the same as
			<guimenuitem>Edit &#9654; Clear &#9654; Comments</guimenuitem>,
			described above.
		</para>
		<para>
			<guimenuitem>Hyperlinks</guimenuitem>: This is similar
			to <guimenuitem>Edit &#9654; Clear &#9654; Formats &amp;
				Hyperlinks</guimenuitem>, as described above, except
			that existing cell formats are not disturbed.
		</para>
     	   		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    <guimenuitem>Modify</guimenuitem> opens a submenu with three choices:
		    </para>
		  <itemizedlist>
		    <listitem>
		      <para>
		        <guimenuitem>Comment...</guimenuitem> opens the
		        <guimenu>Edit Cell Comment</guimenu> dialog.
		        This is the same as the dialog for
		        <guimenuitem>Comment...</guimenuitem> on the
		        <xref linkend="Insert-Menu" />.
		        See <xref linkend="sect-data-comment" /> for more information.
		        </para>
		      </listitem>
		    <listitem>
		      <para>
		        <guimenuitem>Hyperlink...</guimenuitem> opens the
		        <guimenu>Hyperlink</guimenu> dialog.
		        This is the same as the dialog for
		        <guimenuitem>Hyperlink...</guimenuitem> on the
		        <xref linkend="Insert-Menu" />.
		        See <xref linkend="sect-data-link" /> for more information.
		        </para>
		      </listitem>
		    <listitem>
		      <para>
		        <guimenuitem>Names...</guimenuitem> opens the
		        <guimenu>Define Names</guimenu> dialog.
		        <xref linkend="sect-data-names" />
		        explains names and describes the dialog.
		        </para>

		      </listitem>
		    </itemizedlist>
			</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
		<term>
	            <emphasis role="bold">4</emphasis>
			Search and replace operations.
		</term>
		<listitem>

	 		<itemizedlist>

      	    	<listitem>
     	      	<para>
     	       	<guimenuitem>Search...</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
			       <guimenuitem>Search...</guimenuitem> menu item opens a dialog
				 to search for cells with particular content. The dialog has
				 three tabs. In the first the user can enter the information
				 the user wants to find and some constraints on the search. The
				 second tab gives some extra choices for the search. When the
				 user has picked the options they prefer, pushing the search
				 button on the first tab will run the search. The third tab
				 will show which cells match the search.
				 </para>
     	   		</listitem>

      	    	<listitem>
     	      	<para>
     	       	<guimenuitem>Search &amp; Replace...</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
			       <guimenuitem>Search &amp; Replace..</guimenuitem> menu item
				 will launch a dialog to find cells with particular
				 characteristics and replace them all with a common content.
				 This dialog is similar to the <guilabel>Search</guilabel>
				 dialog.
				 </para>
     	   		</listitem>

		    </itemizedlist>
		    </listitem>

	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
		<term>
	            <emphasis role="bold">5</emphasis>
			Other operations on worksheets.
		</term>
		<listitem>

	 		<itemizedlist>
      	    	<listitem>
     	      	<para>
                  <guimenuitem>Sheet</guimenuitem> &mdash; From the
                  <guimenuitem>Sheet</guimenuitem> submenu you can perform operations
                  on the worksheet as a whole. These functions are also available
                  from the worksheet tab context menu. You can create, duplicate,
                  rename, re-order, or delete worksheets. These functions are
                  described in detail in
                  <xref linkend="sect-worksheets-managing-process-contextmenu" />.
		</para>
     	   		</listitem>

      	    	<listitem>
     	      	<para>
     	       	<guimenuitem>Select</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
			       <guimenuitem>Select</guimenuitem> menu item allows the user
				    to select various portions of the worksheet. When selected
                    it opens a submenu.
 				 </para>

    <figure id="menu-edit-select.png">
		    <title>The Select Submenu</title>
		    <screenshot>
		      <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/menu-edit-select.png" />
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>An image of the Select Submenu.</phrase>
            </textobject>
           </mediaobject>
		    </screenshot>
    </figure>


	            <itemizedlist>
     	   		  <listitem>
				    <para>The
				      <guimenuitem>All</guimenuitem> item provides a quick way to
				      select the entire worksheet. 
				    </para>
     	   		</listitem>

      	    	<listitem>
				    <para>
				      The <guimenuitem>Row</guimenuitem> and <guimenuitem>Column
                      </guimenuitem>
				      items allow the user to select all the rows or columns 
				      spanned by the current selection.
				    </para>
     	   		</listitem>

      	    	<listitem>
				    <para>
				      The <guimenuitem>Array</guimenuitem> menu item allows a
				      user to select all the cells which are part of the same array
				      as the current cell. 
				    </para>
     	   		</listitem>

      	    	<listitem>
				    <para>
				      The <guimenuitem>Depends
                      </guimenuitem> 
				      menu item selects all the cells which contain formula that
				      reference data in the current cell. 
				    </para>
     	   		</listitem>

      	    	<listitem>
				    <para>
				      Similarly, the <guimenuitem>Inputs
                      </guimenuitem> 
				      menu item selects all the cells whose data is referenced
                      by the formula in the current cell. 
				    </para>
     	   		</listitem>

      	    	<listitem>
				    <para>
				      The <guimenuitem>Next Object
                      </guimenuitem> 
				      menu item selects the next sheet object on the current sheet.
                      If no object is selected it will select the object locate at
                      the front.
				    </para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    The <guimenuitem>Go to Top</guimenuitem>,  
		    <guimenuitem>Go to Bottom</guimenuitem>,
		    <guimenuitem>Go to the First</guimenuitem>, 
		    <guimenuitem>Go to the Last</guimenuitem>,
		  menu items move the selection within a rectangular block of data cells.
		  the front.
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		
      	    	<listitem>
     	      	<para>
     	       	<guimenuitem>Goto cell...</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
			       <guimenuitem>Goto cell...</guimenuitem> menu item opens up a
				   dialog which allows the user to type the name or address of 
                    a cell in
				   the worksheet. The current view will then change to ensure
				   that the selected cell is in the current view and the
				   selection will cover that cell.
				 </para>
     	   		</listitem>
	            </itemizedlist>
     	   		</listitem>

      	    	<listitem>
     	      		<para>
     	       		<guimenuitem>Recalculate</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
			       	  <guimenuitem>Recalculate</guimenuitem> menu item forces
					the workbook to recalculate its results. This is useful
					if a formula in the current worksheet depends on a cell in
					a different workbook. &gnum; will not necessarily know
					when that data has been updated so a user can force
					&gnum; to recalculate all the cells in the current
					workbook.
     	      		</para>
     	   		</listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>
	</listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
		<term>
	            <emphasis role="bold">6</emphasis>
			General Configuration of
            &gnum;.
		</term>
		<listitem>
                <para>
                    <guimenuitem>Preferences...</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
                    <guimenuitem>Preference...</guimenuitem> menu item calls
                    the <guilabel>&gnum; Preferences</guilabel> dialog 
                    explained in detail in <xref linkend="chapter-configuring" />
                </para>
	    </listitem>
	</varlistentry>

  </variablelist>
</sect2>


  <!-- *************************** View Menu *********** -->
  <sect2 id="View-Menu">
    <title>View Menu</title>

 


    <para>
      The <guimenu>View</guimenu> menu is 
    </para>
		
    <figure id="menu-view-labelled.png">
      <title>The <guimenu>View</guimenu> menu.</title>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/menu-view-labelled.png" />
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>An image of the View menu.</phrase>
            </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>
	
    <para>
      The menu choices are grouped into the following groups:
    </para>



    <variablelist>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <emphasis role="bold">1</emphasis>
          Alternative views of the current document.
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            These menu items allow the user to open multiple views of
            the same document. 
          </para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <guimenuitem>New View...</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
                <guimenuitem>New View...</guimenuitem> menu item opens
                up a new window with the current workbook visible.
                and where both windows are open to the same section of
                the workbook. If the user starts editing a different
                part of the sheet in one view, the other view moves
                automatically to that portion of the
                worksheet. Similarly, if the user changes to a
                different worksheet in one view, the other view
                changes also.
<!-- TODO: are views 'shared' or 'unshared'? To what extent? -->
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <guimenuitem>Freeze Panes</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
                <guimenuitem>Freeze Panes</guimenuitem> menu item is
                used to freeze the top-most and leftmost visible
                portion of the worksheet. This is useful to be able to
                line up portions of the worksheet which are not
                usually together. For instance, if a user had a very
                large table with the titles of each column of data on
                row 12, the user could select row 13 and select this
                menu item.  If the user scrolled through each data
                row, the data would line up underneath each header.
              </para>
              <para> There are 3 ways to determine which rows and/or 
                columns should be frozen.
              </para>
              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    If the selection is at least partially visible and does
                    not include the cell
                    A1, &gnum; freezes the
		            portion of the worksheet above or to the left of the 
                    current selection. 
                 </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    If the selection is at least partially visible, 
                    includes cell A1, and does not consist
                    of whole rows or columns,
                    &gnum; freezes all rows or columns intersecting the
                    selection.
                 </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    If the selection is at least partially visible, 
                    includes cell A1, and consists
                    of whole rows or columns,
                    &gnum; freezes those rows or columns.
                 </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>If the
		            selection is not visible at all, then &gnum; freezes those 
                    rows and columns to the left or above the sixth visible column
                    and tenth visible row.
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
              <para>In all cases, the region of the worksheet above or to the left
                of the currently visible region will become inaccessible until the
                view is unfrozen.
              </para>
<!-- TODO: menu elements, freeze only row/col. -->
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <guimenuitem>Windows</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
                <guimenuitem>Windows</guimenuitem> menu item provides
		access to a submenu which lists all of the windows
		which are currently open. This provides an easy way to
		jump between all the different instances and views of
		&gnum; documents.
              </para>
            </listitem>


          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>



      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <emphasis role="bold">2</emphasis>
          Changes to the current view.
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            These menu items alter the display of the current view.
	  </para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <guimenuitem>Toolbars</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
                <guimenuitem>Toolbars</guimenuitem> menu item provides
                a submenu which lists each &gnum; toolbar. The
                toolbars in this submenu which have a check mark in
                front of their name will be shown. The display status
                of each toolbar can be changed by selecting the menu
                item with that toolbar's name. 
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <guimenuitem>View Statusbar</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
                <guimenuitem>View Statusbar</guimenuitem> menu item
                determines whether to display the status bar and
                information area at the bottom of each
                worksheets. Selecting the menu item toggles the check
                mark in front. When this menu item has the checkmark,
                &gnum; will display the statusbar.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <guimenuitem>Full Screen</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
                <guimenuitem>Full Screen</guimenuitem> menu item
                changes the display of &gnum; from a window based
                display to a display which occupies the whole
                screen. In full screen mode, the window borders will
                not be displayed nor will the toolbars. The key
                <keysym>F11</keysym> toggles between full screen and
                regular display mode. When this menu item has the checkmark,
                &gnum; is in <guimenuitem>Full Screen</guimenuitem> mode.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <guimenuitem>View Properties...</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
                <guimenuitem>View Properties...</guimenuitem> menu item opens the 
                <guimenuitem>View Properties</guimenuitem> dialog.
                </para> 

                <figure id="menu-view-properties-dialog.png">
                <title>The <guimenu>View Properties</guimenu> dialog</title>
                    <screenshot>
                        <mediaobject>
                            <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="figures/menu-view-properties-dialog.png" />
                            </imageobject>
                            <textobject>
                            <phrase>An image of the View Properties dialog.</phrase>
                            </textobject>
                        </mediaobject>
                    </screenshot>
                </figure>

                <para>The <guimenu>View Properties</guimenu> dialog has four tabs.
                    <guimenu>Auto Completion </guimenu>is described in 
                    <xref linkend="sect-worksheets-settings" />, 
                    <guimenu>Protection</guimenu> in
                    <xref linkend="sect-worksheets-settings-protection" />.
                </para>

                <figure id="menu-view-properties-dialog-cm.png">
                <title>The <guimenu>View Properties</guimenu> dialog, <guimenu>Cell Markers</guimenu> tab</title>
                    <screenshot>
                        <mediaobject>
                            <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="figures/menu-view-properties-dialog-cm.png" />
                            </imageobject>
                            <textobject>
                            <phrase>An image of the Cell Markers tab of the View Properties dialog.</phrase>
                            </textobject>
                        </mediaobject>
                    </screenshot>
                </figure>

                <para>The check boxes on the <guimenu>Cell Markers</guimenu> tab shown in 
                    <xref linkend="menu-view-properties-dialog-cm.png" /> determine
                    whether cells are shown with indicators that they contain formulae and/or 
                    that they have clipped content.
                </para>

                <para>The check boxes on the <guimenu>Widget</guimenu> tab shown in 
                    <xref linkend="menu-view-properties-dialog.png" /> determine
                    whether the notebook tabs, the horizontal scrollbar and/or 
                    the vertical scrollbars are shown in this view.
                </para>
            </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <emphasis role="bold">3</emphasis>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <guimenuitem>Zoom...</guimenuitem> opens a dialog where you can set
            the magnification of one or more worksheets in the current workbook.
          </para>
        </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>


	</variablelist>
  </sect2>


  <!--  *********************************** INSERT MENU ********************* -->
  <sect2 id="Insert-Menu">
    <title>Insert Menu</title>

    <para>
      The <guimenu>Insert</guimenu> menu is 
    </para>

    <figure id="menu-insert-labelled.png">
      <title>The <guimenu>Insert</guimenu> menu.</title>
        <screenshot>
	  <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/menu-insert-labelled.png" />
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>An image of the Insert menu.</phrase>
            </textobject>
           </mediaobject>
	 </screenshot>
    </figure>

    <para>
      The menu choices are grouped into the following groups:
    </para>

    <variablelist>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>
	  <emphasis role="bold">1</emphasis>
	  Insert into workbook.
	</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    These menu items alter the cells available in a workbook. 
	  </para>
	  <itemizedlist>

	   <listitem>
	     <para>
	       <guimenuitem>Cells...</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
	       <guimenuitem>Cells...</guimenuitem> menu item opens a
	       dialog asking the user how the sheet should be altered
	       when new cells are inserted. The dialog lists four
	       choices. The user can choose one of these by clicking
	       the mouse pointer on one of the four dots.  Only one
	       choice is possible and the currently selected choice
	       has a black dot in front.
	     </para>
	     <para>
	       The <guilabel>Shift cells right</guilabel> will insert
	       a region of new cells of the size of the current
	       selection. Cells which are on the same row as the
	       selection and within or to the right of the selection
	       will shift over to the right to accommodate the new
	       cells. The <guilabel>Shift cells down</guilabel> choice
	       will also insert a region of new cells the same size as
	       the current selection. With this choice, cells which
	       are in the selection or below the selection will move
	       down to accommodate the new cells. The two other
	       choices will act as if the user had chosen to insert
	       rows or columns. These actions are explained above.
	     </para>
	   </listitem>

	   <listitem>
	     <para>
	       <guimenuitem>Columns</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
	       <guimenuitem>Columns</guimenuitem> menu item will
	       insert columns to the left of the current
	       selection. The number of columns inserted will equal
	       the number of columns spanned by the current selection.
	     </para>
	   </listitem>

	   <listitem>
	     <para>
	       <guimenuitem>Rows</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
	       <guimenuitem>Rows</guimenuitem> menu item will insert
	       rows above the current selection. The number of rows
	       inserted will be equal to the number of rows spanned by
	       the current selection.
	     </para>
	   </listitem>

	    <listitem>
	      <para>
	        <guimenuitem>Sheet</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
		<guimenuitem>Sheet</guimenuitem> menu item allows the
		user to insert a worksheet immediately following the
		current sheet.
	     </para>
	   </listitem>

	 </itemizedlist>
       </listitem>
     </varlistentry>

<!-- TODO: add a separtor to insert menu. Sep. sheet obj. from cell content. -->

     <varlistentry>
       <term>
         <emphasis role="bold">2</emphasis>
	 Insert an object into the worksheet or content into the current cell.
       </term>

       <listitem>
         <para>
	   The menu items insert sheet objects into the worksheet or
	 insert content into the current cell.
	 </para>
	 <itemizedlist>

	   <listitem>
	     <para>
	       <guimenuitem>Graph...</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
	       <guimenuitem>Graph...</guimenuitem> menu item will
	       allow a user to insert a graphic plot of data. This
	       menu item will launch the graph druid. Graphing in
	       &gnum; is explained in
	       <xref linkend="chapter-graphs" />.
	     </para>
	   </listitem>

	   <listitem>
	     <para>
	       <guimenuitem>Image...</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
	       <guimenuitem>Image...</guimenuitem> menu item will
	       allow a user to insert a graphic object containing the
	       image from an external file. The use of images in
	       &gnum;  is explained in
	       <xref linkend="sect-graphics-images" />.
	     </para>
	   </listitem>

<!-- TODO: bonobo build where are insert obj/ins. shaped obj. ? -->
<!--
	   <listitem>
	     <para>
	       <guimenuitem>Object...</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
	       <guimenuitem>Object...</guimenuitem> menu item launches
	       a dialog with the objects which
	       &gnum; is currently able
	       to embed in a worksheet. The user simply picks one of
	       the objects in the list, and then inserts the object
	       into the worksheet. These objects are not part of
	       &gnum; but are provided by
	       other programs in the GNOME project.
	     </para>
	   </listitem>

	   <listitem>
	     <para>
	       <guimenuitem>Shaped Object...</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
	       <guimenuitem>Shaped Object...</guimenuitem> menu item
	       allows user to insert more complicated objects into a
	       worksheet. This is currently not used but will provide
	       more extended functionality for the future.
	     </para>
	   </listitem>
-->

	   <listitem>
	     <para>
	       <guimenuitem>Function</guimenuitem> &mdash; This menu item
		opens a dialog to allow the user to enter a
		mathematical formula into the cell. The function
		dialog includes the names and a brief explanation of
		all the available functions.
	     </para>
	   </listitem>
	   <listitem>
	     <para>
	       <guimenuitem>Function Wrapper</guimenuitem> &mdash; 
	       Selecting an item from the submenu shown in <xref linkend="menu-insert-fw.png"/>
	       replaces every rectangular region in the current selection with an array function
	       in which the appropriate function is wrapped around an array version of the 
	       current content. This can be used to create a self-sorting data region. 
	     </para>
    <figure id="menu-insert-fw.png">
      <title>The <guimenu>Function Wrapper</guimenu> submenu.</title>
        <screenshot>
	  <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/menu-insert-fw.png" />
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>An image of the Function Wrapper submenu.</phrase>
            </textobject>
           </mediaobject>
	 </screenshot>
    </figure>
	   </listitem>

	   <listitem>
	     <para>
	       <guimenuitem>Name...</guimenuitem> opens a dialog with a 
	       list of all defined names that can be pasted into
	       the current cell.
	       The dialog is similar to the <guimenu>Define Names</guimenu> dialog
	       opened by choosing <guimenuitem>Modify&nbsp;&#9654; Names...</guimenuitem>
	       from the <xref linkend="Edit-Menu" />.
	       See <xref linkend="sect-data-formulas-names" /> for details.
	     </para>
	   </listitem>

	   <listitem>
	     <para>
	       <guimenuitem>Comment...</guimenuitem> opens a dialog where
		you can enter or edit a comment for the active cell. 
		The dialog is described in <xref linkend="sect-data-comment" />.
	     </para>
	   </listitem>

	   <listitem>
	     <para>
	       <guimenuitem>Hyperlink...</guimenuitem> opens a dialog for entering the
	       location of a link. The dialog is described in <xref linkend="sect-data-link" />.
	       </para>
	   </listitem>

	   <listitem>
	     <para>
	       <guimenuitem>Special</guimenuitem> opens a submenu from which
	       you can insert predefined content into a cell.
	       You can insert the current date, the current time, or both.
	     </para>
	   </listitem>

	 </itemizedlist>
       </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>


</sect2>













  <!--  ************************************FORMAT MENU ********************* -->
  <sect2 id="Format-Menu">
    <title>Format Menu</title>

    <para>
      The <guimenu>Format</guimenu> menu allows users to control the
      formats of cells, columns, rows, worksheets and the
      workbook. This menu also gives users access to templates of
      standard formats.
    </para>

    <figure id="menu-format-labelled.png">
      <title>The <guimenu>Format</guimenu> Menu and Its <guimenu>Cells</guimenu>
      Submenu.</title>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/menu-format-labelled.png" />
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>An image of the Format menu and its Cells submenu.</phrase>
            </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>

    <!-- the list of format menu items -->
    <variablelist> 
      <varlistentry>
       <term><guimenu>The Format Menu</guimenu> offers these menuitems:</term>


       <listitem>
       <para>
         <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
           <para>
            <guimenuitem>Cells</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
	    <guimenuitem>Cells...</guimenuitem> menu item opens a submenu
	    with choices to allows the user to modify the formatting of the
	    selected cells.
	   </para>

	  <para>
	    <itemizedlist>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  <guimenuitem>Format...</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
		  <guimenuitem>Format...</guimenuitem> menu item opens the
		  cell format dialog. This dialog is used to set cell data
		  types and formats. It is explained in <xref
		  linkend="sect-data-format" />.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  <guimenuitem>Conditional Formatting...</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
		  <guimenuitem>Conditional Formatting...</guimenuitem> menu item 
		  opens the
		  conditional format dialog. This dialog is used to set cell data
		  types and formats that depend on values in the workbook.
		  It is explained in <xref
		  linkend="sect-data-format-conditional" />.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  <guimenuitem>Merge</guimenuitem> &mdash;
		  This menu item combines the current selection into a single
		  large cell.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  <guimenuitem>Unmerge</guimenuitem> &mdash;
		  This menu item divides a merged selection into the original
		  cells.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  <guimenuitem>Auto Fit Height</guimenuitem> &mdash;
		  This menu item makes &gnum;
		  automatically choose the optimal row heights to display
		  all of the text in the current selection.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  <guimenuitem>Auto Fit Width</guimenuitem> &mdash;
		  This menu item makes &gnum;
		  automatically choose the optimal column widths to display
		  all of the text in the current selection.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>
	  </para>
	  </listitem>

        <listitem>
         <para>

          <guimenuitem>Column</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
	  <guimenuitem>Column</guimenuitem> menu item opens a submenu
	  with choices to allows the user to modify the view of the
	  selected columns.
        </para>
    <figure id="menu-format-column.png">
      <title>The <guimenu>Column</guimenu> Submenu.</title>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/menu-format-column.png" />
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>An image of the Column submenu.</phrase>
            </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>

        <para>
	 <itemizedlist>
	   <listitem>
	     <para>
	     <guimenuitem>Width...</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
	     <guimenuitem>Width...</guimenuitem> menu item opens a
	     dialog to enable the user to adjust the size of the
	     columns which hold the current selection. The dialog has
	     a single entry box in which the user can change the
	     current size of the column in points.
	   </para>
	 </listitem>
	 <listitem>
	   <para>
	     <guimenuitem>Auto Fit Width</guimenuitem> &mdash;
	     This menu item makes &gnum;
	     automatically choose the optimal column size to display
	     all of the text in the current selection.
	   </para>
	 </listitem>
	 <listitem>
	   <para>
	     <guimenuitem>Hide</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
	     <guimenuitem>Hide</guimenuitem> menu item will hide the
	     columns containing the current
	     selection. &gnum; still
	     holds these columns in memory and will save them to a
	     file but will not display those columns. The only
	     indication that a user has that columns have been hidden
	     is that the column header names are not sequential.
	   </para>
	 </listitem>
	 <listitem>
	   <para>
	     <guimenuitem>Unhide</guimenuitem> &mdash; This menu item
	     will show columns which are hidden if the selection spans
	     the two columns on either side of the selection. If
	     columns D, E, and F have been hidden, the selection must
	     span at least across columns C and G for this menu item
	     to unhide columns D, E, and F.
	   </para>
	 </listitem>
	 <listitem>
	   <para>
	     <guimenuitem>Standard Width</guimenuitem> &mdash; This
	     menu item allows the user to resize the columns which
	     hold the selection to the standard size. At 100 percent
	     zoom this is 48 points or 64 pixels.
	   </para>
	 </listitem>
	 </itemizedlist>
	</para>
	</listitem>
	
	
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <guimenuitem>Row</guimenuitem> &mdash; The 
	    <guimenuitem>Row</guimenuitem>
	    menu item provides the same functions as the 
	    <guimenuitem>Column</guimenuitem>
	    menu item but operates on rows.
	    <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>
		  <guimenuitem>Height...</guimenuitem> &mdash; This menu item 
		  opens a
		  dialog which allows the user to type in a row height in pixels.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
		  <guimenuitem>Auto Fit Height</guimenuitem> &mdash; This menu
		  item
		  changes the rows which hold the selection to the optimal height
		  to hold the text in the selection. 
		</para>
	      </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
		  <guimenuitem>Hide</guimenuitem> &mdash; The 
		  <guimenuitem>Hide</guimenuitem> menu item will hide the rows
		  in the selection. The workbook still contains the data in the
		  hidden rows but those rows are not shown. 
		</para>
	      </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
		  <guimenuitem>Unhide</guimenuitem> &mdash; This menu item will 
		  make
		  hidden rows visible. The selection must span the rows which are
		  hidden for this menu item to unhide the hidden rows.
	        </para>
	      </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
		  <guimenuitem>Standard Height</guimenuitem> &mdash; This menu item 
		  resizes the rows back to the default height of 12.75 points or
		  17 pixels (at 100 percent zoom).
	        </para>
	      </listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>
	  </para>
        </listitem>
	

        <listitem>
<!-- Do NOT introduce any whitespace AROUND the <anchor>. -->
        <para><anchor id="format-menu-sheet"
          xreflabel="Format&nbsp;&#9654; Sheet"
          /><guimenuitem>Sheet</guimenuitem> opens a submenu where you can change
          properties of the current worksheet.
          With the exception of <guimenuitem>Manage Sheets...</guimenuitem> and
          <guimenuitem>Zoom...</guimenuitem>,
          all operations on this submenu apply to just the current worksheet.
        </para>
    <figure id="menu-format-sheet.png">
      <title><guimenu>Sheet</guimenu> Submenu</title>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/menu-format-sheet.png" />
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>An image of the Sheet submenu.</phrase>
            </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>

    <variablelist>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>
	  <emphasis role="bold">1</emphasis>
          Sheet Management
	</term>
	<listitem>
        <para>
            These items are also on the worksheet tab context menu, accessed
            by clicking
	       (usually with the right mouse button) on one of the
	       worksheet tabs.
        </para>
        <para>
          <guimenuitem>Manage Sheets...</guimenuitem> opens a dialog from
          which the names and many properties of all the sheets can be
          managed. Properties that can be managed from this dialog include
          locking, worksheet visibility, column display order (left to right
          or right to left), sheet name, sheet order, and sheet tab appearance.
          From this dialog you can also add new worksheets and duplicate
          or remove existing worksheets.
          For more information, see <xref linkend="sect-worksheets-managing-process-dialog" />.
        </para>
              <para>
                <guimenuitem>Rename...</guimenuitem> opens the <guilabel>Rename
                Sheet</guilabel> dialog. Edit the sheet name in the <guilabel>New
                Name:</guilabel> field and press <keysym>Enter</keysym> or click
                <guibutton>OK</guibutton> to change the worksheet name.
	        </para>
	      </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>
	  <emphasis role="bold">2</emphasis>
            Sheet Display Toggles
	</term>
	<listitem>
        <para>The second section contains various toggles that control how
            a worksheet is displayed.
            If a toggle is enabled, a small check mark is displayed to the left
            of the menu item.
        </para>
        <para>
		<itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  <guimenuitem>Display Formulas</guimenuitem> &mdash; When this property
                  is enabled, the worksheet will show the actual formulae for all cells
                  with formulae, instead of showing the calculated result.
                  You can use this property to quickly determine which cells contain data
                  and which contain formulae.
                </para>
	      </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  <guimenuitem>Use R1C1 Notation</guimenuitem> &mdash; When this property
                  is enabled, &gnum; uses R1C1-style notation to address cells,
                        rather than A1 notation.
	        			</para>
	      </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  <guimenuitem>Hide Zeros</guimenuitem> &mdash; When this property
                  is enabled, &gnum; displays all cells which would display a zero
                  value as empty cells.
                  This can be used to more easily find cells with non-zero data in
                  sheets with many zero results.
	        			</para>
	      </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  <guimenuitem>Hide Gridlines</guimenuitem> &mdash; When this property
                  is enabled, &gnum; does not draw the grid lines that ordinarily separate
                  cells.
	        			</para>
	      </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  <guimenuitem>Hide Column Headers</guimenuitem> &mdash; When this property
                  is enabled, &gnum; does not display the column headers, which leaves room
                  in the cell grid for roughly one more row of cells of default height.
	        			</para>
	      </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                <guimenuitem>Hide Row Header</guimenuitem> &mdash; When this property
                is enabled, &gnum; does not display the row headers, which leaves
                slightly more room to display the contents of cells.
	        			</para>
	      </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  <guimenuitem>Direction</guimenuitem> &mdash; When this menu item
                  is selected, &gnum; switches between left-to-right sheets and
                  right-to-left sheets. If row headers are displayed, they are moved
                  to the right-hand side of the cell grid when the worksheet
                  is displayed right to left.
	        			</para>
	      </listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	    </para>
	      </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <emphasis role="bold">3</emphasis>
          Zoom...
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <guimenuitem>Zoom...</guimenuitem> opens a dialog where you can set
            the magnification of one or more worksheets in the current workbook.
          </para>
        </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
         <para>
           <guimenuitem>Autoformat...</guimenuitem> &mdash; This menu item
	   opens the autoformat dialog to give user access to a list
	   of format templates.  Format templates are useful for users
	   who are often filling out tables in a particular
	   format. The user picks an area of the worksheet into which
	   they want to apply the template. Most templates define
	   headers and footers so the selection area must be big
	   enough to fit those template elements and the user's
	   data. The template will not affect data which has already
	   been input into a worksheet.
	 </para>
	 <para>
	   The dialog has two tabs: <guilabel>Preview</guilabel> and
	   <guilabel>Template Details</guilabel>. The details are
	   simply information about the template. The
	   <guilabel>Preview</guilabel> tab has three main options: a
	   <guilabel>Settings</guilabel> menu, an
	   <guilabel>Edit</guilabel> menu and a category chooser. The
	   settings menu allows a user to pick what parts of the
	   template they want to copy into the worksheet. The edit
	   menu will be used to create new templates. Currently
	   templates are written as text into an extensible markup
	   language (XML) format. The category chooser gives the user
	   access to different groups of templates.  Templates in each
	   category are displayed in the middle area of the
	   dialog. Users select the template they want to use by
	   clicking on it.  The currently selected template is
	   highlighted with a red boundary which may be hard to see.
	 </para>
       </listitem>

      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

  </sect2>



<!--   ********************* TOOLS MENU ************  -->
<sect2 id="Tools-Menu">
	<title>Tools Menu</title>

	<para>The <guimenu>Tools</guimenu> menu is </para>
		<figure id="menu-tools-labelled.png">
		    <title>The <guimenu>Tools</guimenu> menu.</title>
		    <screenshot>
		      <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/menu-tools-labelled.png" />
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>An image of the Tools menu.</phrase>
            </textobject>
           </mediaobject>
		    </screenshot>
	    </figure>
	<para>The menu choices are grouped into the following groups:</para>



 <variablelist>

      <varlistentry>
	<term>
	  <emphasis role="bold">1</emphasis>
	    Automatic tools
	</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>These two tools allow the user to make
	  &gnum; automatically correct
	  typing or automatically save workbooks at periodic
	  intervals.</para>
       <itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
		<para><guimenuitem>Auto Correct...</guimenuitem> &mdash;
		The <guimenuitem>Auto Correct...</guimenuitem> menu
		item opens a dialog which allows the user to configure
		the way in which &gnum; automatically corrects text
		which is being entered. The dialog presents the user
		with three tabs. Each of these tabs allows the user to
		correct one type of common spelling mistake, while
		allowing the user to add exceptions to the
		rules. &gnum; can
		automatically capitalize the names of week
		days. &gnum; can
		automatically change an entry which starts with two
		capital letters to only start with one and
		&gnum; can change a
		sentence entry to start with a capital letter.
						</para>
					</listitem>

		<listitem>
		<para>
		  <guimenuitem>Auto Save</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
		  <guimenuitem>Auto Save</guimenuitem> menu item opens
		  a dialog which allows the user to have
		  &gnum; automatically
		  save the current workbook after a fixed interval of
		  time. The user can also have
		  &gnum; ask for
		  confirmation before saving so that the user always
		  remains aware of the state the workbook was in when
		  it was saved.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
				</listitem>
      </varlistentry>

<!-- TODO: Split lp and scenarios when the 2 chpt.  are written. -->
      <varlistentry>
	<term>
	  <emphasis role="bold">2</emphasis>
	   Linear programming, scenario generation, simulation and statistical
        analysis tools
	</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    &gnum; can be used to solve
	    systems of linear equations and other mathematical
	    problems. These two dialogs enable access to these
	    tools. A full discussion of these tools is presented in
	    <xref linkend="sect-advanced-analysis-solver" />.
	  </para>
	  <itemizedlist>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>

	      <guimenuitem>Goal Seek</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
	      <guimenuitem>Goal Seek</guimenuitem> menu item opens a
	      dialog through which the user can configure
	      &gnum; to iteratively
	      search for a numeric value which solves a formula. This
	      dialog is explained in <xref
	      linkend="sect-advanced-analysis-goalseek" />.

	    </para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <guimenuitem>Solver</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
	      <guimenuitem>Solver</guimenuitem> menu item opens a
	      dialog through which the user can configure
	      &gnum; to solve linear
	      systems of equations.  This is explained in <xref
	      linkend="sect-advanced-analysis-solver" />.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <guimenuitem>Scenarios</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
	      <guimenuitem>Scenarios</guimenuitem> menu item displays
	      a submenu with two entries. The
	      <guimenuitem>View...</guimenuitem> menu item opens a
	      dialog in which the user can select previously defined
	      scenarios. The <guimenuitem>Add...</guimenuitem> menu
	      item opens a dialog in which the user can define the
	      contents of a new scenario.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <guimenuitem>Simulation</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
	      <guimenuitem>Simulation</guimenuitem> menu item opens a
	      multipaned dialog allowing the user to configure the
	      parameters for a simulation using linear modeling
	      constraints. 
	    </para>
	  </listitem>

	</itemizedlist>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
	<term>
	  <emphasis role="bold">3</emphasis>
	    The Plug-ins dialog.
	</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>This entry launches the plug-in management
	  dialog. Plug-ins are programs which are separate from
	  &gnum; but provide useful
	  functionality.  Some of the core parts of &gnum;, such as
	  Excel file format support, are actually plugins. This means
	  that a user who never uses Excel files can remove this
	  module from &gnum; and make
	  &gnum; use less memory.<!--
	  <xref linkend="Plugins" /> explains plug-ins in greater
	  detail.--></para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>


</variablelist>

</sect2>

<!--   ********************* Statistics MENU ************  -->
<sect2 id="Statistics-Menu">
  <title>Statistics Menu</title>
  
  <para>The <guimenu>Statistics</guimenu> menu is </para>
  <figure id="menu-statistics-labelled.png">
    <title>The <guimenu>Statistics</guimenu> menu.</title>
    <screenshot>
      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata fileref="figures/menu-statistics-labelled.png" />
	</imageobject>
	<textobject>
	  <phrase>An image of the Statistics menu.</phrase>
	</textobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
  </figure>
  <para>The
  <guimenuitem>Statistics</guimenuitem> menu and its submenus contain
  all available statistical analysis tools. These tools
  are explained in <xref linkend="chapter-stat-analysis" />.</para>
</sect2>

  <!-- ******************* THE DATA MENU   ************** -->
  <sect2 id="Data-Menu">
    <title>Data Menu</title>

    <para>
      The <guimenu>Data</guimenu> menu is 
    </para>

    <figure id="menu-data-labelled.png">
      <title>The <guimenu>Data</guimenu> menu.</title>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/menu-data-labelled.png" />
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>An image of the Data menu.</phrase>
            </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>

    <para>
      The menu choices are grouped into the following groups:
    </para>

    <variablelist>

      <varlistentry>
	<term>
	  <emphasis role="bold">1</emphasis>
	    Data Field tools.
	</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    These menu items allow the user to re-organize data.
	  </para>

	  <itemizedlist>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
	        <guimenuitem>Sort...</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
		<guimenuitem>Sort...</guimenuitem> menu item opens a
		dialog which allows users to sort a selection
		according to defined criteria. By default
		&gnum; sorts the rows in
		a selected area 
		depending on the contents of the cells in a particular
		column of each row. The sort criteria can be extended
		to calculate on the basis of the cells in several
		columns.  &gnum; can sort
		a selection using any number of rules. Rules can be
		added using the <guibutton>Add</guibutton>
		button. Rules with no column entered will be ignored
		or the user can remove these rules with the
		<guibutton>Remove</guibutton> button.
	      </para>

	      <para> 
	        For each rule, the dialog has an entry box in
	        which the column to be sorted must be entered. The
	        dropdown box (the little down pointing arrow) will
	        show a list of appropriate columns.  The user can
	        determine a sort order for the selection. The
	        <guibutton>Advanced</guibutton> button allows the user
	        to further characterize the sort criteria..
	      </para>

	      <para> If the first row of the selection is a header,
	        &gnum; can be told not to
	        shuffle this row during the
	        sort. &gnum; can also
	        sort columns based on the contents of cells in
	        specified rows, instead of shuffling rows on the basis
	        of columns, if the user toggles the
	        <guilabel>Sort</guilabel> to act right-left instead of
	        top-down.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>

	    <listitem>
	      <para>
	        <guimenuitem>Shuffle...</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
		<guimenuitem>Shuffle...</guimenuitem> menu item opens a
		dialog that allows users to shuffle a selection. Shuffling
		means to rearrange the cells in the selection into a random
		order. The dialog allows users to shuffle the data within a
		column, within a row, or within an area.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>

	    <listitem>
	      <para>
	        <guimenuitem>Fill</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
		<guimenuitem>Fill</guimenuitem> menu item opens a
		submenu that allows various forms of data to be created.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>

	    <listitem>
	      <para>
	        <guimenuitem>Filter</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
		<guimenuitem>Filter</guimenuitem> menu item opens a
		submenu with three entries: <guimenuitem>Add Auto
		Filter</guimenuitem>, <guimenuitem>Show
		All</guimenuitem>, and <guimenuitem>Advanced
		Filter</guimenuitem> entry. Filters are explained in
		<xref linkend="sect-data-filter" />.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>

	    <listitem>
	      <para>
	        <guimenuitem>Validate...</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
		<guimenuitem>Validate...</guimenuitem> menu item opens
		the cell format dialog to the validation
		tab. Validation is a means of constraining the
		contents of a cell either to have a certain value or
		to fall within a certain range.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>


	    <listitem>
	      <para>
	        <guimenuitem>Consolidate...</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
		<guimenuitem>Consolidate...</guimenuitem> menu item
		opens a dialog box through which a user can create
		derived information based on data in other worksheets.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>

	    <listitem>
	      <para>
	        <guimenuitem>Table...</guimenuitem> &mdash; 
	      </para>
	    </listitem>

	    <listitem>
	      <para>
	        <guimenuitem>Group and Outline</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
		<guimenuitem>Group and Outline</guimenuitem> menu item
		provides a submenu through which users can group rows
		or columns into units which can be collapsed to be
		hidden from view. These entries also allow users to
		alter the display of the grouping handles on the
		borders of the worksheet.

	      </para>
	    </listitem>

	  </itemizedlist>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
	<term>
	  <emphasis role="bold">2</emphasis>
	    Data Modifications or Import.
	</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    These entries allow user to convert data already in a worksheet or to 
        import external
	    data directly into a worksheet.
	    </para>
	    <itemizedlist>

	    <listitem>
	      <para>
	        <guimenuitem>Text to Columns...</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
		<guimenuitem>Text to Columns...</guimenuitem> menu item
		opens a dialog box through which a user can create
		derived information based on data in other worksheets.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>

	    <listitem>
	      <para>
	        <guimenuitem>Import Data</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
		<guimenuitem>Import Data</guimenuitem> menu item
		provides the following submenu:
	      </para>
	      <figure id="menu-data-import.png">
		<title>The <guimenu>Import Data</guimenu> submenu.</title>
		<screenshot>
		  <mediaobject>
		    <imageobject>
		      <imagedata fileref="figures/menu-data-import.png" />
		    </imageobject>
		    <textobject>
		      <phrase>An image of the Import Data submenu.</phrase>
		    </textobject>
		  </mediaobject>
		</screenshot>
	      </figure>
	      <para>
		The items in this submenu allow the user to import data
		from various non-spreadsheet formats. To open files in  a
		spreadsheet format,
		use the <guimenuitem>Open</guimenuitem> menu described in
		<xref linkend="File-Menu"/>. See <xref
	        linkend="sect-file-formats" /> for details.  These
	        submenu items create a
	        new window containing the selected file.  A more
	        extensive discussion is presented in <xref
	        linkend="sect-file-open" />.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>

	    <listitem>
	      <para>
	        <guimenuitem>Export Data</guimenuitem> &mdash; The
		<guimenuitem>Export Data</guimenuitem> menu item
		provides the following submenu:
	      </para>
	      <figure id="menu-data-export.png">
		<title>The <guimenu>Export Data</guimenu> submenu.</title>
		<screenshot>
		  <mediaobject>
		    <imageobject>
		      <imagedata fileref="figures/menu-data-export.png" />
		    </imageobject>
		    <textobject>
		      <phrase>An image of the Export Data submenu.</phrase>
		    </textobject>
		  </mediaobject>
		</screenshot>
	      </figure>
	      <para>
		The items in this submenu allows users to export the current
		file or sheet to a non-spreadsheet format. The 
		<guimenuitem>Repeat Export</guimenuitem> menu item repeats
		the last
		export in the current session or, if the file was recently
		imported, exports the file to the original source. 
		To save data from &gnum; in a spreadsheet format,
		use the <guimenuitem>Save As...</guimenuitem> menu described in
		<xref linkend="File-Menu"/>.
		For an explanation of the file formats which
		&gnum; supports see <xref linkend="sect-file-save"/>.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>

	  </itemizedlist>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>

    </variablelist>


  </sect2>





  <!--  *********************** HELP MENU *****************-->
  <sect2 id="Help-Menu">
    <title>Help Menu</title>

    <para>
      The <guimenu>Help</guimenu> menu is quite simple.
    </para>

    <figure id="menu-help-labelled.png">
      <title>The <guimenu>Help</guimenu> menu.</title>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/menu-help-labelled.png" />
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>An image of the Help menu.</phrase>
            </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>

    <para>
      The <guimenu>Help</guimenu> menu connects users to this manual,
      to the list of functions available for use in
      &gnum; and to the list of people
      who created this wonderful application.
    </para>

<!-- TODO: Split help from bug report. -->
    <!-- the help menu list -->
    <variablelist> 

      <varlistentry>
	<term>
	  <emphasis role="bold">1</emphasis>
	    Entries to find help and report a problem with &gnum;
	</term>

	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    These menu items allow the user to obtain help from
	    several sources or to report a problem with the program.
	  </para>

	  <itemizedlist>

	    <listitem>
              <para>
                <guimenuitem>Contents</guimenuitem> &mdash; This menu
                entry allows the user to launch the local help system
                and display this manual.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>

	    <listitem>
              <para>
                <guimenuitem>&gnum; on the Web</guimenuitem> &mdash;
                This menu entry allows the user to launch a web
                browser and explore the web site dedicated to &gnum;
                on the server used by the GNOME project.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>

	    <listitem>
              <para>
                <guimenuitem>Live Assistance</guimenuitem> &mdash;
                This menu entry allows the user to launch an Internet
                Relay Chat (IRC) client to join the GIMPnet network
                and the #&gnum; channel. This channel is used by the
                &gnum; developers. There is generally someone around
                who will, after a few minutes, notice a nice question
                and attempt to answer it.
	      </para>
	      <warning>
	        <para>
		  Live assistance is provided on a purely voluntary
                  basis. There are no guarantees that your question
                  will be answered or that the answer will be
                  correct. We generally try our best to answer
                  questions when they are asked politely and when the
                  user shows that they have at least looked in the
                  User Manual for an answer.
		</para>
	      </warning>
	    </listitem>

	    <listitem>
              <para>
                <guimenuitem>Report a Problem</guimenuitem> &mdash;
                This menu entry allows the user to launch a web
                browser and open the page on GNOME's GitLab issue/
				        bug entry system for the &gnum; program. This page
                includes instructions on submitting reports of
                problems. The first time a user reports a problem,
                they will be asked to login to the system.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>

          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
	<term>
	  <emphasis role="bold">2</emphasis>
	    The <interface>About &gnum;</interface> dialog.
	</term>

        <listitem>
         <para>
          <guimenuitem>About</guimenuitem> &mdash;Shows basic
          information about &gnum;, such
          as the authors' names and the application version number.
         </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

  </sect2>


</sect1>


<!--  *********************** CONTEXT MENUS *****************-->
<sect1 id="context-menu">
	<title>Context Menus</title>

<!-- TODO: add info area context menu. -->
<!-- TODO: add text entry context menu. -->

	<para>Context menus are menus which open up under the mouse pointer and are
	therefore detached from the format graphical structure
	of the application. These menus provide an extra and convenient way to access
	&gnum; commands. All of the commands in context menus are available
	through the regular menu system. Context menus provide different commands
	depending on the position of the pointer.</para>

	<para>To activate a context menu, a user simply positions the pointer over
	the appropriate area and clicks one of the buttons on their mouse. Since this
	button is configurable and users have mice with different buttons, it may be a
	different button on any given machine or may even require the combination of a
	keyboard key and a mouse buttons. The user will have to find how to do this
	themselves.</para>

  <para>
    Currently &gnum; provides five different context menus. The
    context menu that is called in the central grid area is discussed
    next in <xref linkend="menu-context-grid" />. The Context menu
    that appears when the pointer is over the row headers or column
    headers is presented in <xref
    linkend="menu-context-col-row-header" />. Another context menu
    relates to the worksheet tabs and is explained in <xref
    linkend="menu-context-tabs" />. Yet another context menu applies
    to embedded objects or shaped components such as a plot. These are
    shown in <xref linkend="menu-context-object" />.
  </para>


  <sect2 id="menu-context-grid">
    <title>The Context Menu for the Cell Grid Area</title>

    <para>
      The context menu in the cell grid area appears when the pointer
      is over the cell grid area. This menu applies to the cells that
      have been selected, not necessarily the cell underneath the
      mouse pointer.
    </para>
		<figure id="menu-context-grid.png">
		    <title>The Context Menu for the Cell Grid Area.</title>
		    <screenshot>
		      <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/menu-context-grid.png" />
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>An image of the context menu in the cell grid area.</phrase>
            </textobject>
           </mediaobject>
		    </screenshot>
	    </figure>
	<para>
	  The grid context menu merely provides an extra way to access &gnum;
	  commands. The <guimenuitem>Cut</guimenuitem>, <guimenuitem>Copy</guimenuitem>, 
	  <guimenuitem>Paste</guimenuitem>, <guimenuitem>Paste Special</guimenuitem>,
	  <guimenuitem>Delete Cells...</guimenuitem>,
	  <guimenuitem>Clear Contents</guimenuitem>,
	  <guimenuitem>Remove Comment</guimenuitem>, <guimenuitem>Edit Hyperlink</guimenuitem>,
	  and <guimenuitem>Remove Link</guimenuitem>
	  commands are taken from the  <guimenu>Edit</guimenu> menu and its submenus and are 
	  explained in <xref linkend="Edit-Menu" />. The
	  <guimenuitem>Insert Cells...</guimenuitem> and <guimenuitem>Add Comment</guimenuitem>
	  menu items are explained in the section on the <guimenu>Insert</guimenu> menu
	  in <xref linkend="Insert-Menu" />. The <guimenuitem>Format Cells...</guimenuitem>, 
	  <guimenuitem>Conditional Formatting...</guimenuitem> items as well as the items
	  on the
	  <guimenu>Cell</guimenu>, <guimenu>Column</guimenu>, and <guimenu>Row</guimenu>
	  submenus are explained in the manual section on the <guimenu>Format</guimenu> menu
	  in <xref linkend="Format-Menu" />.
	</para>
</sect2>


<sect2 id="menu-context-col-row-header">
	<title>The Context Menu for Column and Row Headers</title>
	<para>The Context Menu for Column and Row Headers</para>
		<figure id="menu-context-col-row-header.png">
		    <title>The Context Menu of a Row Header</title>
		    <screenshot>
		      <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/menu-context-col-row-header.png" />
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>An image of the context menu on a row header.</phrase>
            </textobject>
           </mediaobject>
		    </screenshot>
	    </figure>
	<para>The context menu which relates to column or row headers is similar to
	the context menu for the grid area. Both insert and delete operations are
	modified to operate explicitly on rows or on columns.
	</para>


</sect2>

  <sect2 id="menu-context-tabs">
    <title>Context Menu for Worksheet Tabs</title>

    <para>
      The context menu for worksheet tabs provides access to functions
      that manipulate worksheets as a whole, rather than their contents.
    </para>

    <figure id="menu-context-tabs.png">
      <title>The Context Menu for Worksheet Tabs</title>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/menu-context-sheet-tabs.png" />
          </imageobject>
          <textobject>
            <phrase>An image of the context menu of the worksheet tabs.</phrase>
          </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>
    <para>
      The context menu for the worksheet tabs provides the same functions as the
      <guimenuitem>Sheet</guimenuitem> submenu of the <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
      menu. These functions are explained in
      <xref linkend="sect-worksheets-managing-process-contextmenu" />.
      There are also two submenus where you can select one of the
      existing sheets, whether its tab is currently visible or not.
      The first submenu lists the sheets in their current order, 
      the second submenu lists them alphabetically.
    </para>

  </sect2>


  <sect2 id="menu-context-object">
    <title>The Context Menu for Embedded Objects and Components</title>

    <para>
      The Context Menu for Embedded Objects and Components.
    </para>

    <figure id="menu-context-object.png">
      <title>The Context Menu for Graphical Objects</title>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/menu-context-object.png" />
          </imageobject>
          <textobject>
            <phrase>An image of the context menu on embedded objects.</phrase>
          </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>

    <para>
      All embedded objects, such as drawing elements, graphs and
      images, have a context menu which can be invoked by placing the
      mouse pointer over the element and clicking with one of the
      secondary mouse buttons.
    </para>

    <para>
      The first menu entry, labeled
      <guimenuitem>Properties</guimenuitem>, will open a dialog
      specific to the type of element selected in which the user can
      configure the properties of the element.
    </para>

    <para>
      The menu entry labeled
      <guimenuitem>Size &amp; Position</guimenuitem>, will open a dialog
      that permits the user to adjust the size and position of the embedded object.
    </para>

    <para>
      The menu entry labeled
      <guimenuitem>Snap to Grid</guimenuitem>, enlarges the object such that all of
        its corners are located at cell corners.
    </para>

    <para>
      The menu entry labeled <guimenuitem>Order</guimenuitem>,
      opens a submenu which allows the user to change the visual order
      in which the graphical elements are placed. This order will
      affect the way in which the graphical elements obscure each other.
    </para>

    <figure id="menu-context-object-order.png">
      <title>The Context Submenu for Graphical Object Order</title>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/menu-context-object-order.png" />
          </imageobject>
          <textobject>
            <phrase>An image of the context submenu allowing the
            re-ordering of graphical objects.</phrase>
          </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>


    <para>
      The menu entries labeled <guimenuitem>Cut</guimenuitem>,
      <guimenuitem>Copy</guimenuitem>, and
      <guimenuitem>Delete</guimenuitem>, allow the user to operate on
      the whole object at once. The <guimenuitem>Cut</guimenuitem>
      menu item allows the user to remove the element from its current
      position and then paste the object in a different location on
      the same sheet, in a different worksheet, in a different
      &gnum; file, or in a file from a different program entirely. The
      <guimenuitem>Copy</guimenuitem> menu item provides the same
      functionality while leaving the original item in place. The
      <guimenuitem>Delete</guimenuitem> allows the user to remove the
      graphical element entirely.
    </para>

    <para>
      The remaining menu item, <guimenuitem>Print</guimenuitem>, allows just the
      selected object to be printed. 
    </para>

    <para>
      For certain types of objects, a menu entry labeled <guimenuitem>Save
      As Image...</guimenuitem> 
      allows the object to be saved as an image file. This menu item
      is not present in <xref linkend="menu-context-object.png"/> but is shown in 
        <xref linkend="menu-context-graph.png"/> .
    </para>

    <figure id="menu-context-graph.png">
      <title>The Context Menu for Graphs and Images</title>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/menu-context-graph.png" />
          </imageobject>
          <textobject>
            <phrase>An image of the context menu for graphs and images.</phrase>
          </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>

    <para>
        Graphs have a context menu that also contains menu entries labeled <guimenuitem>Open in
        New Window</guimenuitem> and <guimenuitem>Copy to New Graph Sheet</guimenuitem>.
	The <guimenuitem>Open in New Window</guimenuitem> menu item shows the graph by
	itself in a window. The <guimenuitem>Copy to New Graph Sheet</guimenuitem> copies
	the graph to a special sheet in the current workbook that contains only a single graph. 
    </para>



</sect2>

<sect2 id="menu-context-toolbars">
	<title>The Context Menu for Toolbars</title>
		<para>The Context Menu for Toolbars</para>
		<figure id="menu-context-toolbars.png">
		    <title>The Context Menu for Toolbars.</title>
		    <screenshot>
		      <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/menu-context-toolbars.png" />
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>An image of the context menu on the toolbars.</phrase>
            </textobject>
           </mediaobject>
		    </screenshot>
	    </figure>
	<para>
	  The context menu for toolbars allows the user to configure toolbars.
	  Each toolbar can be displayed above the sheets, to the left of the sheets,
	  or to the right of the sheets. The context menu can also be used to hide a
	  toolbar. The toolbar can be made visible again via the
	  <guimenuitem>Toolbars</guimenuitem> submenu of the <guimenu>View</guimenu>
	  menu. See <xref linkend="View-Menu"/>.
	</para>

</sect2>

</sect1>

