<sect1 id="keybindings">
  <title>Gnumeric Keybindings</title>
  <para>
    Keybindings are combinations of keystrokes which tell an application to
    run a task.  These can greatly speed-up the user's interactions
    with an application.  Some of the most common ones are
    <keycombo>
      <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
      <keycap>s</keycap>
    </keycombo>
    to save a file or
    <keycombo>
      <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
      <keycap>q</keycap>
    </keycombo>
    to quit the application.  <application>Gnumeric</application> also
    comes with keybindings to make your spreadsheet exprience faster.
  </para>

  <para>
    Normally, keybindings are next to a command in a menu.  For
    example, if 
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenuitem>Save</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>
    has
    <keycombo>
      <keycap>Ctl</keycap>
      <keycap>s</keycap>
    </keycombo>
    next to it, that means that
    <keycombo>
      <keycap>Ctl</keycap>
      <keycap>s</keycap>
    </keycombo>
    can be typed at the same time to save your file.  However, some
    keystrokes aren't listed in the menus.  They are as follows:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
	<keycap>F2</keycap> sets the current cell for editing.  The
	cursor is inserted at the end of the current text.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
	<keycap>F3</keycap> opens the <interface>Load file</interface>
	dialog window.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
	<keycap>Ctl-F3</keycap> opens the <interface>Define Name</interface>
	dialog window.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
	<keycap>F5</keycap> opens the <interface>Go to</interface>
	dialog window which allows you to jump to a specified cell.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
	<keycap>F6</keycap> opens the <interface>Search and
	Replace</interface> dialog where you can search through your
	spreadsheets for text strings and replace them with something
	else.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
	<keycap>F7</keycap> opens the <interface>Search
	Center</interface>.  The <interface>Search Center</interface>
	allows you to search through your spreadsheets for text
	strings.
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>
	<keycap>Ctl-~</keycap> Formats the current selection as a number.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
	<keycap>Ctl-$</keycap> Formats the current selection with the default currency
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
	<keycap>Ctl-#</keycap> Formats the current selection with default date style
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
	<keycap>Ctl-^</keycap> Formats the current selection as using scientific notation
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
	<keycap>Ctl-@</keycap> Formats the current selection with the default time format
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
	<keycap>Ctl-!</keycap> Formats the current selection with the default accounting format
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
	<keycap>Ctl-&amp;</keycap> Adds a thin border around the current selection
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
	<keycap>Ctl-_</keycap> Removes any borders around or in the current selection
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
	<keycap>Ctl-$</keycap> Formats the current selection as the default currency
      </para>
    </listitem>

  </itemizedlist>
</sect1>
