<sect1 id="sect-morehelp">
  <title>Getting Help using Gnumeric</title>

  <para>
    This manual is the most complete source of explanation for
    <application>Gnumeric</application> and attempts to describe as
    much of the program as possible. However, this manual is not yet
    complete and there are many situtations which cannot be explained
    through a manual. There are several other sources of information
    which might be helpful.
  </para>

  <warning>
    <para>
      Several of the sources of information below involve talking
      directly with the people who have created
      <application>Gnumeric</application>. These people are volunteers
      who have spend several years working on the program to make it
      useful. They will all be glad to help you
      <emphasis>but</emphasis> only if they decide they want to. They
      are all busy and only volunteer on this project. You can take
      several steps to make these people want to help you.
    </para>

    <para>
      First, please look carefully through this manual to see if you
      can answer your own question. This can be hard and requires
      careful thinking but will teach you the most. Second, look at
      the <application>Gnumeric</application> web site, look on the
      world wide web for explanations using other spreasheets or look
      for a book on how to use another spreadsheet. Finally, if you
      want to meet the developers and ask for their help directly then
      be nice. If you are using their program, consider introducing
      yourself and thanking them for their work. Then be polite as you
      talk to them. They are all nice people but may sound brisk
      because that is how they talk to each other. These developers
      will not spend time to make sure you do not become offended
      because they do not want to offend you. They want to help you
      quickly and then get back to their own work. Please assume they
      respect you and want to help you, after all they have written a
      program for you to use.
    </para>
  </warning>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="sect-morehelp-web">
  <title>The Gnumeric Web Site and Other Web Resources</title>

  <para>
      
  </para>

</sect1>



<sect1 id="sect-morehelp-books">
  <title>The Gnumeric Web Site</title>

  <para>
    <application>Gnumeric</application> strives to mimic the behaviour
    of other spreadsheets so books which explain how to use these
    other spreadsheets will probably be useful to help understand
    <application>Gnumeric</application>.
  </para>

</sect1>


<sect1 id="sect-morehelp-maillist">
  <title>The Gnumeric Mailing List</title>

  <para>
    
  </para>

</sect1>



<sect1 id="sect-morehelp-irc">
  <title>Joining the Gnumeric Discussion Channel</title>

  <para>
    
  </para>

</sect1>



<sect1 id="sect-morehelp-bugs">
  <title>Reporting Bugs in the Program</title>

  <para>
    
  </para>

</sect1>

