<sect1 id="scenarios">
  <title>Scenarios</title>

 <para>A scenario is a set of values for specified cells that Gnumeric
  saves and can later substitute automatically in the worksheet.  Use
  scenarios to compare outcomes of a worksheet model using different
  inputs for the model.  You can, for instance, add a scenario for the
  worst case, an average case and the record sales figures and then
  switch between the scenarios to perform what-if analyses.</para>

  <sect2 id="scenario-add">
    <title>Adding New Scenarios</title>

    <para>In order to add new scenarios, select tools menu and click
     `Scenarios->Add...'.  A dialog for adding new scenarios should
     now appear on the screen.  Each scenario on a worksheet should
     have a unique name that is given on the first entry box.</para>

    <para>Changing cells determine the cells whose values are to be
     stored.  The values are read directly from the worksheet so if
     you want to store values other than the current values on the
     worksheet then press the close button, make your changes into the
     sheet and re-enter the scenario tool.  If changing cells contain
     formulas, only the current value of a formula is stored (not the
     formula itself).  Thus, when the scenario is later shown the
     formula is replaced with the stored value.  Also note that all
     changing cell references should refer to the current
     worksheet.</para>

    <para>You can also store a comment about the scenario.  When
     everything is ready press the ok button to add the new
     scenario.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="scenario-view">
    <title>Doing What-If Analyses Using Scenarios</title>

    <para>In order to perform what-if analyses with scenarios, select
     tools menu and click `Scenarios->View...'.  To compare all
     scenarios at once, you can create a scenario summary report by
     pressing `Summary Report' button.  The summary report is written
     into a new worksheet.</para>

    <para>To view a scenario, select the scenario you want to show
     from the scenario list according to its name, and then press
     `Show' button.  Gnumeric then updates the changing cells of the
     scenario with the stored values and you can see the effects on
     your worksheet.  Switching between scenarios is easy; just select
     the one you want to see and press `Show'.</para>

    <para>In order to delete a scenario, select it from the list of
     scenarios and press `Delete' button.  If you accidentially
     deleted a scenario you can press cancel button to recover the
     changes.</para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>

  <!-- Keep this comment at the end of the file
  Local variables:
  mode: sgml
  sgml-omittag:t
  sgml-shorttag:t
  sgml-minimize-attributes:nil
  sgml-always-quote-attributes:t
  sgml-indent-step:2
  sgml-indent-data:t
  sgml-parent-document:nil
  sgml-exposed-tags:nil
  sgml-local-catalogs:nil
  sgml-local-ecat-files:nil
  End:
  -->             
