<sect1 id="solver-chapter">
  <title>Solver</title>

  <para>With Gnumeric Solver you can solve linear programs.</para>

  <sect2>
    <title>Introduction to Linear Programming</title>

    <para>A linear program (LP) is a problem that can be expressed as
    linear functions.  As you probably already know, a linear function
    is the one whose graph is always a straight line.  Thus each
    variable of it appears in a separate term with its coefficient.
    There must be no products or quotients of these variables.  In
    addition, the exponent of each term must be one.  No logarithmic,
    exponential, trigonometric terms are allowed.  Especialy note that
    functions like ABS, IF, MAX, and MIN are not linear.  Here are a
    few examples of linear functions:</para>

    <programlisting>
    3x + y - 5z
    -3.23x + 0.33y
    -0.3x + 4y - 2z + 1.2m
    </programlisting>

    <para>The linear problem has a so called objective function which
    is to be minimized or maximized and constraints.  The objective
    function is the one whose value we would like to optimize.
    Typically, this function could determine the profit generated by
    the expected sales of the given model (maximization problem), or,
    the cost of the production in the given environment (minimization
    problem).  Anyway, on purely mathematical point of view, we could
    examine the following objective function:</para>

    <programlisting>
    Maximize 2x + 3y - z
    </programlisting>

    <para>In linear programming the variables of this functions are
    not allowed to take any values (otherwise the maximum of any
    objective function would be infinity).  The problem also has
    constraints.  The constraints are a set of linear functions and a
    set of their right hand side values (RHS).  For example, for the
    previously defined objective function we have the following
    constraints:</para>

    <programlisting>
    x + y &lt;= 5           (#1)
    3x - y + z &lt;= 9      (#2)
    x + y &gt;= 1           (#3)
    x + y + z = 4        (#4)
    x, y, z &gt;= 0         (non-negativity assumption)
    </programlisting>

    <para>This constraint set consists of three unequality constraints
    (#1-#3) and one equality constraint (#4).  Their RHS values are 5,
    9, 1, and 4.  In addition, we also have the non-negativity
    assumption.  That is, all the variables (x, y, and z) have to take
    only positive numbers.  The idea is to find the optimal values for
    the variables (x, y, and z) but also to satisfy all the given
    constraints.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title>Spreadsheet Modeling</title>

    <para>To solve optimization problems with Gnumeric you have to
    type in the problem into a sheet.  A recomended way to start with
    is to allocate a separate column in the spreadsheet for each
    decision variable (in the previous example the x, y, and z) and a
    separate row for each constraint (the constraints #1-#4).  The
    coefficients of these variables should be placed into the cells
    corresponding to the allocated row and the column.  It is also
    recomended that you label the rows and the columns to make the
    sheet much more readable.  The sheet for our maximization problem
    would look like this:</para>

    <figure id="linear-program-example">
      <title>Linear programming example</title>
      <screenshot>
        <graphic fileref="figures/solver-01.png"></graphic>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>

    <para>As you can see, we have put the model variables into cells
    B3:D3.  They are currently all zeros.  The cell E4 contains the
    objective function definition.  The easiest way to define it is to
    use SUMPRODUCT build-in function.  Thus in our model, we have the
    formula `=SUMPRODUCT(B3:D3,B4:D4)' in E3 .</para>

    <para>The constraints are defined in rows seven to ten.  Since the
    coefficients of these functions are in columns B, C and D we will
    get the total sum of each of the constraint using the formula
    `SUMPRODUCT(B$3:D$3,Bn:Dn)' where n is the row number of
    the constraint.  For example, in E7 we have
    `=SUMPRODUCT(B$3:D$3,B7:D7)', in E8 `=SUMPRODUCT(B$3:D$3,B8:D8)'
    and so on.  The right hand side (RHS) values of the constraints
    are typed into cells G7:G10.</para>

    <para>Now it is time to select `Solver...' from the `Tools' menu.
    After you have done it, the following dialog will appear:</para>

    <figure id="solver-dialog-1">
      <title>The empty Solver dialog.</title>
      <screenshot>
        <graphic fileref="figures/solver-02.png"></graphic>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>

    <para>Since we have the objective function in E3 type this into
    the `Set Target Cell:' entry.  We are about to maximize this
    function, thus the radiobutton `Max' should be pressed on.  By
    default, the problem is assumed to be maximization problem.  The
    input variables (x, y, and z) were in cells B3:D3 so type the cell
    range into the `By Changing Cells:' entry.  Now we can add the
    constraints.  Click <mousebutton>Add</mousebutton> button and the
    following dialog will appear.</para>

    <figure id="solver-add-constraint-dialog">
      <title>Add constraint dialog.</title>
      <screenshot>
        <graphic fileref="figures/solver-03.png"></graphic>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>

    <para>Now type in the constraints (#1-#4) one by one.  The
    constraint dialog has three entry boxes.  Put a cell name of the
    total left hand side (LHS) cell into the `Left Hand Side:' entry
    box.  In our example, this would be E7 for the constraint #1, E8
    for constraint #2, and so on.  The combo entry in the middle
    defines the type of the constraint.  It can be<![CDATA[ `<=', `=',
    `>=' ]]> , or
    `Int'.  We will explain the `Int' constraints later.  In this
    example, you should select <![CDATA[ `<=' for constraints #1-#2, `>=' ]]>for
    #3, and `=' for constraint #4.  The last entry on the right takes
    the right hand side values of the constraints.  For constraints
    #1-#4 they should be 5, 9, 1, and 4 in this order.  After typing
    each constraint press <mousebutton>Add</mousebutton> button if you
    still want to add more constraints after this one, or, press
    <mousebutton>Ok</mousebutton> button after typing the last
    constraint.  When you have typed in all the constraints, the
    Solver dialog should look like this:</para>

    <figure id="solver-dialog-2">
      <title>The solver dialog</title>
      <screenshot>
        <graphic fileref="figures/solver-04.png"></graphic>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>

    <para>The order of the constraints does not matter.  If you want
    to change or delete a constraint click it and then press `Change'
    or `Delete' button.  If everything looks ok, we should check the
    current settings of the Solver options by pressing the
    <mousebutton>Options...</mousebutton> button.  Since the problem
    is a linear problem the checkbutton called `Assume linear model'
    should be checked on.  In addition, since we want the variables to
    be positive in our problem setting, in this case, we should also
    have the `Assume non-negative' button checked on.  Click
    <mousebutton>OK</mousebutton> when done.  Now it's time to press
    the <mousebutton>Solve</mousebutton> button.  If everything went
    ok, the following window will appear:</para>

    <figure id="solver-results">
      <title>The Solver results dialog</title>
      <screenshot>
        <graphic fileref="figures/solver-05.png"></graphic>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>

    <para>If you look the sheet, you will notice that X and Z are set
    to zero and Y is set to four.  It means that in the optimal
    solution Y=4 and X=Z=0.</para>

  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title>Integer Programming</title>

    <para>You can use the Solver tool also for integer programming
    (IP) and more generally mixed integer programming.  In integer
    programming some of the decision variables are required to take on
    integer values.  To do so, just add a constraint whose type is
    `Int'.</para>

  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title>Reporting</title>

    <para>Solver can produce various kinds of reports that can be very
    useful in practise.  Currently there are five types of reports
    that Solver can create for LP problems being solved.</para>

    <sect3>
      <title>Answer report</title>

      Answer report reports the optimal solution found.  It will give
      you the original values of the input variables with the optimal
      values.  In addition, it reports all the model constraints,
      their final values, right hand side values, binding status, and
      slack.

    </sect3>

    <sect3>
      <title>Sensitivity report</title>
    </sect3>

    <sect3>
      <title>Limits report</title>

      Limits report reports the attchieved optimal value all the input
      variables of the model with the optimal values and with upper
      and lower bound for the optimal value in with the particular
      variable could vary without changing the optimal solution.

      If an optimal value for a variable x is 4, for example, and the
      lower bound is 2.4 and upper bound 5.9, then x could take any
      value between 2.4 and 5.9, and still all the same constraints
      were binding as with the optimal value 4.  In limits report, you
      can also find the value of the target cell for both upper
      and lower bound values for the variable.  For example, if the
      optimal value where x is 4 leads to a profit of $5,000, limits
      report specifies that if x is set to 2.4 the profit drops to
      $3,640.

    </sect3>

    <sect3>
      <title>Performance report</title>

      In a performance report you will have various statistical
      information about the problem, required computing time for
      solving the problem, and various other information.

    </sect3>

    <sect3>
      <title>Program report</title>

      In a program report you will have the optimization problem
      defined for the solver in a mathematical form.  The output is
      nicely formatted especially if you have placed proper labels for
      each variable and constraint in the model.

      A program report can be very useful, for example, if you want to
      check that you have defined the problem correctly for the tool.
      It is easy to make a mistake or two if you have large programs
      to be solved.

    </sect3>

  </sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="goal-seek">
  <title>Goal Seek Tool</title>

  <para>Use Goal Seek Tool to search for a value of a single model
  variable that yields a given desired value of another single
  variable.  For example, you can use the Goal Seek to find the
  break-even value for sales (the break-even is the amount of sales
  whose marginal revenue just covers the fixed costs and the profit is
  thus zero).</para>

  <sect2>
    <title>Using the Tool</title>

    <para>First, select the ``Goal Seek...''  tool item from ``Tools''
    menu.  Specify the output variable cell (``Set Cell'') by typing
    the cell reference into the entry or by clicking the worksheet
    cell.  If you are searching for the break-even point, for example,
    you should specify the cell reference of the profit calculation
    here.</para>

    <para>Specify the desired result for the output variable cell into
    the ``To Value'' cell.  In the search for the break-even, specify
    this to be zero.</para>

    <para>Specify the input variable cell (``By changing cell'') by
    typing the cell reference into the entry or by clicking the
    worksheet cell.  In the search for the break-even, specify the
    cell reference of the sales here.  When you have done this, you
    may want to press the ``Apply'' button to start the tool.</para>

  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title>Results</title>

    <para>Gnumeric will systematically iterate the model by changing
    the input value to achieve the desired result, if possible.  If
    goal seek was successful the tool displays the message ``Goal
    Seeking with cell __ found a solution''.</para>

    <para>It is possible that Gnumeric does not find a solution that
    generates the desired result.  There may not be such a solution
    for the model, or, it may be too difficult to find.  For example,
    the mathematical function behind the calculation may have many
    non-continuous points.</para>

  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title>Desired Value in a Given Range</title>

    <para>If Gnumeric did not find a solution that generates the
    desired result, you may want to try to specify a range (minimum
    and maximum) in which the value of the output variable should be.
    To do this, specify the ``Minimum'' and ``Maximum''
    entries.</para>

  </sect2>

</sect1>