<sect1 id="start-first">
  <title>Starting Gnumeric the First Time</title>
  
  <para>
	To start <application>Gnumeric</application> click on the 
	<guibutton>Main Menu</guibutton> button to open the 
	<guimenu>Main Menu</guimenu> and click on the 
	<guimenu>Applications</guimenu> menu and finally click on the 
	<guibutton>Gnumeric</guibutton> button.  The main window of 
	<application>Gnumeric</application> will appear as shown 
	in shown in <xref linkend="worksheet-all-1.png" />
  </para>

  <figure id="worksheet-all-1.png">
    <title>An example of the entire worksheet.</title>
    <screenshot>
      <graphic fileref="images/worksheet-all-1" format="png"></graphic>
    </screenshot>
  </figure>

  <para>
	After opening up gnumeric, you're presented with a view of a
    worksheet. This is where the majority of the work on the
    spreadsheet is done. <citation>Miguel, Canty, Likin 1.1.1</citation>
  </para>
  
  <para>
	The worksheet view is split into several main areas. The menu
    bar, the main tool bar, the format tool bar, the entry area, 
	the object tool bar, the main cell area, and the
    info area. <citation>Miguel, Canty, Likin 1.1.1</citation>
  </para>

  <figure id="worksheet-all-notes.png">
    <title>A example of the entire worksheet with notes.</title>
    <screenshot>
      <graphic fileref="images/worksheet-all-notes" format="png"></graphic>
    </screenshot>
  </figure>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="files">
	<title>Opening and Saving Files</title>

  <para>
	When you first start <application>Gnumeric</application> a new book 
	will be opened.  To save the the book into a file for the first time 
	click on <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu><guimenuitem>Save As &hellip;
	</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.  This brings up the file dialog where you 
	can pick the filename and format for the book you are saving.  It is 
	best to save the book in the <guilabel>Gnumeric XML file format</guilabel>
	the first time.  This allows you to easily edit the file without worrying 
	about changes in the format and look of the book.  When you have already 
	saved the book you just need to click on the
	<inlinemediaobject>
	  <imagedata fileref="images/stock-save.png"/>
		<textobject>
		  <phrase>Save button</phrase>
		</textobject>
	</inlinemediaobject>
	in the tool bar or click on <menuchoice><shortcut><keysym>C-s
	</keysym></shortcut><guimenu>File</guimenu><guimenuitem>Save
	</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.
  </para>

  <para>
	Sometimes you want your book to be saved often so you do not lose any work.  
	To save the book at intervals click on <menuchoice><guimenu>Tools</guimenu>
	<guimenuitem>Auto Save &hellip;</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.  The <interface>
	Auto Save</interface> dialog appears.  
	<figure id="auto-save.png">
	  <title>Auto Save dialog</title>
	  <screenshot>
		<graphic fileref="images/auto-save" format="png"></graphic>
	  </screenshot>
	</figure>
	Click on the <guibutton>Automatic Save Every</guibutton> button and enter 
	the number of minutes will pass between each save.  When the interval is 
	shorter more of your work will be potentially saved, but 
	<application>Gnumeric</application> might appear sluggish.  If 
	<application>Gnumeric</application> is sluggish increase the time between 
	saves.  The button <guibutton>Prompt Before Saving</guibutton> brings up a 
	dialog to ask if you want to save the book.
  </para>

  <para>
	Open an book by clicking on <menuchoice><shortcut><keysym>F3</keysym></shortcut>
	<guimenu>File</guimenu><guimenuitem>Open</guimenuitem></menuchoice> or the 
	<inlinemediaobject>
	  <imagedata fileref="images/stock-open.png"/>
		<textobject>
		  <phrase>Open button</phrase>
		</textobject>
	</inlinemediaobject>	
	in the tool bar.  The <interface>Open</interface> dialog will appear.  You can 
	then select the spreadsheet file you wish to open.  
	<application>Gnumeric</application> can open many different types of spreadsheet 
	file formats.  Currently the supported formats are &file-format-open;.
  </para>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="highlighting">
  <title>Highlighting Cells</title>
  
  <para>
	The main cell area contains a grid of boxes which are called 
	<link linkend="cells">cells</link>.  When a cell is highlighted each 
	row and column is also highlighted by changing the row and column 
	color from a light gray to a dark gray.  Click on a cell in the main 
	cell area to highlight a single cell.  You will notice one column and 
	one row has turned to a darker gray and the letter and number is in 
	bold.  Also on the far left side of the entry area the cell's designation 
	is displayed.  The cell designation is a letter and number corresponding 
	to the column and row respectively.
	<figure id="cells-2.png">
	  <title>Single Cell being Highlighted</title>
	  <screenshot>
		<graphic fileref="images/cells-2" format="png"></graphic>
	  </screenshot>
	</figure>
  </para>

  <para>
	Sometimes you need to highlight multiple cells.  Click on the cell you 
	want to start with and drag the mouse to highlight the desired cells.  
	This will highlight a box of cells with the starting cell being at 
	one of the corners of the box.
	<figure id="selection-3.png">
	  <title>Multiple Cells being Highlighted</title>
	  <screenshot>
		<graphic fileref="images/selection-3" format="png"></graphic>
	  </screenshot>
	</figure>
  </para>

  <para>
	There are some special situations that arise when you highlight cells. 
	The cells you want highlighted might be at two different places in the 
	sheet.  Highlight the first group of cells.  Then press the
	<keycap>Ctrl</keycap> key and highlight the second group of cells.  Both 
	groups of cells are now highlighted.  
	<tip>
	  <para>
	Make sure you hold down the 
	<keycap>Ctrl</keycap> key while you are highlighting the second group of 
	cells.  You cannot press the <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> key once, let go of the 
	key and then highlight the second group of cells.  This will not work.  You 
	need to hold down the <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> key while you are highlighting 
	the second group of cells.  This might take some practice for you to master 
	the skill.
	  </para>
	</tip>
  </para>

  <para>
	There is an easier way to highlight multiple cells.  Instead of dragging the 
	mouse over multiple cells to highlight the ones you want you can use the 
	<keycap>Shift</keycap> key.  Highlight the cell at the corner of the box 
	you want to highlight.  Press the <keycap>Shift</keycap> key while click on 
	the cell at the opposite corner of the box you want to highlight.  A box is 
	now highlighted.
	<tip>
	  <para>
		You can highlight a portion of one row this way too.  Just 
		highlight the starting cell in the row and press the 
		<keycap>Shift</keycap> key while you click on the ending cell.  This 
		makes a box with a row of one cell.  The same procedure applies to 
		columns.
	  </para>
	</tip>
  </para>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="enter-data">
  <title>Entering Data</title>

  <para>
	Highlight the cell you want to enter data in.  When the desired cell 
	is highlighted type your data.  You will notice that the data is being 
	displayed in the entry area.  When you are done click the 
	<inlinemediaobject>
	  <imagedata fileref="images/worksheet-data-3.png"/>
		<textobject>
		  <phrase>enter button</phrase>
		</textobject>
	</inlinemediaobject>
	or press the Enter key.  The data is then stored into the highlighted 
	cell.
  </para>
  
  <para>
	If you made a mistake in the data you entered in one cell you can 
	change it.  Highlight the desired cell.  Click on the entry area 
	and modify the data you wanted to change.  After you are done click 
	the <guibutton>enter</guibutton> button or press the Enter key.
  </para>
  
  <para>
	If you accidentally entered data into the wrong cell you can revert 
	the cell to its previous data.  Click on the 
	<inlinemediaobject>
	  <imagedata fileref="images/worksheet-data-4.png"/>
		<textobject>
		  <phrase>cancel button</phrase>
		</textobject>
	</inlinemediaobject>
	in the entry area.  The data you entered into the cell is erased 
	and the cell goes back to its previous state.
	<note>
	  <title>Note:</title>
	  <para>
		If you have already clicked on the <guibutton>enter</guibutton> 
		button or pressed the Enter key you cannot use the 
		<guibutton>cancel</guibutton> button to undo the mistake.  Instead 
		use the <link linkend="undo"><guibutton>undo</guibutton></link> 
		button.
	  </para>
	</note>
  </para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="sheets">
  <title>Sheets</title>

  <para>
	