<!-- ******************THE MENU SECTION ********************************** -->
<sect1 id="menus-start">
	<title>Introduction to Menus</title>

	<para> This section of the manual describes the use of the
	menubar and the menus themselves. The rest of <xref
	linkend="menus" /> then explains each entry in every
	<application>Gnumeric</application> menu, submenu or context
	menu.</para>

	<para>A menu is a graphical element within a program which appears
	with a list of options. For instance, almost all applications have a
	<guimenu>File</guimenu> menu through which the user can access the
	computer's filesystem to open or save their work. The main menus are 
	on the menubar. The use of these menus is discussed in <xref 
	linkend="menu-bars" />.</para>

	<para><application>Gnumeric</application>
	also uses context menus to give users a quick way to access certain
	commands. The context menu will open up right under the mouse
	pointer when one of the mouse buttons, usually the rightmost, is
	clicked. This menu is called a context menu because the entries in
	the menu are different depending on the location of the mouse
	pointer. The <guilabel>context</guilabel> menus are discussed in <xref
	linkend="context-menu" />.</para>

	<para>Both the main menus, on the menubar, and context menus may have
	sub-menus. Sub-menus are indicated by a small right pointing arrow. To
	access the sub-menus, the user must move the pointer down to the sub-menu
	entry and carefully across to the position of the little arrow. After an
	instant the sub-menu will open up and the user must carefully move the
	pointer directly across into the sub-menu. Occasionally, when there is not
	enough room to the right of the currently open menu, sub-menus may open to
	the left. Navigating sub-menus can be difficult since the menu will close
	if the mouse pointer moves into any other menu entry.</para>

	<para>
	Menu entries which are followed by an ellipsis (three dots) indicate that
	this entry will open a dialog window which will ask the user for more choices.
	</para>
	
<sect2 id="menu-bars">
    <title>The Menubar</title>    

    <para>The default location of the menubar is at the top of the
    application window.  The menus provide quick and organized access to all
    major commands such as opening files, saving files, printing and quitting
    the application. </para>
  <figure id="menubar.png">
    <title>The Gnumeric menubar.</title>
    <screenshot>
      <graphic fileref="figures/menubar.png"></graphic>
    </screenshot>
  </figure>
	<para>The leftmost portion of the menubar is a little
	tab. This tab can be used to grab the menu bar and remove it
	from the rest of the application. This is done by clicking and
	holding on the tab and dragging it away from the
	<application>Gnumeric</application> window. The menu can also
	be placed in different parts of the
	<application>Gnumeric</application> window, so that it could
	appear at the very bottom of
	<application>Gnumeric</application> as is shown in <xref
	linkend="gnumeric-rearranged.png" />.</para>

  <figure id="gnumeric-rearranged.png">
    <title>A re-arranged Gnumeric.</title>
    <screenshot>
      <graphic fileref="figures/gnumeric-rearranged.png"></graphic>
    </screenshot>
  </figure>
	<para>The menubars and the toolbars share this ability to be
	re-arranged. The menubar is at the
	bottom of the <application>Gnumeric</application> window, the
	standard toolbar has been detached and the object toolbar has
	been moved the the right side. The user can choose what
	configuration works best. The toolbars can be dragged back
	into place in the same manner by which they were moved
	originally.</para>
</sect2>


<sect2 id="Menus-General">
	<title>General Menu Behavior</title>

	<para><application>Gnumeric</application> menus are opened
	with a simple click on the name of the menu in the menu
	bar. Once clicked, the menu will stay open. If the mouse
	pointer is dragged over the name of another menu on the
	menubar, the first menu will close and the new menu open
	up. This is a useful way to look in each menu to hunt for a
	commands. Menus can also be opened through the keyboard. One
	of the letters in each menu is underlined. Typing the
	<keycap>Alt</keycap> key at the same time as the underlined
	letter key will open the menu. This is also true of
	sub-menus. Once the menus are open, the arrow keys can be used
	to move between menus or select an entry in a particular
	menu. An open menu can be closed with a click over any other
	area of the application or of the desktop. The menus can also
	be closed by typing the escape key,
	<keysym>Esc</keysym>.</para>

  <sect3>
		<title>Menus can be "torn-off".</title>
                <para><application>Gnumeric</application> menus, like
                most menus in GNOME project software, are "tear-off"
                menus. This means that the menu can be opened up into
                its own window and kept open in a differnt part of the
                screen. This is useful if there is a menu that you
                keep using for a particular task. Just beneath the top
                of each menu is a dashed line. Clicking on that line
                tears off the menu.</para>
 		 <figure id="tear-off-menu.png">
 		   <title>Gnumeric menus can be torn off.</title>
 		   <screenshot>
 	 	    <graphic fileref="figures/tear-off-menu.png"></graphic>
 		   </screenshot>
 		 </figure>

	<para>To get rid of a dettached menu, the dotted line can be clicked
	once more or the window containing the menu can simply be
	closed. The window can usually be closed by clicking in the top
	right corner of the window. Like the window containing <application>Gnumeric</application>, this outer
	window is not actually made by <application>Gnumeric</application>. Therefore the manner in which a
	user closes this window will depend on the configuration of the desktop the
	user has chosen.</para>
  </sect3>

	<sect3>
		<title>Keyboard Shortcuts</title>
		<para> Many menu entries are followed by a series of keynames. These keys
		can be used to perform the menu action without having to open the menu.
		These are often combinations of keys involving the control key which is
		labeled as <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>, the shift key which is labeled <keycap>Shift</keycap> and the function
		keys which are labeled with an <keycap>F</keycap> and then a number. For example, to
		quickly cut a selection (accessible through the <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
		menu), the user can make a selection and then type the
		control key and the "x" key at the same time. 
		</para>
	</sect3>
	
</sect2>

</sect1>


<!-- ************************  FILE MENU   *************************** -->
<sect1 id="File-Menu">
	<title>The File Menu</title>

	<para>The <guimenu>File</guimenu> menu is the most important
	menu in <application>Gnumeric</application> because it gives
	the user the ability to interact with the computer operating
	system. This menu allows the user to create files containing
	all the work they have done. It also enables users to print
	the results of their work. Finally, the
	<guimenu>File</guimenu> menu is the best way to close
	<application>Gnumeric</application>.</para>
		<figure id="menu-file-labelled.png">
		    <title>The <guimenu>File</guimenu> menu.</title>
		    <screenshot>
		      <graphic fileref="figures/menu-file-labelled.png"></graphic>
		    </screenshot>
	    </figure>
	<para>The menu choices are grouped into the following groups:</para>


	<para>
 <variablelist>

      <varlistentry>
	<term>
	  <guiicon><inlinegraphic fileref="figures/label-one.png"></inlinegraphic>
	    File operations.
	  </guiicon>
	</term>

	<listitem>
<!--
	  <para>These menu items perform operations on files. Each item is
	  presented below. File operations are critical and are therefore
	  discussed in their own section latter in this manual in <xef
	  linkend="saving" />. </para>
-->
	 <itemizedlist>

      	    <listitem>
     	      <para>
     	       <guimenuitem>New</guimenuitem> --- Create a new workbook. This 
				opens a new workbook in a new window. By default the workbook
				will be named "Book1" or another number if there is already a
				worksheet with that name open. Note that the opened file has
				not yet been saved.
     	      </para>
     	   </listitem>
     	   <listitem>
     	    <para>
     	     <guimenuitem>Open...</guimenuitem> --- The 
				<guimenuitem>Open</guimenuitem> menu item opens the file chooser
				dialog to allow the user to pick an existing workbook for 
				Gnumeric to open. Only two file types can be opened with this 
				option. The <guimenuitem>Open</guimenuitem> menu item can open 
				Gnumeric's default XML 
			based file format which uses the extension ".gnumeric" and can 
			open Microsoft Excel's file format which uses the ".xls" extension. 
			The <guimenuitem>Open</guimenuitem> menu item creates a new window 
			containing the selected file.  A more extensive dicsussion is
			presented in <xref linkend="opening" />.
      	   </para>
     	   </listitem>
     	   <listitem>
     		    <para>
      		    <guimenuitem>Import...</guimenuitem> --- The 
					<guimenuitem>Import...</guimenuitem> menu item opens a file
					chooser dialog similar to the one opened by the 
					<guimenuitem>Open</guimenuitem> menu item. The
					<guilabel>Import...</guilabel> dialog has a file type
					selector in which the user can pick supported file
					formats. For more information on file import, including the
					extensive druid to assist users importing text files, such 
					as tab delimited files or comma separated value files, 
					see <xref linkend="importing" />.
     		    </para>
    	    </listitem>
      		 <listitem>
   		      <para>
          <guimenuitem>Save</guimenuitem> --- The
		     <guimenuitem>Save</guimenuitem> menu item saves the current
         	 worksheet. If the file has been named and saved before, this will
         	 silently save the file to the current filename. If it has not been
          	saved before, this will act as if the 
		  	<guimenuitem>Save As...</guimenuitem> menu item had been called and
		 	 prompt the user for a filename.
         </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          <guimenuitem>Save As...</guimenuitem> --- The
		    <guimenuitem>Save As...</guimenuitem> menu item allows users to save 
			a file which has not yet been named to a named file. This is always 
			used when a user saves a file which Gnumeric has named by default. 
			This menu item can also be used to save a newly created file or to 
			save an existing file to a new and different name. For an
			explanation of the file formats which gnumeric supports see 
			<xref linkend="saving" />.
         </para>
        </listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
      </listitem>

	</varlistentry>


	<!--printing -->
      <varlistentry>
	<term>
	  <guiicon><inlinegraphic fileref="figures/label-two.png"></inlinegraphic>
	    Printing operations.
	  </guiicon>
	</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>These menu items enable <application>Gnumeric</application> to print. Each item is
	  presented below and printing issues are discussed fully in <xref
	  linkend="printing" />. </para>
	  
	 	<itemizedlist>
 	       <listitem>
	         <para>
 	         <guimenuitem>Print Setup...</guimenuitem> --- The
			 	<guimenuitem>Print Setup...</guimenuitem> menu item call the 
				<guilabel>Print Setup</guilabel> dialog. This dialog allows the
				user to set various printing options such as paper type, margin
				sizes and running header and footer formats. This dialog is 
				explained in detail in <xref
			 	linkend="print-setup" />.
  	       </para>
  	      </listitem>
  	      <listitem>
   	      <para>
   	       <guimenuitem>Print...</guimenuitem> --- The
		   	<guimenuitem>Print...</guimenuitem> menu item allows a user to print
			one or all of the worksheets in a workbook. Gnumeric can send files
			directly to a printer or can print to postscript or portable
			document format files. The
		   	<guilabel>Print</guilabel> dialog is
			explained further in <xref linkend="print" />.
         </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          <guimenuitem>Print Preview...</guimenuitem> --- The
		  	<guimenuitem>Print Preview...</guimenuitem> menu item calls a dialog
			which presents the current workbook as it would be printed with the
			current <guilabel>Print Setup</guilabel> settings. The dialog also
			permits the user to print. This dialog is explained in 
          	<xref linkend="print-preview" />.
         </para>
        </listitem>

		   
		</itemizedlist>
		
      </listitem>


	
      </varlistentry>



	<!-- summary -->
      <varlistentry>
		<term>
	  <inlinemediaobject>
	    <imageobject>
	      <imagedata fileref="figures/label-three.png" />
	    </imageobject>
	  </inlinemediaobject>
	  The document summary.
	</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    This menu item opens a dialog with fields to edit the 
	    document summary information of
	    the file currently open in that window. Summary information
	    describes the sheet, for instance, with the author name and
	    a comment.
	  </para>
	  
	  <!--TODO-->
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>

	<!-- recent files -->
      <varlistentry>
	<term>
	  <inlinemediaobject>
	    <imageobject>
	      <imagedata fileref="figures/label-four.png" />
	    </imageobject>
	  </inlinemediaobject>
	  Recently used files.
	</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    These menu entries are shortcuts to re-open recently used
	    files.  The list will change dynamically as new workbooks are
	    opened and created.  Clicking on a file name listed here is the
	    same as using the <guimenuitem>Open</guimenuitem> menu entry and
	    finding the file in the <guilabel>Find File</guilabel>
	    dialog. Note that if the file has been moved since 
	    <application>Gnumeric</application> last saved it, 
	    <application>Gnumeric</application> will not find the
	    file. 
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      
      
      <varlistentry>
	<term>
	  <inlinemediaobject>
	    <imageobject>
	      <imagedata fileref="figures/label-five.png" />
	    </imageobject>
	  </inlinemediaobject>
		    The Close and Quit operations.
	</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    These menu items either close the current
	    worksheet, <guimenuitem>Close</guimenuitem>, or close all open
	    worksheets, <guimenuitem>Quit</guimenuitem>. Gnumeric will prompt
	    the user with a <guilabel>Save Workbook..</guilabel> dialog for
	    any workbooks that have been changed since the last time they were
	    opened or saved.
	  </para>
	  
	  <itemizedlist>
      	    <listitem>
     	      <para>
     	       <guimenuitem>Close</guimenuitem> --- The
			       <guimenuitem>Close</guimenuitem> menu item allows the user to
				   close the current workbook. If this is the only workbook
				   which this instance of <application>Gnumeric</application> has open, the close
				   operation will also quit <application>Gnumeric</application>. If other workbooks are
				   open, this workbook will close without affecting the others.
				   If the workbook has unsaved changes, <application>Gnumeric</application> will ask
				   the user if he wants to save the file.
     	      </para>
     	   </listitem>

      	    <listitem>
     	      <para>
     	       <guimenuitem>Exit</guimenuitem> --- The
			       <guimenuitem>Exit</guimenuitem> menu item will close all the
				   workbooks currently being used by <application>Gnumeric</application> and quit the
				   program. <application>Gnumeric</application> will prompt the user asking if he wants to
				   save any workbooks which has changes which have not been
				   saved.
     	      </para>
     	   </listitem>

		   
		</itemizedlist>

		  
		</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
	  
	</variablelist>
	</para>

		

</sect1>


<!--  ******************************** EDIT MENU    ******************** -->
<sect1 id="Edit-Menu">
	<title>The Edit Menu</title>


	<para>The <guimenu>Edit</guimenu> menu is mostly used for
	operations on a worksheet or between worksheets. This menu
	gives users powerful editing operations such as the ability to
	undo recent changes, the ability to cut and paste selections
	of cells and the ability to search for specific cell contents.
	</para>
		<figure id="menu-edit-labelled.png">
		    <title>The <guimenu>Edit</guimenu> menu.</title>
		    <screenshot>
		      <graphic fileref="figures/menu-edit-labelled.png"></graphic>
		    </screenshot>
	    </figure>
	<para>The menu choices are grouped into the following groups:</para>



  <variablelist>
    
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
	<guiicon><inlinegraphic fileref="figures/label-one.png"></inlinegraphic>
	  Change History.
	</guiicon>
      </term>
      <listitem>
	<para>These menu items allow the user to remove recent changes to a
	  worksheet or re-introduce changes which have been undone. These options give
	  the user control over recent edits. This functionality is often
	  called the "change history" of an application. </para>
	
	<para>The type of edit has no importance. An edit which deletes the 
	  contents 
	  of a cell is treated in the same way as an edit which adds contents to 
	  a cell. The change history is session
	  specific. The user will not be able to undo changes through the
	  change history if the
	  file is saved and then re-opened. Note also that the list only covers
	  the last few dozen operations. The number of operations which
	  Gnumeric tracks in its history depends on the size and
	  complexity of those operations. Finally, there are some operations
	  which cannot yet be modified in this way in <application>Gnumeric 1.0</application>. Sheet
	  operations (adding or removal) cannot be undone, nor can deleted
	  comments be restored, nor can altered summary information, nor can
	  operations on embedded objects be undone.
	</para>
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <guimenuitem>Undo</guimenuitem> --- The
	      <guimenuitem>Undo</guimenuitem> menu item is used to
	      remove
	      the last few edits from a workbook. The edits must be
	      undone in order. This menu item removes only the last edit
	      from the workbook. The user can also access the undo
	      list through one of the toolbar buttons and its
	      associated menu. 
	      With this menu, the user can undo several
	      operations at once. This is explained in section <xref
								     linkend="std-toolbar" />.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <guimenuitem>Redo</guimenuitem> --- The
	      <guimenuitem>Redo</guimenuitem> menu item is used after
	      an undo operation to restore the change that was undone.
	      The menu item only restores the last undone operation. Users
	      can also resotre edit using a button on the standard toolbar
	      and through the associated menu. The menu allows several 
	      operations to be redone at once. It is explained in <xref
									linkend="std-toolbar" />.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    
    
    
    
    <!-- Cut, Copy, Paste, Paste Special... -->
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
	<guiicon><inlinegraphic fileref="figures/label-two.png"></inlinegraphic>
	  Operations on selected areas.
	</guiicon>
      </term>
      <listitem>
	<para>These menu items enable selected cell contents to be moved
	  around a spreadsheet, moved between worksheets or between
	  workbooks. Selections are areas of the spreadsheet that have been chosen,
	  usually with the mouse, and are usually colored pale blue. Selections
	  are explained in greater detail in <xref
						   linkend="selections-edit" />.
	    <application>Gnumeric</application> currently only allows single range selections for these
	    operations.
	</para>
	<para> To use these menuitems, the user must first select the range of
	  the cut or copy area. When the user then picks these menuitems, the contents
	  of the selected areas will be entered into the <application>Gnumeric clipboard</application> and
	  into the X clipboard. The contents of the <application>Gnumeric</application> clipboard can then be
	  inserted into a new region of the spreadsheet, into another worksheet or
	  into a new workbook. The X clipboard holds the
	  space delimited results of each cell: either the text or the result of
	  any calculation. The X clipboard can be pasted into any text area.
	  </para>

	  	<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>
				<guimenuitem>Cut</guimenuitem> --- The <guimenuitem>Cut</guimenuitem>
				menu item is used to remove a selection from the selected area
				of a currently open workbook. When the menu item is chosen, the
				selected area will be outlined with a moving dotted line. This
				is the area which will be moved. The selection will only be
				removed after it is moved to the new location. Until then cut
				has not had an effect on the worksheet.
				</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>
				<guimenuitem>Copy</guimenuitem> --- The 
				  <guimenuitem>Copy</guimenuitem> menu item allows a user to
				duplicate a selection. The original data remains where it was
				and the <application>Gnumeric</application> clipboard (and the X clipboard) has a copy 
				which can be inserted elsewhere.
				</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>
				<guimenuitem>Paste</guimenuitem> --- The 
				  <guimenuitem>Paste</guimenuitem> menu item is used to paste
				the contents of a selection which has been cut or copied. If
				the selection was cut, it is pasted into the new location
				unchanged. Cell references will not change in that they will
				still point to the same cells.
				</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>
				<guimenuitem>Paste Special...</guimenuitem> --- The 
				  <guimenuitem>Paste Special...</guimenuitem> is used to paste
				a selection while altering certain characteristics. The 
				<guimenuitem>Paste Special...</guimenuitem> menu item opens a
				dialog with three categories. The defaults make 
				<guimenuitem>Paste Special...</guimenuitem> act as if it were the 
				<guimenuitem>Paste</guimenuitem> menu item. 
				</para>
				<para>The first set of
				choices allow the user to control the data pasted.The user can chose
				to limit the pasting to only the cell contents (no cell
				formatting is copied) or the opposite only cell formats copied
				(no contents). Furthermore, the user can insert the selection
				while transforming all the contents into values only. Formulas
				will not be copied, only the results will be. 
				</para>
				<para>A second set of choices allows the user to perform simple
				mathematical transformations during the paste. The data in the
				cells being pasted into are modified by the cell contents. For
				instance, using the divide operation will result in each cell
				in the zone pasted into being divided by the equivalent cell
				which was cut or copied originally.
				</para>
				<para>The final choices allow the transposition of the original
				selection or to not paste empty cells. The 
				<guilabel>transpose</guilabel> check box
				will change the selection so that the cells that are down n
				rows from the selection's origin are pasted as being over n
				columns (and vice-versa). The <guilabel>skip blanks</guilabel>
				prevents <application>Gnumeric</application> from taking any action for the cells in the
				selection that are blank. Note that the selection will be
				transformed if that option is selected but then that the 
				paste will not change the cells in the transformed location if
				this <guilabel>skip blanks</guilabel> option is selected.
				</para>
			</listitem>

		</itemizedlist>
	  
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>


	<varlistentry>
		<term>
			<guiicon>
			<inlinegraphic fileref="figures/label-three.png"></inlinegraphic>
			Data removal operations.
			</guiicon>
		</term>
		<listitem>
			<para>All of these operations remove data from the worksheet. They
			differ in the type of data removed and the re-arangement of
			remaining data. The differences are explained below.
			</para>


			<itemizedlist>
      	    	<listitem>
     	      	<para>
     	       	<guimenuitem>Clear</guimenuitem> --- The
			       <guimenuitem>clear</guimenuitem> menu item merely opens a
				   sub-menu with four choices. The user can choose to clear all
				   the elements of the cells in a selection: the formats, the
				   comments, the contents. Alternatively, the user can choose
				   to clear a single one of those elemets. Clearing the formats
				   will leave the data or formula in the cell intact. It will
				   remove any borders, re-set the cell alignments, change the
				   background colour to white and the text colour to black and
				   reset the number format to <guilabel>General</guilabel>. Clearing the comments
				   will simply delete the comments for the cells in that
				   location. Finally clearing the contents will leave the
				   cell's formatting in place but remove the formula or data
				   contents of the cell.
				   </para>
     	   		</listitem>

      	    	<listitem>
     	      	<para>
     	       	<guimenuitem>Delete</guimenuitem> --- The
			       <guimenuitem>delete</guimenuitem> menu item may open a dialog
				 giving the user a choice of options. Any of the options
				 will completely delete the selected cells. Depending on the
				 selection, <application>Gnumeric</application> will fill in the space the cells
				 were occupying differently. With column or row selections,
				 the effect is easy to understand and no choice is possible
				 so <application>Gnumeric</application> does not open the dialog. The space left by
				 selected rows, is filled by moving lower rows up
				 whereas the space filled by deleting columns is filled by
				 moving to the left columns which were right of the selection. 
				 For example, if columns D and E are selected for deletion,
				 <application>Gnumeric</application> will move the contents of all columns from F
				 onwards two columns to the left.
				 </para>
				 <para>
				 With blocks of cells, the <guimenuitem>delete</guimenuitem> 
				 menu item will open a dialog asking the user how to fill in the
				 deleted cells. Blocks of cells will either be filled in by the
				 columns of cells below the block selection or by the rows on 
				 the right of the block. For example, if the user chose the
				 block of cells from E6:G8 for deletion, those cells could be
				 filled in by the cells below E8, F8 and G8 if the <guilabel>Shift cells
				 up</guilabel> option were chosen. Alternatively, the cells to the right
				 of G6, G7 and G8 could fill in the space from the right if the
				 <guilabel>Shift cells left</guilabel> option were chosen.
				 </para>
     	   		</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</listitem>
	</varlistentry>


	<varlistentry>
		<term>
			<guiicon><inlinegraphic fileref="figures/label-four.png"></inlinegraphic>
			Other operations on worksheets.
			</guiicon>
		</term>
		<listitem>
			<para>These menu entries do not group together logically. Each
			  entry is explained in detail below. </para>

	 		<itemizedlist>
      	    	<listitem>
     	      	<para>
     	       	<guimenuitem>Sheet</guimenuitem> --- The
			       <guimenuitem>Sheet</guimenuitem> menu item opens up a
				   submenu which allows users to perform operations on the
				   worksheet. Note that this is the same set of choices as are
				   available from the context menu which appears by clicking
				   (usually with the right mouse button) on one of the
				   worksheet tabs. The worksheet can be duplicated to create a
				   second sheet with the same contents. A new worksheet can be
				   inserted immediately following the current sheet. The
				   current sheet can be renamed in a the little pop-up window. The
				   sheets can be re-ordered or the current sheet can be
				   deleted. For this last option <application>Gnumeric</application> asks for confirmation
				   since this choice cannot be undone.
				 </para>
     	   		</listitem>

      	    	<listitem>
     	      	<para>
     	       	<guimenuitem>Select</guimenuitem> --- The
			       <guimenuitem>Select</guimenuitem> menu item allows the user
				 to select various portions of the worksheet. The
				 <guimenuitem>Select All</guimenuitem> provides a quick way to
				 select the entire worksheet. The <guimenuitem>Select
				 Row</guimenuitem> and <guimenuitem>Select Column</guimenuitem>
				 menuitems allow the user to select all the rows or columns 
				 spanned by the current selection.
				 </para>
				 <para>
				 The <guimenuitem>Select Array</guimenuitem> menu item allows a
				 user to select all the cells which are part of the same array
				 as the current cell. The <guimenuitem>Select Depends</guimenuitem> 
				 menu item selects all the cells which are formulas which at
				 least partially need the data in the current cell. 
				 </para>
     	   		</listitem>

      	    	<listitem>
     	      	<para>
     	       	<guimenuitem>Fill</guimenuitem> --- The
			       <guimenuitem>Fill</guimenuitem> menu item opens a submenu
				 with only one choice currently. The 
				 <guimenuitem>Autoill</guimenuitem> menu item will fill an
				 entire selection with any formula which is in the top left
				 cell of the selection. 
				 </para>
     	   		</listitem>

      	    	<listitem>
     	      	<para>
     	       	<guimenuitem>Search...</guimenuitem> --- The
			       <guimenuitem>Search...</guimenuitem> menu item opens a dialog
				 to search for cells with particular content. The dialog has
				 three tabs. In the first the user can enter the information
				 the user wants to find and some constraints on the search. The
				 second tab gives some extra choices for the search. When the
				 user has picked the options they perfer, pushing the search
				 button on the first tab will run the search. The third tab
				 will show which cells match the search.
				 </para>
     	   		</listitem>

      	    	<listitem>
     	      	<para>
     	       	<guimenuitem>Search and Replace...</guimenuitem> --- The
			       <guimenuitem>Search and Replace...</guimenuitem> menu item
				 will launch a dialog to find cells with particular
				 characteristics and replace them all with a common content.
				 This dialog is similar to the <guilabel>Search</guilabel>
				 dialog.
				 </para>
     	   		</listitem>

      	    	<listitem>
     	      	<para>
     	       	<guimenuitem>Goto cell...</guimenuitem> --- The
			       <guimenuitem>Goto cell...</guimenuitem> menuitemn opens up a
				   dialog which allows the user to type the name of a cell in
				   the worksheet. The current view will then change to be sure
				   that the selected cell is in the current view and the
				   selection will cover that cell.
				 </para>
     	   		</listitem>

      	    	<listitem>
     	      		<para>
     	       		<guimenuitem>Recalculate</guimenuitem> --- The
			       	  <guimenuitem>Recalculate</guimenuitem> menu item forces
					the workbook to recalculate its results. This is useful
					if a formula in the current worksheet depends on a cell in
					a different workbook. <application>Gnumeric</application> will not necessarily know
					when that data has been updated so a user can force
					<application>Gnumeric</application> to recalculate all the cells in the current
					workbook.
     	      		</para>
     	   		</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>  
		</listitem>
	</varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
</sect1>


<!-- *************************** View Menu *********** -->
<sect1 id="View-Menu">
	<title>The View Menu</title>

 


	<para>The <guimenu>View</guimenu> menu is </para>
		<figure id="menu-view-labelled.png">
		    <title>The <guimenu>View</guimenu> menu.</title>
		    <screenshot>
		      <graphic fileref="figures/menu-view-labelled.png"></graphic>
		    </screenshot>
	    </figure>
	<para>The menu choices are grouped into the following groups:</para>



 <variablelist>

		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<guiicon><inlinegraphic fileref="figures/label-one.png"></inlinegraphic>
				Alternative views of the current document.
				</guiicon>
			</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>These menu items allow the user to open multiple views of
				the same document.</para>

				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para><guimenuitem>New Shared</guimenuitem> --- The
							<guimenuitem>New Shared</guimenuitem> menu item opens up a new
						window with the current workbook visible and where both windows 
						are open to the same
						section of the workbook. If the user starts editing a different
						part of the sheet in one view, the other view moves automatically to that
						portion of the worksheet. Similarly, if the user changes to a
						different worksheet in one view, the other view changes also.
						</para>
					</listitem>

					<listitem>
						<para>
						<guimenuitem>New Unshared</guimenuitem> --- The
							<guimenuitem>New Unshared</guimenuitem> menu item opens up a new
							window with the current workbook visible. Both view are then
							independent. When a change is made in either view, the other will
							move to show the area of the edit. 
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>



		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<guiicon><inlinegraphic fileref="figures/label-two.png"></inlinegraphic>
				Global changes to the current view.
				</guiicon>
			</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>The<guimenuitem>Zoom</guimenuitem> menu item allows a user
				to change the amount of the sheet visible in a window of a given
				size. The <guimenuitem>Freeze Panes</guimenuitem> menu item allows
				part of the worksheet to be frozen in place while the rest of the
				sheet scrolls next to it.</para>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para><guimenuitem>Zoom...</guimenuitem> --- The
							<guimenuitem>Zoom</guimenuitem> menu item opens a dialog which
						allows the user to set the magnification of any of the worksheets
						in the current workbook. 
						</para>
					</listitem>

					<listitem>
						<para>
						<guimenuitem>Freeze Panes</guimenuitem> --- The
						<guimenuitem>Freeze Panes</guimenuitem> menu item is used to freeze
						the top-most and leftmost visible portion of the worksheet. This is
						useful to be able to line up portions of the worksheet which are
						not usually together. For instance, if a user had a very large table
						with the titles of each oolumn of data on row 12, the user could
						select row 13 and select this menu item.  If the user scrolled 
						through each data row, the data would line up underneath each header.
						</para>
						<para><application>Gnumeric</application> freezes the portion of the worksheet which is currently
						visible and is above and left of the current selection. If the
						selection is not visible, then the frozen section will be nine rows
						tall and five columns wide unless the selection is in a currently
						visible column or row in which case that postion is used.
						</para>
						<para><application>Gnumeric</application> currently does not support freezing only columns or 
						only rows. The user can simply move the selection far to the 
						right or far below of the area they want to freeze. This will
						achieve the same effect. Currently, inserted objects are not
						tracked with frozen panes. Objects which are not in the lower right
						hand pane are lost from view while the panes are frozen. These
						objects reappear when the view is unfrozen.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>



		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<guiicon><inlinegraphic fileref="figures/label-three.png"></inlinegraphic>
				Toolbar configuration.
				</guiicon>
			</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
				The <guimenuitem>Toolbars</guimenuitem> menu option launches
				a dialog to configure the presence and look of the three
				toolbars. This dialog allows the user either to show or completely hide
				each toolbar. The user can also set the toolbars to display as icons or
				as icons and text. The third selection <guilabel>Priority text
				only</guilabel> currently has no effect. This dialog allows 
				users to view tooltips as
				the mouse scrolls over the toolbars. Tooltips are small windows which
				open up automatically when the mouse pointer is over a button. These
				windows contain a text explanation of the button under the mouse
				pointer.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
	</variablelist>

</sect1>


<!--  *********************************** INSERT MENU ********************* -->
<sect1 id="Insert-Menu">
	<title>The Insert Menu</title>



	<para>The <guimenu>Insert</guimenu> menu is </para>
		<figure id="menu-insert-labelled.png">
		    <title>The <guimenu>Insert</guimenu> menu.</title>
		    <screenshot>
		      <graphic fileref="figures/menu-insert-labelled.png"></graphic>
		    </screenshot>
	    </figure>
	<para>The menu choices are grouped into the following groups:</para>



	<variablelist>

		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<guiicon><inlinegraphic fileref="figures/label-one.png"></inlinegraphic>
				Insert into workbook.
				</guiicon>
			</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>These menu items allow the user to insert objects to the
				workbook.
				</para>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para><guimenuitem>Sheet</guimenuitem> --- The
							<guimenuitem>Sheet</guimenuitem> menu item allows the user to
							inset a worksheet immediately following the current sheet.
						</para>
					</listitem>

					<listitem>
						<para>
						<guimenuitem>Rows</guimenuitem> --- The
							<guimenuitem>Rows</guimenuitem> menu item will insert rows 
							above the current selection. The number of rows inserted will
							be equal to the number of rows spanned by the current selection.
						</para>
					</listitem>

					<listitem>
						<para>
						<guimenuitem>Columns</guimenuitem> --- The
							<guimenuitem>Columns</guimenuitem> menu item will insert columns
							to the left of the current selection. The number of columns
							inserted will equal the number of columns spanned by the current
							selection.
						</para>
					</listitem>

					<listitem>
						<para>
						<guimenuitem>Cells...</guimenuitem> --- The
							<guimenuitem>Cells...</guimenuitem> menu item opens a dialog
							asking the user how the sheet should be altered when new cells are
							inserted. The dialog lists four choices. The user can choose one
							of these by clicking the mouse pointer on one of the four dots.
							Only one choice is possible and the currently selected choice has 
							a black dot in front.
							</para>
							<para>The <guilabel>Shift cells right</guilabel> will insert a region of new
							cells of the size of the current selection. Cells which are on the same row as 
							the selection and within or to the right of the selection will
							shift over to the right to accomodate the new cells. The 
							<guilabel>Shift cells down</guilabel> choice will also insert a
							region of new cells the same size as the current selection. With
							this choice, cells which are in the selection or below the
							selection will move down to accomodate the new cells. The two
							other choices will act as if the user had chosen to insert rows
							or columns. These actions are explained above.
						</para>
					</listitem>

					<listitem>
						<para>
						<guimenuitem>Graph...</guimenuitem> --- The
							<guimenuitem>Graph...</guimenuitem> menu item will allow a user to
							insert a graphic plot of data. This menu item will launch the
							graph druid. Graphing in <application>Gnumeric</application> is explained in 
							<xref
							linkend="graphs"
							/>.
						</para>
					</listitem>

					<listitem>
						<para>
						<guimenuitem>Object...</guimenuitem> --- The
							<guimenuitem>Object...</guimenuitem> menu item launches a dialog
							with the objects which <application>Gnumeric</application> is currently able to embed in a
							worksheet. The user simply picks one of the objects in the list,
							and then inserts the object into the worksheet. These objects are
							not part of <application>Gnumeric</application> but are provided by other programs in the
							GNOME project.
						</para>
					</listitem>

					<listitem>
						<para>
						<guimenuitem>Shaped Object...</guimenuitem> --- The
							<guimenuitem>Shaped Object...</guimenuitem> menu item allows user
							to insert more complicated objects into a worksheet. This is
							currently not used but will provide more extended functionality
							for the future.
						</para>
					</listitem>

				</itemizedlist>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<guiicon><inlinegraphic fileref="figures/label-two.png"></inlinegraphic>
				Insert to current cell.
				</guiicon>
			</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>The menu items insert objects into the current cell.</para>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para><guimenuitem>Name</guimenuitem> --- The
							<guimenuitem>Name</guimenuitem> menu item opens a sub-menu with
							the single entry <guilabel>Define</guilabel>. This will open a 
							dialog to allow the user
							to define a named expression. The expression can be as simple as
							defining an expression called "Total" which refers to a particular
							cell. However, the user can also build up a whole sheet with
							named
							experssions.
							<xref
							linkend="formulas-names"
							/> explains names
							in greater detail.
						</para>
					</listitem>

					<listitem>
						<para><guimenuitem>Add/Modify comment...</guimenuitem> --- This
						menu item opens a dialog to allow the user to enter a comment to the
						currently selected cell. A red triangle will appear in the top
						right corner of the cell to show that the cell has a comment.
						</para>
					</listitem>

					<listitem>
						<para>
						<guimenuitem>Special</guimenuitem> --- The
							<guimenuitem>Special</guimenuitem> menu item opens a sub-menu
						which allows the user to
						insert either the current date or the current time into the
						selected cell.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
	</variablelist>


</sect1>













<!--  ************************************FORMAT MENU ********************* -->
<sect1 id="Format-Menu">
	<title>The Format Menu</title>



	<para>The <guimenu>Format</guimenu> menu allows users to control the formats
	of cells, columns, rows, worksheets and the workbook. This menu also gives users
	access to templates of standard formats.
</para>
		<figure id="menu-format-torn-off.png">
		    <title>The <guimenu>Format</guimenu> menu.</title>
		    <screenshot>
		      <graphic fileref="figures/menu-format-torn-off.png"></graphic>
		    </screenshot>
	    </figure>

	<!-- the list of format menu items -->
     <variablelist> 
      <varlistentry>
       <term><guimenu>The Format Menu</guimenu> offers these menuitems:</term>
       <listitem>
       <para>
         <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
           <para>
            <guimenuitem>Cells...</guimenuitem> --- The 
						  <guimenuitem>Cells...</guimenuitem> menu item opens the cell format
            dialog. This dialog is used to set cell data types and formats. It
						is explained in <xref
						  linkend="cell-formatting"
						  />.
						</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
         <para>
          <guimenuitem>Column</guimenuitem> --- The 
					  <guimenuitem>Column</guimenuitem> menu item opens a sub-menu with
						choices to allows the user to modify the view of the selected
						columns.
						<itemizedlist>
 		             <listitem>
 		               <para>
 		               <guimenuitem>Width...</guimenuitem> --- The 
									   <guimenuitem>Width...</guimenuitem> menu item opens a dialog
									 to enable the user to adjust the size of the columns which 
									 hold the current selection. The
									 dialog has a single entry box in which the user can change
									 the current size of the column in points.
						</para>
				      </listitem>
 		             <listitem>
					 <para>
  		              <guimenuitem>Auto Fit Selection</guimenuitem> --- This
										menu item makes <application>Gnumeric</application> automatically choose the optimal 
										column size to display all of the text in the current
										selection.
										</para>
			      </listitem>
    	          <listitem>
                       <para>
      	          <guimenuitem>Hide</guimenuitem> --- The 
									  <guimenuitem>Hide</guimenuitem> menu item will hide the
										columns containing the current selection. <application>Gnumeric</application> still
										holds these columns in memory and will save them to a file
										but will not display those columns. The only
										indication that a user has that columns have been hidden is
										that the column header names are not sequential.
										</para>
	 		     </listitem>
    	          <listitem>
     	           <para>
     	           <guimenuitem>Unhide</guimenuitem> --- This menu item wiil
								 show columns which are hidden if the selection spans the two
								 columns on either side of the selection. If columns D, E, and
								 F have been hidden, the selection must span at least across
								 columns C and G for this menu item to unhide columns D, E, and
								 F. 
								 </para>
	  		   	 </listitem>
      	     	   <listitem>
             		  <para>
              		  <guimenuitem>Standard Width</guimenuitem> --- This menu item
										allows the user to resize the columns which hold the
										selection to the standard size. At 100 percent zoom this is
										48 points or 64 pixels.
										</para>
	   	 	     </listitem>
         	  </itemizedlist>
         </para>
        </listitem>


        <listitem>
         <para>
           <guimenuitem>Row</guimenuitem> --- The <guimenuitem>Row</guimenuitem>
					 menu item provides the same functions as the <guimenuitem>Column</guimenuitem>
					 menu item but operates on rows.
					 <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                <guimenuitem>Height...</guimenuitem> --- This menu item opens a
								dialog which allows the user to type in a row height in pixels.
								</para>
	      </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                <guimenuitem>Auto Fit Selection</guimenuitem> --- This menu item
								changes the rows which hold the selection to the optimal height
								to hold the text in the selection. 
								</para>
	      </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                <guimenuitem>Hide</guimenuitem> --- The 
								  <guimenuitem>Hide</guimenuitem> menu item will hide the rows
									in the selection. The workbook still contains the data in the
									hidden rows but those rows are not shown. 
									</para>
	      </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                <guimenuitem>Unhide</guimenuitem> --- This menu item will make
								hidden rows visible. The selection must span the rows which are
								hidden for this menu item to unhide the hidden rows.
	        </para>
	      </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                <guimenuitem>Standard Height</guimenuitem> --- This menu item 
                resizes the rows back to the default height of 12.75 points or
								17 pixels (at 100 percent zoom).
	        </para>
	      </listitem>
           </itemizedlist>
         </para>
        </listitem>


        <listitem>
         <para>
          <guimenuitem>Sheet</guimenuitem> --- The <guimenuitem>Sheet</guimenuitem>
					menu item opens a sub-menu with operations to change properties of the
					worksheet.
					<itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                <guimenuitem>Change Name...</guimenuitem> --- This opens a
								dialog with the name of the worksheet. A user can use this to
								change the name of the current sheet.
	        </para>
	      </listitem>
              <listitem>
                 <para>
                <guimenuitem>Re-Order Sheets...</guimenuitem> ---- This opens a
								dialog with the names of all the sheets. A user can click on
								one of the names in the dialog and then click on the up and
								down arrows, as appropriate, to move the selected sheet in
								front or behind others. The tabs for the sheets will move at
								the same time. This dialog also allows the user to delete
								sheets.
								</para>
	      </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                <guimenuitem>Display Formulas</guimenuitem> --- This menu item
								acts as a toogle. By default it is unset and formulas results
								are displayed. If this menu item is clicked, it will display a
								little check mark on the left. The worksheet will show the
								actual fomuals for all cells with formulas instead of showing
								the calculated result. This is useful for quickly assessing
								which cells contain formulas and which contain data.
	        			</para>
	      </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                <guimenuitem>Hide Zeros</guimenuitem> --- This menu item acts as
								a toggle. Click on this menu item will cause a check mark to
								appear on the left. The sheet will then display all the cells
								which display zeros as empty cells. This is useful in sheets
								with many zero results, to quickly find cells with data.
	        			</para>
	      </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                <guimenuitem>Hide Gridlines</guimenuitem> --- This menu item
								acts as a toggle. If this menu item is clicked, <application>Gnumeric</application> will
								display a check mark to the left of the menu item. The lines
								which separate all the cells will then be hidden and <application>Gnumeric</application>
								will appear to be a blank background. This is useful to make
								certain data look pretty on screen.
	        			</para>
	      </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                <guimenuitem>Hide Column Headers</guimenuitem> --- This
								menu item acts as a toggle. If this menu item is clicked,
								<application>Gnumeric</application> display a check mark on the left of the menu item.
								<application>Gnumeric</application> will also hide the boxes with the alphabetical names
								of the columns.
	        			</para>
	      </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                <guimenuitem>Hide Row Header</guimenuitem> --- This
								menu item acts as a toggle. If this menu item is clicked,
								<application>Gnumeric</application> display a check mark on the left of the menu item.
								<application>Gnumeric</application> will also hide the boxes with the numeric names
								of the rows.
	        			</para>
	      </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          <guimenuitem>Autoformat...</guimenuitem> This menu item opens the
					autoformat dialog to give user access to a list of format templates.
					Format templates are useful for users who are often
					filling out tables in a particular format. The user picks an area of
					the worksheet into which they want to apply the template. Most
					templates define headers and footers so the selection area must be
					big enough to fit those template elements and the user's data. The
					template will not affect data which has already been input into a
					worksheet. 
					</para>
					<para> The dialog has two tabs: <guilabel>Preview</guilabel> and <guilabel>Template Details</guilabel>. The
					details are simply information about the template. The <guilabel>Preview</guilabel> tab
					has three main options: a <guilabel>Settings</guilabel> menu, an <guilabel>Edit</guilabel> menu and a 
					category chooser. The settings menu allows a user to pick what parts
					of the template they want to copy into the worksheet. The edit menu
					will be used to create new templates. Currently templates are written
					as text into an extensible markup language (XML) format. The catory
					chooser gives the user access to different groups of templates.
					Templates in each category are displayed in the middle area of the
					dialog. Users select the template they want to use by clicking on it.
					The currently selected template is highlighted with a red boundary
					which may be hard to see.
					</para>
        </listitem>
         <listitem>
         <para>
          <guimenuitem>Workbook...</guimenuitem> This menu item opens a dialog
					which allows users to configure the current workbook. The dialog
					currently has four choices. Text autocomplete can be unset which
					means that <application>Gnumeric</application> will not compare text as it entered against text
					in above it in the column. Text autocomplete is useful to users
					entering data because if entries are repeated, <application>Gnumeric</application> can guess
					what the user intends. The user can simply type the <keycap>Tab</keycap> key and
					<application>Gnumeric</application> will enter the rest of the text.
					The use of notebook tabs can be turned off, as can the
					horizontal and vertical scrollbars. 
					</para>
        </listitem>
       </itemizedlist>
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

</sect1>



<!--   ********************* TOOLS MENU ************  -->
<sect1 id="Tools-Menu">
	<title>The Tools Menu</title>

	<para>The <guimenu>Tools</guimenu> menu is </para>
		<figure id="menu-tools-labelled.png">
		    <title>The <guimenu>Tools</guimenu> menu.</title>
		    <screenshot>
		      <graphic fileref="figures/menu-tools-labelled.png"></graphic>
		    </screenshot>
	    </figure>
	<para>The menu choices are grouped into the following groups:</para>



 <variablelist>

      <varlistentry>
	<term>
	  <guiicon><inlinegraphic fileref="figures/label-one.png"></inlinegraphic>
	    The Plug-ins dialog.
	  </guiicon>
	</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>This entry launches the plug-in manangement
	  dialog. Plug-ins are programs which are separate from
	  <application>Gnumeric</application> but provide useful
	  functionality.  Some of the core parts of gnumeric, such as
	  Excel file format support, are actually plugins. This means
	  that a user who never uses Excel files can remove this
	  module from <application>Gnumeric</application> and make
	  <application>Gnumeric</application> use less memory.<!--
	  <xref linkend="Plugins" /> explains plug-ins in greater
	  detail.--></para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
	<term>
	  <guiicon><inlinegraphic fileref="figures/label-two.png"></inlinegraphic>
	    Automatic tools
	  </guiicon>
	</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>These two tools allow the user to make
	  <application>Gnumeric</application> automatically correct
	  typing or automatically save workbooks at periodic
	  intervals.</para>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para><guimenuitem>Auto Correct...</guimenuitem> --- The
							<guimenuitem>Auto Correct...</guimenuitem> menu item opens a
							dialog which allows the user to configure the way in which
							gnumeric automatically corrects text which is being entered. The
							dialog presents the user with three tabs. Each of these tabs allows
							the user to correct one type of common spelling mistake, while
							allowing the user to add exceptions to the rules. <application>Gnumeric</application> can
							automatically caplitalize the names of week days. <application>Gnumeric</application> can
							automatically change an entry which starts with two capital
							letters to only start with one and <application>Gnumeric</application> can change a sentence
							entry to start with a capital letter.
						</para>
					</listitem>

					<listitem>
						<para>
						<guimenuitem>Auto Save</guimenuitem> --- The
							<guimenuitem>Auto Save</guimenuitem> menu item opens a dialog
						which allows the user to have <application>Gnumeric</application> automatically save the
						current workbook after a fixed interval of time. The user can also
						have <application>Gnumeric</application> ask for confirmation before saving so that the user
						always remains aware of the state the workbook was in when it was
						saved.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
				</listitem>
      </varlistentry>


      <varlistentry>
	<term>
	  <guiicon><inlinegraphic fileref="figures/label-three.png"></inlinegraphic>
	   Linear Programming tools
	  </guiicon>
	</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para><application>Gnumeric</application> can be used to
	  solve systems of linear equations and other mathematical
	  problems. These two dialogs enable access to these tools. A
	  full discussion of these tools is presented in <xref
	  linkend="solver-chapter" />. </para>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para><guimenuitem>Goal Seek</guimenuitem> --- The
							<guimenuitem>Goal Seek</guimenuitem> menu item opens a dialog
							through which the user can configure <application>Gnumeric</application> to iteratively
							search for a numeric value which solves a formula. This dialog is
							explained in
							<xref
							linkend="goal-seek"
							/>.
						</para>
					</listitem>

					<listitem>
						<para>
						<guimenuitem>Solver</guimenuitem> --- The
							<guimenuitem>Solver</guimenuitem> menu item opens a dialog through
							which the user can configure <application>Gnumeric</application> to solve linear systems of
							equations.
							This is
							explained in
							<xref
							linkend="solver-chapter"
							/>.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>


      <varlistentry>
	<term>
	  <guiicon><inlinegraphic fileref="figures/label-four.png"></inlinegraphic>
	    Statistics and other Data Analsyis tools
	  </guiicon>
	</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>Statistical analysis can easily be done with
	  <application>Gnumeric</application>. All the statistical
	  tools are explained in <xref linkend="analysis-tools" />.
		</para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>


</variablelist>

</sect1>


<!-- ******************* THE DATA MENU   ************** -->
<sect1 id="Data-Menu">
	<title>The Data Menu</title>





	<para>The <guimenu>Data</guimenu> menu is </para>
		<figure id="menu-data-labelled.png">
		    <title>The <guimenu>Data</guimenu> menu.</title>
		    <screenshot>
		      <graphic fileref="figures/menu-data-labelled.png"></graphic>
		    </screenshot>
	    </figure>
	<para>The menu choices are grouped into the following groups:</para>



 <variablelist>

      <varlistentry>
	<term>
	  <guiicon><inlinegraphic fileref="figures/label-one.png"></inlinegraphic>
	    Data Field tools.
	  </guiicon>
	</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>These menu items allow the user to re-organize data fields.</para>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para><guimenuitem>Sort...</guimenuitem> --- The
							<guimenuitem>Sort...</guimenuitem> menu item opens a dialog which
						allows users to sort a selection according to defined criteria. By
						default <application>Gnumeric</application> sorts rows depending on the contents of the cells
						in a particular column of each row. The sort criteria can be
						extended to calculate on the basis of the cells in several columns. 
						<application>Gnumeric</application> can sort a
						selection using any number of rules. Rules can be added using the 
						<guibutton>Add</guibutton> button. Rules with no column entered will
						be ignored or the user can remove these rules with the 
						<guibutton>Remove</guibutton> button. 
						</para>
						<para> For each rule, the
						dialog has an entry box in which the column to be sorted must be
						entered. The dropdown box (the little down pointing arrow) will
						show a list of appropriate columns.
						The user can determine a sort order for the selection. The
						<guibutton>Advanced</guibutton> button allows the user to further characterize the sort
						criteria.
						</para>
						<para>
						If the first row of the selection is a header, <application>Gnumeric</application> can be told
						not to shuffle this row during the sort. <application>Gnumeric</application> can also sort
						columns based on the contents of cells in specified rows, instead 
						of shuffling rows on the basis of columns, if the user toggles the 
						<guilabel>Sort</guilabel> to act right-left instead of top-down.
						</para>
					</listitem>

					<listitem>
						<para>
						<guimenuitem>Filter</guimenuitem> --- The
							<guimenuitem>Filter</guimenuitem> menu item opens a sub-menu which
							currently only has the <guimenuitem>Advanced Filter</guimenuitem> entry. Filters are
							explained in
							<xref
							linkend="filters"
							/>.
						</para>
					</listitem>

					<listitem>
						<para>
						<guimenuitem>Validate...</guimenuitem> --- The
							<guimenuitem>Validate...</guimenuitem> menu item opens the cell
							format dialog to the validation tab. Validation is a means of
							constraining the contents of a cell either to have a certain
							value or to fall within a certain range.
						</para>
					</listitem>

					<listitem>
						<para>
						<guimenuitem>Consolidate...</guimenuitem> --- The
							<guimenuitem>Consolidate...</guimenuitem> menu item opens a dialog
							box through which a user can create derived information based on
							data in other worksheets. 
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>


	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
	<term>
	  <guiicon><inlinegraphic fileref="figures/label-two.png"></inlinegraphic>
	    Group and Outline.
	  </guiicon>
	</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>The sub-menu options of the <guimenu>Group and
	  Outline</guimenu> menu are useful for creating data hiearchies
	  within a worksheet.</para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>

</variablelist>


</sect1>





<!--  *********************** HELP MENU *****************-->
<sect1 id="Help-Menu">
	<title>The Help Menu</title>


	<para>The <guimenu>Help</guimenu> menu is quite simple.</para>
		<figure id="menu-help-torn-off.png">
		    <title>The <guimenu>Help</guimenu> menu.</title>
		    <screenshot>
		      <graphic fileref="figures/menu-help-torn-off.png"></graphic>
		    </screenshot>
	    </figure>
	<para>The <guimenu>Help</guimenu> menu connects users to this
	manual, to the list of functions available for use in <application>Gnumeric</application>
	and to the list of people who created this wonderful
	application.</para>


	<!-- the help menu list -->
    <variablelist> 
      <varlistentry>
       <term><guimenu>Help</guimenu></term>
       <listitem>
       <para>
        This menu contains:
         <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
           <para>
            <guimenuitem>Gnumeric Manual</guimenuitem> &mdash;Clicking on
            this menu entry should launch the local help system and display
            this manual.            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          <guimenuitem>Gnumeric Function Reference</guimenuitem>
          &mdash;View the Gnumeric function reference, a list and description 
          of the functions available in Gnumeric. 
         </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          <guimenuitem>About</guimenuitem>
          &mdash;Shows basic information about <application>Gnumeric</application>, such as the authors' names 
          and the application version number. 
         </para>
        </listitem>
       </itemizedlist>
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

</sect1>








<!--  *********************** CONTEXT MENUS *****************-->
<sect1 id="context-menu">
	<title>Context Menus in Gnumeric</title>

	<para>Context menus are menus which open up under the mouse pointer and are
	therefore detached from the format graphical structure
	of the applicaton. These menus provide an extra and convenient way to access
	Gnumeric commands. All of the commands in context menus are available
	through the regular menu system. Context menus provide different commands
	depending on the position of the pointer.</para>

	<para>To activate a context menu, a user simply positions the pointer over
	the appropriate area and clicks one of the buttons on their mouse. Since this
	button is configurable and users have mice with different buttons, it may be a
	different button on any given machine or may even require the combination of a
	keyboard key and a mouse buttons. The user will have to find how to do this
	themselves.</para>

	<para> Currently Gnumeric provides five
	different context menus. The context menu that is called in the central
	grid area is discussed next in <xref
	linkend="menu-context-grid" />. The
	Context menu that appears when the pointer is over the row headers or
	column headers is presented in <xref
	linkend="menu-context-col-row-header" />. Another context menu relates to the
	worksheet tabs and is explained in <xref
	linkend="menu-context-tabs" />. Yet
	another context menu applies to embbeded objects or shaped components such
	as a plot. These are shown in <xref
	linkend="menu-context-object" />. The
	final context menu allows the configuration of the toolbars. This menu is
	presented in <xref linkend="menu-context-toolbars" />.</para>


<sect2 id="menu-context-grid">
	<title>The Context Menu for the Cell Grid Area</title>
	<para>The context menu in the cell grid area apprears when the pointer is over the cell
	grid area. This menu applies to the cells that have been selected, not
	necessarily the cell underneath the mouse pointer. </para>
		<figure id="menu-context-grid.png">
		    <title>The Context Menu for the Cell Grid Area.</title>
		    <screenshot>
		      <graphic fileref="figures/menu-context-grid.png"></graphic>
		    </screenshot>
	    </figure>
	<para>The grid context menu merely provides an extra way to access Gnumeric
	commands. The <guimenuitem>Cut</guimenuitem>, <guimenuitem>Copy</guimenuitem>, 
	<guimenuitem>Paste</guimenuitem>, <guimenuitem>Paste Special...</guimenuitem>,
	<guimenuitem>Delete...</guimenuitem>, and <guimenuitem>Clear Contents...</guimenuitem> 
	commands are taken from the Edit menu and are explained in
	<xref linkend="Edit-Menu" />.
	The <guimenuitem>Insert...</guimenuitem> menu item is explained in the section
	on the <guimenu>Insert</guimenu> menu in <xref
	linkend="Insert-Menu" />. The 
	<guimenuitem>Format Cells...</guimenuitem> is explained in the manual section
	on the <guimenu>Format</guimenu> menu in <xref
	linkend="Format-Menu" />.
	</para>
</sect2>


<sect2 id="menu-context-col-row-header">
	<title>The Context Menu for Column and Row Headers</title>
	<para>The Context Menu for Column and Row Headers</para>
		<figure id="menu-context-col-row-header.png">
		    <title>The Context Menu of a Row Header</title>
		    <screenshot>
		      <graphic fileref="figures/menu-context-col-row-header.png"></graphic>
		    </screenshot>
	    </figure>
	<para>The context menu which relates to column or row headers is similar to
	the context menu for the grid area. Both insert and delte operations are
	modified to operate explicitly on rows or on columns. An option is added
	which changes the height of rows or the width of columns. This context menu
	also provides a way to hide rows or columns and a way to reveal missing
	columns or rows.
	</para>


</sect2>


<sect2 id="menu-context-tabs">
	<title>The Context Menu menu for Worksheet Tabs</title>
		<para>The Context Menu menu for Worksheet Tabs.</para>
		<figure id="menu-context-tabs.png">
		    <title>The Context Menu.</title>
		    <screenshot>
		      <graphic fileref="figures/menu-context-tabs.png"></graphic>
		    </screenshot>
	    </figure>
	<para>The context menu for tabs provides the same functions as are provided 
	in the <guimenuitem>Sheet</guimenuitem> menu item in the
	<guimenu>Edit</guimenu> menu. These options are explained at the bottom of 
	<xref linkend="Edit-Menu" />.
	</para>


</sect2>


<sect2 id="menu-context-object">
	<title>The Context Menu for Embedded Objects and Components</title>
		<para>The Context Menu for Embedded Objects and Components.</para>
		<figure id="menu-context-object.png">
		    <title>The Context Menu</title>
		    <screenshot>
		      <graphic fileref="figures/menu-context-object.png"></graphic>
		    </screenshot>
	    </figure>
	<para>Since this menu gives access to functionality which is not part of
	Gnumeric, the menu entries will be different for each kind of object. This
	menu is accessible when first selecting on the embedded object or if the user
	clicks on the very border of the inserted object. All objects will provide a
	method to delete the object which will remove the object. Note that this
	operation will mostly not register into Gnumeric's history and therefore
	cannot easily be reversed.
	</para>


</sect2>



<sect2 id="menu-context-toolbars">
	<title>The Context Menu for Toolbars</title>
		<para>The Context Menu for Toolbars</para>
		<figure id="menu-context-toolbars.png">
		    <title>The Context Menu.</title>
		    <screenshot>
		      <graphic fileref="figures/menu-context-toolbars.png"></graphic>
		    </screenshot>
	    </figure>
	<para>The context menu for toolbars allows the user to configure toolbars.
	Each toolbar entry can have text associated with it or simply be an icon. The
	text only does not currently work in Gnumeric. The tooltips which are
	displayed by default can be turned off for this toolbar. The toolbar itself
	can be removed to save space. Finally the customize dialog can be launched
	which allows the user to configure these options for all the toolbars at
	once.
	</para>


</sect2>





</sect1>






      <!-- IF someone knows a more approriate way to document menu
      options, let me know. This seems a bit excessive, and the output
      from db2html is kind of lame -->
      
     <!-- <title><guimenu><accel>F</accel>ile</guimenu></title>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><guimenuitem><accel>N</accel>ew</guimenuitem></term>
	  <listitem><para>Create a new worksheet. This opens a new
	  worksheet in a window.</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><guimenuitem><accel>O</accel>pen</guimenuitem></term>
	  <listitem><para>Open an existing worksheet. A new window is
	  created with the file selected in it.</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><guimenuitem><accel>S</accel>ave</guimenuitem></term>
	  <listitem><para>Save the current worksheet. If the file has been
	  named and saved before, this will silently save the file to the
	  current filename. If it has not been saved before, this will
	  prompt for a filename and path.</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><guimenuitem>S<accel>a</accel>ve
	  as..</guimenuitem></term>

	  <listitem><para>Save a file with a new name. Save a newly created
	  file or save a file with a different name. </para></listitem>

	</varlistentry>
	
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><guimenuitem><accel>P</accel>lugins</guimenuitem></term>
	  <listitem><para>Open the plugins dialog. For loading, saving of
	  plugins. This shows the listing of pre loaded plugins and allows
	  the user the user to add more.</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><guimenuitem><accel>C</accel>lose</guimenuitem></term>
	  <listitem><para>Close the current worksheet.</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><guimenuitem><accel>Q</accel>uit</guimenuitem></term>
	  <listitem><para>Close the open worksheets and quit
	  Gnumeric</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	
      </variablelist>  
      
      
    </sect3> 
    
    <sect3>
      <title><guimenu><accel>E</accel>dit</guimenu></title>
      <variablelist>
	
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><guimenuitem><accel>C</accel>ut</guimenuitem></term>
	  <listitem><para>Remove the content in the currently selected cells
	  and save it.</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><guimenuitem>C<accel>o</accel>py</guimenuitem></term>
	  <listitem><para>Make a copy of the current selection to be pasted
	  later.</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><guimenuitem><accel>P</accel>aste</guimenuitem></term>
	  <listitem><para>Paste whatever is in the cut buffer at the
	  cursor.</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><guimenuitem>P<accel>a</accel>ste
	  Special</guimenuitem></term> <listitem><para>Paste from the cut
	  buffer, but with more options as to what to paste.  Useful for
	  pasting just format, or just values, etc.</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><guimenuitem><accel>S</accel>elect All</guimenuitem></term>
	  <listitem><para>Select every cell in the worksheet.</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><guisubmenu>Clear -&gt;</guisubmenu></term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <variablelist>
		<varlistentry>
		  <term><guimenuitem><accel>A</accel>ll</guimenuitem></term>
		  <listitem><para>Clear every cell.</para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
		  <term><guimenuitem><accel>F</accel>ormats</guimenuitem></term>
		  <listitem><para>Clear the format from selected
		  cells.</para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>
	      </variablelist>
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><guimenuitem><accel>G</accel>oto Cell</guimenuitem></term>
	  <listitem><para>Let the user specify a cell to "jump" to.</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </sect3>
    
    <sect3>
      <title><guimenu><accel>V</accel>iew</guimenu></title>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry><term><guimenuitem><accel>Z</accel>oom</guimenuitem></term>
	<listitem><para>Zoom in. To show a area of the spreadsheet in more
	detail.</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </sect3>
    
    <sect3>
      <title><guimenu><accel>I</accel>nsert</guimenu></title>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry><term><guimenuitem><accel>C</accel>ells</guimenuitem></term>
	  <listitem><para>Insert a new cell.</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry><term><guimenuitem><accel>R</accel>ows</guimenuitem></term>
	  <listitem><para>Insert a Row of cells.</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry><term><guimenuitem>C<accel>o</accel>lumns</guimenuitem></term>
	  <listitem><para>Insert a Column of cells.</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </sect3>
    
    <sect3>
      <title><guimenu>F<accel>o</accel>rmat</guimenu></title>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry><term><guimenuitem><accel>C</accel>ells</guimenuitem></term>
	<listitem><para>Open the cell format dialog. Used to change
	formatting, color, etc</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </sect3>
    
    <sect3>
      <title><guimenu><accel>H</accel>elp</guimenu></title>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry><term><guimenuitem>Cells</guimenuitem></term>
	  <listitem><para>View the online help for Gnumeric</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </sect3>-->
  <!-- end of menubar description -->
  

<!-- Keep this comment at the end of the file
Local variables:
mode: sgml
sgml-omittag:t
sgml-shorttag:t
sgml-minimize-attributes:nil
sgml-always-quote-attributes:t
sgml-indent-step:2
sgml-indent-data:t
sgml-parent-document:nil
sgml-exposed-tags:nil
sgml-local-catalogs:nil
sgml-local-ecat-files:nil
End:
-->      
